<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><xml><records><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>1</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The effects of hydration status and ice-water dousing on physiological and performance indices during a simulated soccer match in the heat.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Science &amp; Medicine in Sport</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Objectives: To assess the effects of hydration status and ice-water dousing on physiological and performance parameters.Design: Randomized, crossover.Methods: Twelve athletes (mean[M] ± standard deviation[SD]; age, 20 ± 1 years; height, 174 ± 8 cm; body mass, 72.1 ± 11.0 kg; VO2max 53.9 ± 7.3 mL⋅kg-1⋅min-1) completed four trials (euhydrated without dousing, hypohydrated without dousing, euhydrated with dousing, and hypohydrated with dousing), which involved intermittent treadmill running (five 15-minute bouts) in the heat (M ± SD; ambient temperature, 34.7 ± 2.1 °C; relative humidity, 46 ± 3%; wet-bulb globe temperature, 28.0 ± 0.4 °C). Participants also completed four cognitive, power, agility, reaction time, and repeated sprint performance tests throughout each trial. Heart rate (HR) and rectal temperature (Trec) were measured continuously. Repeated measures ANOVAs were performed to assess differences between physiological and performance variables. Alpha was set at ≤0.05, a priori. Data are reported as mean difference ± standard error (MD ± SE).Results: HR was significantly lower in euhydrated trials compared to hypohydrated trials, irrespective of dousing (8 ± 2 bpm; p = 0.001). Dousing did not significantly impact HR (p = 0.455) and there was no interaction between hydration and dousing (p = 0.893). Trec was significantly lower in euhydrated trials compared to hypohydrated trials (0.39 ± 0.05 °C, p &lt; 0.001), with no effect from dousing alone (p = 0.113) or the interaction of hydration and dousing (p = 0.848). Dousing resulted in improved sprint performance (11 ± 3 belt rotations, p = 0.007), while hydration status did not (p = 0.235).Conclusions: Athletes should aim to maintain euhydration during exercise in the heat for improved physiological function and cooling with ice-water dousing elicits additional performance benefits.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jsams.2021.05.013</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 11:56:44)(Select): Amb Cond: 35°C  46%
Ex Cond: intermittent non-motorised treadmill sprinting
Cooling Cond: euhydrated with water dousing, dehydrated with water dousing
Tc: rectal

Note: No control condition; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">723-728</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">24</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>2</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Brief in-play cooling breaks reduce thermal strain during football in hot conditions.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Science &amp; Medicine in Sport</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Objectives: The study examined if three feasible strategies involving additional in-play cooling periods attenuate the core (rectal) temperature rise during simulated football matches.Design: Four counterbalanced experimental trials in an environmental chamber set to 35 °C ambient temperature, 55% relative humidity, and 30 °C WBGT.Methods: Twelve healthy well-trained football players completed a regular simulated match (REG), regular simulated match with additional 3-min cooling periods at the 30-min mark of each half inclusive of chilled water consumption (COOLwater), regular simulated match with additional 3-min cooling periods at the 30-min mark of each half inclusive of chilled water consumption and the application of an ice towel around the neck (COOLtowel), regular simulated match with an extended (+5 min; total of 20-min) half-time break (HTextended).Results: The difference in rectal temperature change was significantly lower in the COOLwater (-0.25 °C), COOLtowel (-0.28 °C), and HTextended (-0.21 °C) trials in comparison to the REG (all p &lt; 0.05). Exercising heart rate and session rating of perceived exertion was lower in the COOLwater (-13 bpm; -1.4 au), COOLtowel (-10 bpm; -1.3 au), and HTextended (-8 bpm; -0.9 au) trials in comparison to the REG trial (all p &lt; 0.05). The cooling interventions did not significantly change skin temperature or thermal sensation in comparison to the REG (all p &gt; 0.05).Conclusions: All three cooling interventions attenuated core body thermal strain during simulated matches. The laboratory-based study supports the use of brief in-play cooling periods as a means to attenuate the rise in core temperature during matches in hot and humid conditions.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jsams.2019.04.009</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">912-917</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">22</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>3</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The Effects of Electric Fan Use Under Differing Resting Heat Index Conditions: A Clinical Trial.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Annals of Internal Medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cardiovascular strain was assessed using 3-lead electrocardiography to measure heart rate, systolic blood pressure was measured using sphygmomanometry (Tango, SunTech), and rate pressure product was calculated as heart rate multiplied by systolic blood pressure. Fan use in very hot, dry conditions worsened rectal temperature, rate pressure product, heart rate, whole-body sweat rate, and whole-body thermal comfort. Outcome variables are rectal temperature (A), rate pressure product (B), whole-body sweat rate (C), heart rate (D), SBP (E), and whole-body thermal comfort (F).</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.7326/M19-0512</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">675-677</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">171</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>4</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Optimal cooling strategies for players in Australian Tennis Open conditions.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Science &amp; Medicine in Sport</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Objectives: We compared the utility of four cooling interventions for reducing heat strain during simulated tennis match-play in an environment representative of the peak conditions possible at the Australian Open (45°C, &lt;10% RH, 475W/m2 solar radiation).Design: Nine trained males undertook four trials in a climate chamber, each time completing 4 sets of simulated match-play.Methods: During ITF-mandated breaks (90-s between odd-numbered games; 120-s between sets), either iced towels (ICE), an electric fan (FANdry), a fan with moisture applied to the skin (FANwet), or ad libitum 10°C water ingestion only (CON) was administered. Rectal temperature (Tre), mean skin temperature (Tsk), heart rate (HR), thermal sensation (TS), perceived exertion (RPE) and whole body sweating (WBSR) were measured.Results: After set 3, Tre was lower in ICE (38.2±0.3°C) compared to FANdry (38.7±0.5°C; p=0.02) and CON (38.5±0.5°C; p=0.05), while Tre in FANwet (38.2±0.3°C) was lower than FANdry (p=0.05). End-exercise Tre was lower in ICE (38.1±0.3°C) and FANwet (38.2±0.4°C) than FANdry (38.9±0.7°C; p&lt;0.04) and CON (38.8±0.5°C; p&lt;0.04).Tsk for ICE (35.3±0.8°C) was lower than all conditions, and Tsk for FANwet (36.6±1.1°C) was lower than FANdry (38.1±1.3°C; p&lt;0.05). TS for ICE and FANwet were lower than CON and FANdry (p&lt;0.05). HR was suppressed in ICE and FANwet relative to CON and FANdry (p&lt;0.05). WBSR was greater in FANdry compared to FANwet (p&lt;0.01) and ICE (p&lt;0.001).Conclusions: Fan use must be used with skin wetting to be effective in hot/dry conditions. This strategy and the currently recommended ICE intervention both reduced Tre by ∼0.5-0.6°C and Tsk by ∼1.0-1.5°C while mitigating rises in HR and TS.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jsams.2017.05.017</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-17 15:41:27)(Select): Cooling stimulus not applied for long enough. First application after WB1, Tc not hot enough; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">232-237</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">21</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>5</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The hybrid personal cooling system (PCS) could effectively reduce the heat strain while exercising in a hot and moderate humid environment.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ergonomics</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study aimed to examine the effectiveness of a hybrid personal cooling system (PCS) in mitigating body heat stain while exercising in a hot environment. Eight subjects underwent two trials: PCS and CON (i.e. no cooling). All trials were conducted at an air temperature of 36 ± 0.5 °C and RH = 59 ± 5%. The key findings demonstrated that the PCS could significantly reduce the core temperature, mean skin temperature, heart rate and physiological strain index during both exercise and recovery periods (p &lt; 0.05). Subjective perceptions were also significantly alleviated in PCS at the end of the exercise and during the recovery (p &lt; 0.05). Besides, the PCS could also bring remarkable benefits in lowering local skin temperatures and in improving perceptual sensations in both upper and lower body during both exercise and recovery periods (p &lt; 0.05). It was thus concluded that the hybrid PCS is effective in mitigating body heat strain while exercising in a hot environment. Practitioner Summary:In hot and humid environments, body heat dissipation through sweating is greatly restricted. Our newly developed hybrid PCS could effectively alleviate heat strain while exercising in hot environments. The findings contribute to the body of knowledge in improving the health and well-being of sportsmen while exercising in hot environments.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1080/00140139.2015.1105305</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 16:09:34)(Select): Not post-cooling, not practical; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1009-1018</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">59</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>6</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cooling Interventions Among Agricultural Workers: A Pilot Study.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Workplace Health &amp; Safety</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Background: Adverse health effects among agricultural workers due to chronic heat exposure have been characterized in the literature as not only due to high ambient temperatures but also due to intensive manual labor in hot and humid conditions. The aim of this study was to use biomonitoring equipment to examine the effectiveness of selected cooling devices at preventing agricultural workers from exceeding the core body temperature threshold of 38.0°C (Tc38) and attenuating heat-related illness symptoms. Methods: A convenience sample of 84 agricultural workers in Florida was randomized to one of four groups: (a) no intervention, clothing as usual; (b) cooling bandana; (c) cooling vest; and (d) both the cooling bandana and cooling vest. Biomonitoring equipment worn by the participants included core body temperature monitor and an accelerometer to capture physical activity. Findings: A total of 78 agricultural workers completed one intervention workday trial. Compared with the control group, the bandana group had lower odds of exceeding Tc38 (odds ratio [OR] = 0.7, 90% confidence interval [CI] = [0.2, 3.2]) and the vest group had higher odds of exceeding Tc38 (OR = 1.8, 90% CI = [0.4, 7.9]). The simultaneous use of cooling vest and bandana showed an effect little different from the control group (OR = 1.3, 90% CI = [0.3, 5.6]). Conclusion/Application to Practice: This is the first field-based study to examine cooling intervention among agricultural workers in the United States using biomonitoring equipment. This study found that using a bandana while working in a hot agricultural environment has the potential to be protective against exceeding the recommended Tc38 threshold.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1177/2165079920976524</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">315-322</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">69</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>7</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">In-Play Cooling Interventions for Simulated Match-Play Tennis in Hot/Humid Conditions.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medicine &amp; Science in Sports &amp; Exercise</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Purpose: This study aimed to assess the efficacy of different in-play cooling strategies for mitigating heat strain during simulated tennis match-play activity in a hot/humid environment representing the most extreme conditions during the US Open (36°C, 50% relative humidity). Methods: On three occasions, nine males completed an intermittent treadmill protocol with an exercise intensity and activity profile simulating a four-set tennis match, with 90-s breaks between odd-numbered games and 120-s breaks between sets, according to International Tennis Federation rules. During breaks, 1) the currently used cooling strategy--an ice-filled damp towel around the neck and a cold-damp towel on the head and thighs (ICE); 2) wetting of arms, neck, face, and lower legs with a sponge in front of an electric fan (FANwet); or 3) no cooling (CON) were applied. Rectal (Tre) and mean skin (Tsk) temperature and HR were measured throughout. Thermal sensation and RPE were assessed during breaks. Trials were terminated upon reaching a Tre ≥ 39.5°C or volitional exhaustion. Results: Seven, five, and one participant completed FANwet, ICE, and CON, respectively. By end set 1, ΔTre was lower in FANwet (0.92±C ± 0.15±C) compared with CON (1.09±C ± 0.09°C, P = 0.01), and by end set 2, ΔTre was lower (P &lt; 0.001) in FANwet (1.55°C ± 0.23°C) and ICE (1.59°C ± 0.17°C) compared with CON (1.99°C ± 0.19°C). Mean RPE (FANwet = 13.9 ± 2.2, ICE = 13.6 ± 1.8, CON = 16.6 ± 1.8), HR (FANwet = 163 ± 21, ICE 164 ± 22, CON = 175 ± 19 bpm), Tsk (FANwet = 36.56°C ± 0.69°C, ICE 36.12°C ± 0.44°C, CON = 37.21°C ± 0.42°C), and thermal sensation were lower in FANwet and ICE (P &lt; 0.05) compared with CON by end set 2. Conclusions: The currently recommended ICE strategy successfully mitigates thermal strain during simulated tennis match play in hot/humid conditions. The FANwet intervention is an equally effective alternative that may be more practical in limited resource settings.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1249/MSS.0000000000001183</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 15:46:22)(Select): Not post cooling; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">991-998</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">49</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>8</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">A Comparison of 2 Practical Cooling Methods on Cycling Capacity in the Heat.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Athletic Training (Allen Press)</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Context: Cooling the torso and neck can improve exercise performance and capacity in a hot environment; however, the proposed mechanisms for the improvements often differ. Objective: To directly compare the effects of cooling the neck and torso region using commercially available devices on exercise capacity in a hot environment (temperature = 358C 6 0.18C, relative humidity = 50.1% 6 0.7%). Design: Crossover study. Setting: Laboratory. Patients or Other Participants: Eight recreationally active, nonheat-acclimated men (age = 24 6 4 years, height = 1.82 6 0.10 m, mass = 80.3 6 9.7 kg, maximal power output = 240 6 25 W). Intervention(s): Three cycling capacity tests at 60% maximal power output to volitional exhaustion: 1 with no cooling (NC), 1 with vest cooling (VC), and 1 with a neck cooling collar (CC). Main Outcome Measure(s): Time to volitional exhaustion, rectal temperature, mean skin temperature, torso and neck skin temperature, body mass, heart rate, rating of perceived exertion, thermal sensation, and feeling scale were measured. Results: Participants cycled longer with VC (32.2 ± 9.5 minutes) than NC (27. 6 ± 7.6 minutes; P=.03; d=0.54) or CC (30.0 ± 8.8 minutes; P = .02; d = 0.24). We observed no difference between NC and CC (P = .12; d = 0.31). Neck and torso temperature and perceived thermal sensation were reduced with the use of cooling modalities (P &lt; .001), but no other variables were affected. Conclusions: Cycling capacity in the heat improved when participants used a commercially available cooling vest, but we observed no benefit from wearing a commercially available CC. The vest and the collar did not alter the heart rate, rectal temperature, skin temperature, or sweat-loss responses to the cycling bout.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.4085/1062-6050-51.8.07</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">525-532</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">51</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>9</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The effect of fan cooling on physiological responses during recovery following prolonged walking in the heat among male military reserve cadets</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">L&apos;effet du refroidissement par ventilateur sur les réponses physiologiques pendant la récupération après une marche prolongée dans la chaleur chez les cadets de la réserve militaire</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Objectives: Military personnel were adversely affected by the heat stress of 2016 El Niño phenomenon, which increases the risk of heatstroke. This study was to investigate the effect of mobile fan-cooling on physiological responses during recovery from prolonged walking in the heat. Equipment and methods: In a crossover trial, 12 male Military Reserve Officer Training Unit (ROTU) cadets (21.5 ± 1.0 years old, height 1.7 ± 0.1 m, bodyweight 62.2 ± 6.7 kg) walked on a motorised treadmill for one hour at 4 km.h−1 in a warm, humid environment (30 °C, 70% relative humidity), before randomly assigned to a fan cooling (FC) trial or passive cooling (PC) trial. Results: No significant differences were found in heart rate, rating of perceived exertion and thermal comfort during the recovery phase between the FC and PC trials, following prolonged walking in the heat. However, there was a significant time and trial interaction effect in the tympanic temperature of the participants across the recovery phase, between the two trials (p &lt; 0.05). In the FC trial, the tympanic temperature was significantly lower (p &lt; 0.05) compared to the PC trial after the 20 min recovery period. Mobile fan-cooling significantly reduces the tympanic temperature during recovery following prolonged walking in the heat.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.scispo.2021.05.001</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 10:44:16)(Select): Ex Cond: loaded treadmill walking 60 min
Amb Cond: 30°C 70%
Cooling Cond: fan cooling and no-fan control (both conditions in heat)
Tc: tympanic temperature

Note: invalid measure for Tc
; Kate Hutchins (2023-02-24 14:15:14)(Screen): tympanic temperature?; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">191-199</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">37</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>10</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Influence of postexercise cooling techniques on heart rate variability in men</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Experimental Physiology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The reduction of core body temperature (TC) is vitally important in the treatment of hyperthermia; however, little is known regarding the impact of cooling treatments on the autonomic control of heart rate (HR). The aim of the present study was to examine the influence of three field-based hyperthermia treatments on the neural control of HR via heart rate variability (HRV). Following exercise-induced hyperthermia (TC ∼40.0°C) in a warm environment (34.2 ± 0.5°C), nine healthy, active men were treated during recovery, in a randomized order, with intravenous cold saline infusion (IV) or ice packs (ICE) or fan cooling with intermittent water spray (FAN) for 40 min. During each treatment, HR dynamics via power spectral (VLF, LF, HF), Poincare plot (SD1, SD2), approximate entropy (ApEn) and short- (α1) and long-term (α2) fractal scaling analyses were determined every 10 min. At recovery onset, HR and TC were similar between treatments and were significantly reduced over the 40 min recovery period. During recovery, HR and α2 were significantly reduced from initial levels but were significantly greater for IV compared with ICE and FAN. In contrast, VLF, LF, HF, SD1, SD2 and ApEn increased during recovery, with all being significantly lower for IV compared with ICE and/or FAN. The present results demonstrated that IV, compared with ICE and FAN, resulted in significantly greater HR, reduced spectral and geometrical HRV, lower HR complexity and reduced long-term HR control, indicative of reduced vagal and/or increased sympathetic modulation. Specific treatments for exercise-induced hyperthermia may result in an altered sympathovagal balance that requires further examination. © 2009 The Physiological Society.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1113/expphysiol.2009.046714</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 10:53:13)(Select): Amb Cond: 34°C 62%
Ex Cond: treadmill walking/running protocol until Tc 40°C
Tc: pill
Cooling Cond: ice packs on armpits, groin, neck, industrial fan with water spray

Note: no control condition; Kate Hutchins (2023-02-24 14:59:01)(Screen): no control; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">695-703</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">94</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Rapid cooling techniques in joggers experiencing heat strain</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Science and Medicine in Sport</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study examined subjects that exercised on three occasions in a heated environment (WBGT = 39°C) until they experienced heat strain. Since morbidity and mortality due to heat injury increase with the duration of elevated core temperature, it is important that techniques to lower core temperature be evaluated. Following three exercise sessions, subjects underwent each of three core cooling treatments in random order: 1) Torso immersion in cool water, 2) Hands and feet immersion in cool water, and 3) Sit-in-shade with a 1.5mph breeze provided. Subjects (n=5) consistently reached peak rectal temperatures of 38.8 (±0.1) °C following each exercise bout in the heated environment. Torso immersion produced a significantly (p&lt;0.05) greater rate of decline in rectal temperature (0.25±0.10°C/min) than the hands and feet immersion technique (0.16±0.05°C/min) and the sit in the shade technique (0.11±0.04°C/min). After only 10 minutes of cooling, the differences among cooling techniques were evident. Similar trends were observed for mean heart rate readings, albeit not significant (p&gt;0.05). It was concluded that rectal temperatures can be reduced rapidly through the use of a cool water torso-immersion technique.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/S1440-2440(01)80026-8</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-14 17:23:51)(Select): Tc: rectal
Amb Cond: 41°C dry bulb
Ex Cond: 45 min run outside then 30 min run in chamber
Cooling Cond: hand and feet immersion (10-12°C), sitting in the shade with a fan (all conditions done in the chamber heat)
Tc end ex: 38.8°C

NOTE: shade and a fan is not control; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">160-167</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">4</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>12</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effects of head cooling on sweat rate in exercising subjects wearing protective clothing and mask for pesticide.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Applied human science : journal of physiological anthropology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study examined the effects of the head cooling on the sweat rates in 6 healthy female subjects at an ambient temperature of 28 degrees C and a relative humidity of 60%. The exercising subjects wore protective clothing and a mask for pesticide. Head cooling was made by putting frozen gel strips on the parietal and the front head which were held by a net-bandage (with cooling). On separate days, the same experiments were made without head cooling (without cooling). The total weight of the frozen gel strips was 250 g. After the subjects rested for 15 min in a chair, they repeated three times the work/rest schedule of 15 min exercise on a bicycle ergometer (50 W) followed by 5 min rest. Frozen gel strips were put on the head just before the first exercise bout. Main results were summarized as follows: 1) The forearm sweat rate, heart rate and the changes in Tre from the initial level (delta Tre) were significantly lower &quot;with cooling&quot; than &quot;without cooling&quot;. 2) The amount of sweat adhered to the clothing ensemble was significantly lower &quot;with cooling&quot; than &quot;without cooling&quot;. 3) The changes in Tty from the initial level (delta Tty) tended to be clearly lower &quot;with cooling&quot; than &quot;without cooling&quot;. 4) Skin temperatures of the forehead and the cheek under a mask tended to be lower &quot;with cooling&quot; than &quot;without cooling&quot;. 5) Subjective sensation ratings seemed to be improved in most subjects &quot;with cooling&quot;. Thus, it was concluded that head cooling seemed to be more effective in reducing thermal strain in working subjects wearing the protective clothing and a mask for pesticide at hot environments.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.2114/jpa.15.149</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 15:07:52)(Select): Tc not high enough (I estimate), and cooling provided prior to exercise; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">149-154</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">15</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>13</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effectiveness of rest pauses and cooling in alleviation of heat stress during simulated fire...</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ergonomics</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study examined whether cooling a fire-fighter with a high velocity fan, during 10 min rest pauses between, and following, 10 min work periods, decreases heat stress during repetitive fire-fighting activity. Twelve professional fire-fighters (mean age 31.8 +/- 6.7 years) completed two, 40 min work/recovery trials in an environmental chamber at 40 degrees C and 70% relative humidity (RH). One trial was termed an enhanced recovery (ER) trial and the other was termed a normal recovery (NR) trial. In both conditions subjects wore full protective clothing and breathing apparatus during the work. In the ER trial a subject removed his protective coat and sat in front of a fan during each recovery period. In the NR trial a subject merely unbuckled his coat and was not cooled by a fan during either recovery period. The group mean metabolic cost (VO2), and the exercise and recovery heart rates were significantly lower (p &lt; or = 0.05) during the ER trial than in the NR condition. Group mean rectal temperature increased by 1.5 degrees C in the NR trial but by only 0.8 degree C during the ER trial. The latter group&apos;s more effective cooling indicates the potential of fan cooling to reduce physiological strain and decrease the risk of heat exhaustion during repetitive fire-fighting activity. The results suggest that a fire-fighter&apos;s short 10 min exposure to heavy work in a hot environment of 40 degrees C and 70% RH produces minimal heat stress in a healthy fire-fighter. However, a period of fire-fighting exposure greater than 10 min without adequate rest and cooling may lead to a significant accumulation of heat stress and fatigue during further fire-fighting activity, irrespective of physical prowess.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1080/001401399185667</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-02-24 12:36:25)(Screen): &apos;high velocity fan&apos;; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">299-299</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">42</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>14</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effects of oral rehydration and external cooling on physiology, perception, and performance in hot, dry climates</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Scandinavian Journal of Medicine and Science in Sports</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Only limited research evaluates possible benefits of combined drinking and external cooling (by pouring cold water over the body) during exercise. Therefore, this study examined cold water drinking and external cooling on physiological, perceptual, and performance variables in hot, dry environments. Ten male runners completed four trials of walking 90min at 30% VO2max followed by running a 5-km time trial in 33±1°C and 30±4% relative humidity. Trials examined no intervention (CON), oral rehydration (OR), external cooling (EC), and oral rehydration plus external cooling (OR+EC). Investigators measured rectal temperature, skin temperatures, heart rate, thirst, thermal sensation, and ratings of perceived exertion (RPE). Oral rehydration (OR and OR+EC) significantly lowered heart rate (P&lt;0.001) and thirst (P&lt;0.001) compared with nondrinking (CON and EC) during low-intensity exercise. External cooling (EC and OR+EC) significantly reduced chest and thigh temperature (P&lt;0.001), thermal sensation (P&lt;0.001), and RPE (P=0.041) compared with non-external cooling (CON and OR) during low-intensity exercise. Performance exhibited no differences (CON=23.86±4.57min, OR=22.74±3.20min, EC=22.96±3.11min, OR+EC=22.64±3.73min, P=0.379). Independent of OR, pouring cold water on the body benefited skin temperature, thermal sensation, and RPE during low-intensity exercise in hot, dry conditions but failed to influence high-intensity performance. © 2012 John Wiley &amp; Sons A/S.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1111/j.1600-0838.2012.01510.x</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-17 18:48:42)(Select): horrible to understand. seems like they dont apply cooling after only but during and after.; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">e115-e124</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">22</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>15</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">To cool, but not too cool: that is the question-immersion cooling for hyperthermia.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medicine &amp; Science in Sports &amp; Exercise</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">INTRODUCTION:: Patient cooling time can impact upon the prognosis of heat illness. Although ice-cold-water immersion will rapidly extract heat, access to ice or cold water may be limited in hot climates. Indeed, some have concerns regarding the sudden cold-water immersion of hyperthermic individuals, whereas others believe that cutaneous vasoconstriction may reduce convective heat transfer from the core. It was hypothesized that warmer immersion temperatures, which induce less powerful vasoconstriction, may still facilitate rapid cooling in hyperthermic individuals. METHODS:: Eight males participated in three trials and were heated to an esophageal temperature of 39.5 degrees C by exercising in the heat (36 degrees C, 50% relative humidity) while wearing a water-perfusion garment (40 degrees C). Subjects were cooled using each of the following methods: air (20-22 degrees C), cold-water immersion (14 degrees C), and temperate-water immersion (26 degrees C). RESULTS:: The time to reach an esophageal temperature of 37.5 degrees C averaged 22.81 min (air), 2.16 min (cold), and 2.91 min (temperate). Whereas each of the between-trial comparisons was statistically significant (P &lt; 0.05), cooling in temperate water took only marginally longer than that in cold water, and one cannot imagine that the 45-s cooling time difference would have any meaningful physiological or clinical implications. CONCLUSION:: It is assumed that this rapid heat loss was due to a less powerful peripheral vasoconstrictor response, with central heat being more rapidly transported to the skin surface for dissipation. Although the core-to-water thermal gradient was much smaller with temperate-water cooling, greater skin and deeper tissue blood flows would support a superior convective heat delivery. Thus, a sustained physiological mechanism (blood flow) appears to have countered a less powerful thermal gradient, resulting in clinically insignificant differences in heat extraction between the cold and temperate cooling trials.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1249/mss.0b013e31817eee9d</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 16:16:40)(Select): Air con was the &apos;control&apos; so probably cant use in Meta-A; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1962-1969</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">40</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>16</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Alleviation of heat strain by cooling different body areas during red pepper harvest work at WBGT 33°C</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Industrial Health</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The purpose of the present study was to examine the effects of different types of personal cooling equipments (PCE) on the alleviation of heat strain during red pepper harvest simulated in a climatic chamber. The experiment consisted of eight conditions: 1) Control, 2) Neck cooling scarf A with a cooling area of 68 cm2, 3) Neck cooling scarf B (cooling area 154 cm2), 4) Brimmed hat with a frozen gel pack, 5) Cooling vest (cooling area 606 cm2), 6) Hat+Neck Scarf B, 7) Hat+Vest, and 8) Hat+Neck Scarf B+Vest. Twelve subjects worked a red pepper harvest simulated in a climatic chamber of WBGT 33°C. The result showed that rectal temperature (Tre) was effectively maintained under 38°C by wearing PCE. Mean skin temperature (T̄sk) and heart rate (HR) became more stable through wearing PCE. When wearing the &apos;Hat+Scarf B+Vest&apos;, particularly, T̄sk and HR quickly decreased to the comfort level during the mid-rest stage. We confirmed that the vest with a cooling area of only 3.3% body surface area (BSA) was effective in alleviating heat strain in a simulated harvest work. Furthermore, the heat strain of farm workers can be considerably eliminated by the combination of the cooling vest, a scarf, and a brimmed hat, with the total cooling area of 4.2% BSA.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.2486/indhealth.46.620</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">620-628</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">46</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>17</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effectiveness of Ice-Sheet Cooling Following Exertional Hyperthermia.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Military Medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Background: The procedure of wrapping a heat casualty in ice-water soaked bed sheets to reduce core temperature has received little investigation, despite the practice and recommendation for its use in some military settings. Thus, the purpose of this study was to investigate the cooling efficacy of ice-sheet cooling (ISC) following exertional hyperthermia.Methods: 13 (11 males, 2 females) participants (age = 23 ± 3 years, height = 176.5 ± 10.3 cm, mass = 78.6 ± 15.3 kg, body fat = 19.6 ± 8.6%, and body surface area = 1.95 ± 0.22 m2) volunteered to complete 2 randomized, crossover design trials on an outdoor recreation field (34.4 ± 1.4°C, 54.4 ± 4.1% relative humidity). Each trial consisted of exercise (self-paced 400-m warm-up, 1,609-m run, and 100-m sprints) followed by 15 minutes of either lying supine in the shade with no treatment (control [CON]) or being treated with ice-water soaked sheets wrapped around their body (ISC). Physiological (rectal temperature [Tre], heart rate, mean-weighted skin temperature) and perceptual measures (thermal sensation, rating of perceived exertion) were assessed after each exercise protocol, every 3 minutes during treatment, and every 5 minutes during recovery.Findings: By design, there were no differences during exercise between ISC and CON for Tre (p = 0.16), skin temperature (p = 0.52), heart rate (p = 0.62), thermal sensation (p = 0.89), or rating of perceived exertion (p = 0.99). There were greater decreases in Tre at 3 (ISC 0.33 ± 0.26°C vs. CON 0.03 ± 0.30°C, p = 0.01) and 6 minutes (ISC 0.47 ± 0.27°C vs. CON 0.30 ± 0.19°C, p = 0.05) of treatment; however, the overall rate of cooling was not different between trials (CON 0.05 ± 0.02°C/min vs. ISC 0.06 ± 0.02°C/min, p = 0.72). Skin temperature (Tsk) was significantly reduced from 3 minutes (ISC 34.4 ± 1.7°C vs. CON 36.6 ± 0.5°C, p = 0.007) through 15 minutes (ISC 32.4 ± 1.5 vs. CON 36.1 ± 0.4°C, p &lt; 0.001) of treatment. There was a trend for lower heart rate with ISC (p = 0.051). Thermal sensation was reduced from 3 minutes of treatment (ISC 3.5 ± 0.9 vs. CON 4.5 ± 0.6, p = 0.002) through 15 minutes (ISC 2.8 ± 1.0 vs. CON 3.9 ± 0.4, p = 0.005).Discussion: ISC does not provide effective reduction in Tre following exertional hyperthermia compared to no treatment. However, perceptual benefits may warrant the use of ISC in settings where rapid reductions in core temperature are not a concern (i.e., recovery from exercise). Thus, clinicians should continue to utilize validated techniques (i.e., cold-water immersion) for the treatment of exertional heat illnesses.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.7205/MILMED-D-17-00057</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 12:12:22)(Select): Thoughts on this being viable at home? At this scale it is too much? Is it close enough to ice towels to include? Maybe we can have 2x ice towels (low surface coverage, and high surface coverage?); Kate Hutchins (2023-03-11 18:05:30)(Select): Amb cond: outdoors 34°C 55%
Tc: rectal
Ex Cond: warm up, mod-high int. 1600m run, rest, 50 m sprints until Tc &gt;39°C
Cooling Cond: control - lying in shade, ice-sheet cooling - wrapped in ice water soaked (3°C) bed sheets in shade and rotated
Tc end ex: 39.2°C
; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">e1951-e1957</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">182</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>18</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">A modified Kalman filter-based model for core temperature estimation during exercise and recovery with/without personal cooling interventions</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Thermal Biology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">One of the most important parameters to consider while analysing heat related illness is the human body core temperature. It is therefore required to monitor real-time core temperature in an ambulatory situation for industrial workers, athletes, military personnel, and a variety of other people. As conventional methods of monitoring core temperature are unsuitable for ambulatory use or prohibitively expensive, it is necessary to develop a reliable, inexpensive and non-invasive method for real-time measurement of core temperature. Kalman filter based models for core temperature estimation are found promising to meet these requirements. In this work, we have highlighted one of the major shortcomings of the existing extended Kalman filter model and proposed a modification. The modified extended Kalman filter based model has better performance compared to the existing model in estimating the core temperature as it considers two separate measurement models for exercise and recovery periods. The proposed modified model is validated using human trials data which includes participants wearing regular clothing and different types of personal cooling clothing. It is found that the proposed modified model can predict core temperature more accurately (bias= −0.03 to −0.06°C, LoA=±0.14 – ±0.32°C, and RMSE=0.09–0.16°C) as compared to the existing model (bias=−0.03 – 0.08°C, LoA=±0.26 – ±0.33°C, and RMSE=0.14°C–0.18°C). Personal cooling intervention minimises core temperature rise significantly and thus helps in heat stress mitigation. It is observed that the proposed modified model can estimate core temperature more accurately for cooling intervention cases and intermittent working cases as compared to the existing model. It can be used effectively in an ambulatory setting, but for situations where higher accuracy is required and invasiveness of the method is not a concern, direct contact method of core temperature is always preferred as the proposed model has varying accuracy levels between individuals.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jtherbio.2022.103307</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 15:24:54)(Select): Model based and not original data from this study; </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">109</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>19</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Efficiency of three cooling methods for hyperthermic military personnel linked to water availability</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Applied Ergonomics</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Purpose: Three feasible cooling methods for treatment of hyperthermic individuals in the military, that differed considerably in water volume needed (none to ~80 L), were evaluated. Methods: Ten male soldiers were cooled following exercise-induced hyperthermia (rectal temperature (Tre) ∼39.5 °C) using ventilation by fanning (1.7 m s−1), ventilation by fanning (1.7 m s−1) while wearing a wet t-shirt (250 mL–27 °C water) and tarp assisted cooling with oscillations (80 L of 27.2 ± 0.5 °C water; TACO). Results: Cooling rates were higher using TACO (0.116 ± 0.032 °C min−1) compared to ventilation (0.065 ± 0.011 °C min−1, P&lt;0.001) and ventilation in combination with a wet t-shirt (0.074 ± 0.020 °C min−1, P=0.002). Time to cool (TTC) to Tre=38.2 °C for TACO was shorter (14 ± 4 min) compared to ventilation only (20 ± 5 min; P=0.018), but not to ventilation while wearing a wet t-shirt (18 ± 6 min; P=0.090). Conclusions: TACO may be an acceptable, efficient and feasible cooling method in case of exertional heat stroke. However, in case of limited water availability, transportat should be prioritized, and cooling of any form should be implemented while waiting for and during transport.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.apergo.2022.103700</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-14 17:03:58)(Select): Amb Cond: 30°C 65%
Ex Cond: treadmill walking
Cooling Cond: whole-body ventilation, ventilation and wet t-shirt
Tc: rectal
Note: No control condition; </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">102</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>20</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Thermal respite for pedestrians in overheated urban environments – Introduction of a dynamic analysis of outdoor thermal comfort</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sustainable Cities and Society</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Superimposition of global warming on urban heat islands is making outdoor cooling infrastructure critical to the maintenance of walkability of many cities. How to better arrange thermal respite (cooling infrastructure) to maximise pedestrians’ thermal comfort is still unclear. In this study, the thermal discomfort accumulating during episodic exercise in outdoor heat was compared to the charging of a capacitor. Skin temperature and core temperature responses were collected from a sample of human participants (n=24) who were exposed to bouts of simulated urban heat stress, while exercising on an ergometer at an intensity corresponding to a brisk walk. Thermal respite (wind and/or shade) was provided to the participants to discharge accumulated heat load after they reached a specific threshold of thermal discomfort. We found that the thermal discomfort capacitor of most participants (75%) became fully charged (‘pleasant’ → ‘intolerable’) after a 0.4 °C increment in mean body temperature, and its discharge required a 0.7 °C degree-minute decrement in mean skin temperature. The comfort capacitor analogy provides an estimate of the intensity and duration of cooling respite required by pedestrians during brief exposures to overheated urban climates. This provides guidance on engineering interventions to ameliorate overheated urban microclimates. © 2022</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.scs.2022.104149</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 16:36:41)(Select): Doubt Tc got to 38 but cant tell...; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-11 18:29:58)(Select): Ex Cond: cycling (duration?)
Amb Cond: sim three radiation int. (low, med, high) ~28°C 45%
Tc: pill
Cooling Cond: wind (fan), shade (turn of solar lamps), wind + shade
Tc end ex: ?; </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">86</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>21</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Temperate-Water Immersion as a Treatment for Hyperthermic Humans Wearing American Football Uniforms.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Athletic Training (Allen Press)</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Context: Cold-water immersion (CWI; 10°C) can effectively reduce body core temperature even if a hyperthermic human is wearing a full American football uniform (PADS) during treatment. Temperate-water immersion (TWI; 21°C) may be an effective alternative to CWI if resources for the latter (eg, ice) are unavailable. Objective: To measure rectal temperature (Trec) cooling rates, thermal sensation, and Environmental Symptoms Questionnaire (ESQ) scores of participants wearing PADS or shorts, undergarments, and socks (NOpads) before, during, and after TWI. Design: Crossover study. Setting: Laboratory. Patients Or Other Participants: Thirteen physically active, unacclimatized men (age = 22 ± 2 years, height = 182.3 ± 5.2 cm, mass = 82.5 ± 13.4 kg, body fat = 10% ± 4%, body surface area = 2.04 ± 0.16 m²). Intervention(s): Participants exercised in the heat (40°C, 50% relative humidity) on 2 days while wearing PADS until Trec reached 39.5°C. Participants then underwent TWI while wearing either NOpads or PADS until Trec reached 38°C. Thermal sensation and ESQ responses were collected at various times before and after exercise. Main Outcome Measure(S): Temperate-water immersion duration (minutes), Trec cooling rates (°C/min), thermal sensation, and ESQ scores. Results: Participants had similar exercise times (NOpads = 38.1 ± 8.1 minutes, PADS = 38.1 ± 8.5 minutes), hypohydration levels (NOpads = 1.1% ± 0.2%, PADS = 1.2% ± 0.2%), and thermal sensation ratings (NOpads = 7.1 ± 0.4, PADS = 7.3 ± 0.4) before TWI. Rectal temperature cooling rates were similar between conditions (NOpads = 0.12°C/min ± 0.05°C/min, PADS = 0.13°C/min ± 0.05°C/min; t12 = 0.82, P = .79). Thermal sensation and ESQ scores were unremarkable between conditions over time. Conclusions: Temperate-water immersion produced acceptable (ie, &gt;0.08°C/min), though not ideal, cooling rates regardless of whether PADS or NOpads were worn. If a football uniform is difficult to remove or the patient is noncompliant, clinicians should begin water-immersion treatment with the athlete fully equipped. Clinicians should strive to use CWI to treat severe hyperthermia, but when CWI is not feasible, TWI should be the next treatment option because its cooling rate was higher than the rates of other common modalities (eg, ice packs, fanning).</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.4085/1062-6050-52.5.05</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-17 15:52:07)(Select): Would just use the non-pads condition; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">747-752</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">52</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>22</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Evaluation of 2 Heat-Mitigation Methods in Army Trainees.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Athletic Training (Allen Press)</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Context: Heat injury is a significant threat to military trainees. Different methods of heat mitigation are in use across military units. Mist fans are 1 of several methods used in the hot and humid climate of Fort Benning, Georgia. Objectives: To determine if (1) the mist fan or the cooling towel effectively lowered participant core temperature in the humid environment found at Fort Benning and (2) the mist fan or the cooling towel presented additional physiologic or safety benefits or detriments when used in this environment. Design: Randomized controlled clinical trial. Setting: Laboratory environmental chamber. Patients or Other Participants: Thirty-five physically active men aged 19 to 35 years. Intervention(s): (1) Mist fan, (2) commercial cooling towel, (3) passive-cooling (no intervention) control. All treatments lasted 20 minutes. Participants ran on a treadmill at 60% VO2max. Main Outcome Measure(s): Rectal core temperature, heart rate, thermal comfort, perceived temperature, perceived wetness, and blood pressure. Results: Average core temperature increased during 20 minutes of cooling (F1,28 = 64.76, P &lt; .001, ηp² = 0.70), regardless of group (F1,28 = 3.41, P = .08, ηp² = 0.11) or condition (F1,28 &lt; 1.0). Core temperature, heart rate, and blood pressure did not differ among the 3 conditions. Perceived temperature during 20 minutes of cooling decreased (F1,30 = 141.19, P &lt; .001, ηp² = 0.83) regardless of group or condition. Perceived temperature was lower with the mist-fan treatment than with the control treatment (F1,15=7.38, P=.02, ηp²=0.32). The mist-fan group perceived themselves to be cooler even at elevated core temperatures. Conclusions: The mist fan and cooling towel were both ineffective at lowering core temperature. Core temperature continued to increase after exercise in all groups. The mist fan produced feelings of coolness while the core temperature remained elevated, possibly increasing the risk of heat illness.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.4085/1062-6050-51.10.13</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">936-945</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">51</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>23</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effectiveness of a head wash cooling protocol using non-refrigerated water in reducing heat stress.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Occupational Health</style></secondary-title></titles><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 14:52:47)(Select): TC &lt;38C during only opportunity for comparison (i.e. Ex1); Kate Hutchins (2023-03-15 16:48:41)(Select): Amb Cond: 35°C 60%
Ex Cond: 20 min cycling (75W) then 15 min rest repeated 3x
Cooling Cond: pour 2L water (23°C) on head during the rest periods and control (no details)
Tc: rectal and oesph
Tc end ex: ~37.5°C after first 20 min bout

Note: Tc did not elevate very much in first exercise bout; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">251-261</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">50</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>24</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effect of cold water immersion on repeat cycling performance and thermoregulation in the heat.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Sports Sciences</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">To assess the effect of cold water immersion and active recovery on thermoregulation and repeat cycling performance in the heat, ten well-trained male cyclists completed five trials, each separated by one week. Each trial consisted of a 30-min exercise task, one of five 15-min recoveries (intermittent cold water immersion in 10 degrees C, 15 degrees C and 20 degrees C water, continuous cold water immersion in 20 degrees C water or active recovery), followed by 40 min passive recovery, before repeating the 30-min exercise task. Recovery strategy effectiveness was assessed via changes in total work in the second exercise task compared with that in the first. Following active recovery, a mean 4.1% (s = 1.8) less total work (P = 0.00) was completed in the second than in the first exercise task. However, no significant differences in total work were observed between any of the cold water immersion protocols. Core and skin temperature, blood lactate concentration, heart rate, rating of thermal sensation, and rating of perceived exertion were recorded. During both exercise tasks there were no significant differences in blood lactate concentration between interventions; however, following active recovery blood lactate concentration was significantly lower (P &lt; 0.05; 2.0 +/- 0.8 mmol . l(-1)) compared with all cold water immersion protocols. All cold water immersion protocols were effective in reducing thermal strain and were more effective in maintaining subsequent high-intensity cycling performance than active recovery.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1080/02640410701567425</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 16:18:40)(Select): Will need Tc data from authors (report Tb); Kate Hutchins (2023-02-24 12:32:37)(Screen): no control; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">431-440</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">26</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>25</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Testing the effectiveness of techniques for reducing heat strain in Royal Navy nuclear, biological and chemical cleansing stations&apos; teams.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of the Royal Naval Medical Service</style></secondary-title></titles><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 15:23:10)(Select): No hot enough before cooling applied; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">27-34</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">89</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>26</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cold-water immersion and iced-slush ingestion are effective at cooling firefighters following a simulated search and rescue task in a hot environment.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Applied Physiology, Nutrition &amp; Metabolism</style></secondary-title></titles><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1139/apnm-2014-0038</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-11 18:13:11)(Select): Cooling Cond: CWI - 15°C water to umbilicus (19°C), slush - 7g/kg (19°C), control seated (19°C)
Ex Cond: loaded sim search/rescue rest period (19°C)
Tc: pill
Amb Cond: chamber 105°C
Tc end ex: ~39°C

Note: would not consider immersion or slushy as practical cooling methods to maybe exclude ; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1159-1166</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">39</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>27</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Palm cooling does not reduce heat strain during exercise in a hot, dry environment.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Applied Physiology, Nutrition &amp; Metabolism</style></secondary-title></titles><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1139/H10-040</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 10:14:52)(Select): Yes, but only the WB condition (which is water immersion of the hands); </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">480-489</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">35</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>28</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Prevention of heat strain by immersing the hands and forearms in water.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of the Royal Naval Medical Service</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The effectiveness of hand immersion in water at 10 degrees C, 20 degrees C and 30 degrees C as a technique for reducing heat strain in Royal Navy (RN) personnel has been investigated at the Institute of Naval Medicine (INM). Four subjects exercised at a moderate work rate, whilst wearing fire fighting clothing in an environmental chamber at 40 degrees C. The subjects reached heat strain safety limits within 45 minutes of commencing work at which point they rested in the heat for 30 minutes whilst they underwent one of four experimental conditions: without intervention (control); or with their hands immersed in water at 10 degrees C, 20 degrees C or 30 degrees C. The experiment was repeated on a further three days so that the subjects undertook each experimental condition in a balanced randomised order. During the control condition without hand immersion the subjects were unable to cool. Immersion of the hands in water (at 10 degrees C, 20 degrees C or 30 degrees C) significantly (P &lt; 0.05) lowered body core (auditory canal) temperature within ten minutes. Assessing the effectiveness of this technique by the initial rates of core temperature reduction, revealed that immersion of the hands was more effective the colder the water. Following 20 minutes of hand immersion mean core temperature had dropped from 38.5C to: 36.9(standard deviation 0.19) degrees C, 37.3(0.18) degrees C, and 37.8(0.10) degrees C, in 10 degrees C, 20 degrees C and 30 degrees C water respectively. Cooling powers estimated from changes in mean body temperature were 334, 307 and 113 watts using 10 degrees C, 20 degrees C and 30 degrees C water respectively. These results indicate that hand immersion in water at a temperature of between 10 degrees C and 30 degrees C is an efficient means of cooling heat stressed personnel who have been exercising. This simple and effective technique may be applied to many industrial and military tasks to reduce heat strain, lower the risk of heat injury, and increase safe total work times in the heat. For the RN, hand immersion could be used in fire fighting, damage control and NBC operations where personnel alternately work and rest.</style></abstract><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-14 16:49:51)(Select): Cooling Cond: Hand immersion (10°C, 20°C, 30°C) and control (all conditions still in the heat)
Ex Cond: loaded stepping exercise until Tc 38.5°C
Amb Comd: 40°C 50%
Tc: auditory canal ... Exclude?
; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">26-30</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">83</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>29</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Heat loss caused by cooling the feet</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aviation Space and Environmental Medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The effect of cooling the feet to alleviate heat strain was examined. Subjects, wearing chemical protective clothing, immersed their feet in water at temperatures of 10, 15, 20, 25, and 30°C after sitting for 120 rain at 35°C. Heat lost via the feet ranged from 151 ± 15 to 55 ± 5 W, being greater in the colder water. In a second experiment, subjects wearing chemical protective clothing and specially designed water-cooled socks walked on a treadmill at 5 km · h-1 and 2.5% grade for 90 min at 35°C. Four conditions were examined: no cooling, cooling throughout the walk, cooling during the last 60 min, and cooling during the first 30 min. Rectal and skin temperatures and heart rates were monitored. Cooling for the first 30 min had little effect on the measured parameters, however, when core temperatures rose to over 37.5°C, cooling during the last 60 min significantly attenuated the increase in body temperatures and heart rates. We conclude that this method could be used to alleviate heat strain.</style></abstract><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-17 15:39:58)(Select): Cooling during work; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">232-237</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">66</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>30</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The effect of hand immersion on body temperature when wearing impermeable clothing.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of the Royal Naval Medical Service</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The effects of hand immersion on body temperature have been investigated in men wearing impermeable NBC clothing. Six men worked continuously at a rate of approximately 490 J. sec-1 in an environmental temperature of 30 degrees C. Each subject was permitted to rest for a period of 20 minutes when their aural temperature reached 37.5 degrees C, and again on reaching 38 degrees C, and for a third time on reaching 38.5 degrees C (three rest periods in total). Each subject completed three experimental conditions whereby, during the rest periods they either: a. Did not immerse their hands (control). b. Immersed both hands in a water bath set at 25 degrees C. c. Immersed both hands in water at 10 degrees C. Physiological measures of core temperature, skin temperature and heart rate were recorded at intervals throughout the experiment. Measures of mean aural temperature and mean skin temperature were significantly (P less than 0.05) reduced if hands were immersed during these rest periods, compared to non immersion. As a result, the total work time of subjects was extended when in the immersed conditions by some 10-20 minutes within the confines of the protocol. It is concluded that this technique of simple hand immersion may be effective in reducing heat stress where normal routes to heat loss are compromised.</style></abstract><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 10:06:56)(Select): Need to think if we include this or just note that this was cooling while wearing encapsulating/impermeable clothing; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">41-47</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">77</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>31</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The Effectiveness of a Standardized Ice-Sheet Cooling Method Following Exertional Hyperthermia.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Military Medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Introduction: Exertional heat illnesses remain a major threat to military service members in the United States and around the world. Exertional heat stroke (EHS) is the most severe heat illness, characterized by core hyperthermia and central nervous system dysfunction. Per current Army regulations, iced-sheet cooling (ISC) is the recommended immediate treatment for heat casualties in the field, but concerns have been raised regarding the efficacy of this approach. Thus, the purpose of this study was to quantify the cooling rate of ISC following exertional hyperthermia.Materials and Methods: We utilized a randomized crossover design with 2 experimental trials. In both trials, exertional hyperthermia was induced by walking (3.5 mph at 5% grade) on a treadmill in an environmental chamber (40 °C, 30% RH) for up to 3 hours or until core body temperature reached 39.2 °C. After the walking portion, individuals either received ISC (experimental trial) or cooling and rested supine in the same environmental conditions for 30 minutes with no ISC (control trial). For ISC, bed sheets soaked in ice water were applied (per Army guidance) at the neck, chest, and groin with another sheet covering the body. Sheets were rotated and resoaked every 3 minutes until core temperature decreased to &lt;38.0 °C.Results: By design, participants finished exercise with increased core temperature (38.8 ± 0.39 °C vs. 38.90 ± 0.34 °C, ISC and control trials, P = 1.00). The ISC trial provided significantly (P = .023) greater cooling rates, 0.068 °C/min 95% confidence interval [CI; 0.053, 0.086], compared to the control trial, 0.047 °C/min 95% CI [0.038, 0.056]. Additionally, the time to decrease to less than 38.0 °C was significantly (P = .018) faster in the ISC trial (median = 9.3 minutes) compared to the control trial (median = 26.6 minutes).Conclusion: ISC increases the cooling rate of those recovering from exertional hyperthermia. With the observed cooling rate, we can extrapolate that ISC would reduce core temperature by ∼2 °C within 30 minutes during a case of EHS. We conclude that ISC provides a safe and effective alternative for the field where cold water immersion resources may not be readily available.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1093/milmed/usac047</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 12:13:56)(Select): Thoughts on this being viable at home? At this scale it is too much? Is it close enough to ice towels to include? Maybe we can have 2x ice towels (low surface coverage, and high surface coverage?); Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 10:58:34)(Select): Tc: pill
Ex Cond: treadmill walking for 3hr or until Tc 39.2°C
Amb Cond: 40°C 30%
Cooling Cond: ice sheet cooling (ice soaked sheets on major artery sites, and over body + replaced freq) and control (both conditions in the heat)
Tc end ex: 38.8°C; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">e1017-e1023</style></pages></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>32</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The elderly&apos;s physiological and perceptual responses to cooling during simulated activities of daily living in UK summer climatic conditions.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Public Health (Elsevier)</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The elderly are the most at-risk population for heat-related illness and mortality during the periods of hot weather. However, evidence-based elderly-specific cooling strategies to prevent heat-illness are limited. The aim of this investigation was to quantify the elderly&apos;s physiological and perceptual responses to cooling through cold water ingestion (COLD) or an L-menthol mouth rinse (MENT) during simulated activities of daily living in UK summer climatic conditions. Randomised, controlled repeated measures research design. A total of ten participants (men n = 7, women n = 3: age; 69 ± 3 yrs, height; 168 ± 10 cm, body mass; 68.88 ± 13.72 kg) completed one preliminary and three experimental trials; control (CON), COLD and MENT. Experimental trials consisted of 40 min rest followed by 30 min of cycling exercise at 6 metabolic equivalents and a 6-min walk test (6MWT), within a 35 °C, 50% relative humidity environment. Experimental interventions (every 10 min); cold water (4 °C) ingestion (total of 1.5L) or menthol (5 ml mouth swill for 5 s, menthol concentration of 0.01%). Peak rectal temperature (T re) was significantly (P &lt; 0.05) lower in COLD compared with CON (−0.34 ± 0.16 °C) and MENT (−0.36 ± 0.20 °C). End exercise heart rate (HR) decreased in COLD compared with CON (−7 ± 9 b min−1) and MENT (−6 ± 7 b min−1). There was no difference in end exercise thermal sensation (TS) (CON; 6.1 ± 0.4, COLD; 6.0 ± 0.4, MENT; 6.4 ± 0.6) or thermal comfort (TC) (CON; 4 ± 1, COLD; 4 ± 1, MENT; 4 ± 1) between trials. The participants walked significantly further during the COLD 6MWT compared with CON (40 m ± 40 m) and MENT (40 m ± 30 m). There was reduced physiological strain in the COLD 6MWT compared with CON (T re ; −0.21 ± 0.24 °C, HR; −7 ± 8 b min−1) and MENT (T re ; −0.23 ± 0.24 °C, HR; −4 ± 7 b min−1). The elderly have reduced physiological strain (T re and HR) during activities of daily living and a 6MWT in hot UK climatic conditions, when they drink cold water. Furthermore, the elderly&apos;s perception (TS and TC) of the hot environment did not differ from CON at the end of exercise with COLD or MENT interventions. Menthol provided neither perceptual benefit to exercise in the heat nor functional gain. The TS data indicate that elderly may be at increased risk of heat illness, due to not feeling hot and uncomfortable enough to implement physiological strain reducing strategies such as cold-water ingestion. Article in a Tweet:</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.puhe.2021.01.016</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 16:24:08)(Select): Heatwave?; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1-9</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">193</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>33</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">A Preliminary Study of the Effect of Dousing and Foot Immersion on Cardiovascular and Thermal Responses to Extreme Heat.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">JAMA: Journal of the American Medical Association</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study assesses the effects of self-dousing and foot immersion on heart rate, core temperature, and thermal discomfort of healthy volunteers randomized to simulated hot and humid vs nonhumid conditions.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1001/jama.2019.13051</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-14 17:16:35)(Select): Cooling Cond: control (consume 22°C water), foot to mid-calf immersion (22°C) and water consumption protocol and self dousing across chest, arms, back, legs, face ad lib (22°C).
Ex Cond: 120 min exposure to environment
Amb Cond: 40°C 50% or 47°C 10%
Tc: rectal
Tc end ex: ?

Note: no exercise but might be classified as heat wave sim; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1411-1413</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">322</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>34</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effects of Forearm vs. Leg Submersion in Work Tolerance Time in a Hot Environment While Wearing Firefighter Protective Clothing.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Occupational &amp; Environmental Hygiene</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study compared physiological responses and total work tolerance time following forearm submersion (FS) or leg submersion (LS) in cool water, after performing work in a hot environment while wearing fire fighting protective clothing (FPC). Participants walked at 3.5 mph on a treadmill in a hot environment (WBGT 32.8 ± 0.9°C) until a rectal temperature (Trec) of 38.5°C was reached. Participants were then subjected to one of two peripheral cooling interventions, in a counterbalanced order. Forearms or lower legs were submerged in water (16.9 ± 0.8°C) for a total of 20 min, followed by a work tolerance trial. Results indicated no significant difference (p = 0.052) between work tolerance time (LS = 21.36 ± 5.35 min vs. FS = 16.27 ± 5.56 min). Similarly, there was no significant difference for Trec (p = 0.65), heart rate (HR) (p = 0.79), mean skin temperature (Tsk) (p = 0.68), and rating of perceived exertion (RPE) (p = 0.54). However, LS ratings of thermal comfort (RTC) at Minute 14 (p = 0.03) were significantly lower for LS (10 ± 1) vs. FS (12 ± 1). Results indicate little difference between FS and LS for physiological measures. Despite a lack of statistical significance a 5-min (24%) increase was found during the work tolerance time following LS.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1080/15459624.2011.590743</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">473-477</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">8</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>35</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Heart rate and body temperature responses to extreme heat and humidity with and without electric fans.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">JAMA: Journal of the American Medical Association</style></secondary-title></titles><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1001/jama.2015.153</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 15:22:01)(Select): Looks like the letter prior to full-publication in study #2475; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">724-725</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">313</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>36</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cooling strategies for firefighters: Effects on physiological, physical, and visuo-motor outcomes following fire-fighting tasks in the heat</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Thermal Biology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Objectives: Due to the nature of firefighting, most effective cooling interventions to reduce heat strain and optimise performance are not practically viable. This study quantified the effects of two practical cooling strategies, co-designed with subject-matter experts, on physiological strain and physical, perceptual, and visuo-motor performance during simulated firefighting in the heat. Design: Randomised cross-over. Methods: On three occasions 14 firefighters completed an 80-min simulation in a hot-humid environment (32.0[0.9]°C, 59[3]%RH) including two 20-min firefighting tasks in full protective clothing, each followed by 20-min seated recovery. Recovery involved removal of protective clothing and one of three interventions – control (CON; ambient-temperature water consumption), basic (BASIC; cool-water consumption, ambient-forearm immersion/towels, fan), and advanced (ADV; ice-slushy consumption, cool-forearm immersion/ice packs, misting-fan). Thermal (core temperature) and cardiovascular (heart rate, arterial pressure) responses were measured throughout, whilst physical (handgrip/balance), visuo-motor (reaction time/memory recall) and perceptual (fatigue/thermal sensation/comfort) measures were assessed pre- and post-trial. Results: Compared to CON, core temperature was lower in BASIC and ADV following the second task (ADV: 37.7[0.4]; BASIC: 38.0[0.4]; CON: 38.3[0.4]°C) and recovery protocol (ADV: 37.5[0.3]; BASIC: 37.7 [0.3] CON: 38.3[0.4]°C). This was paralleled by lowered heart rate, rate pressure product, and thermal sensation following the recovery protocols, in the ADV and BASIC condition compared to CON (p &lt; .05). No physical or visuo-motor outcomes differed significantly between conditions. Conclusion: Whilst these observations need to be extended to field conditions, our findings demonstrate that two novel cooling interventions developed in collaboration with subject-matter experts offered benefits for reducing thermal strain and optimising firefighter safety.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jtherbio.2022.103236</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 14:57:02)(Select): Too many cooling practices at once.; </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">106</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>37</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effect of cooling strategies on overall performance of a hybrid personal cooling system incorporated with phase change materials (PCMs) and electric fans</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Thermal Biology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The effect of four cooling strategies on cooling performance of a hybrid personal cooling system (HPCS) incorporated with phase change materials (PCMs) and electric fans in a hot environment (i.e., Tair = 36 ± 0.5 °C, RH = 59 ± 5%) was investigated. Twelve healthy young male participants underwent four 90-min trials comprising 70 min walking and 20 min resting periods. Cooling strategies adopted in this work were CON (control), PCM-control (PCMs were removed at the end of exercise), Fan-control (fans were switched OFF during the initial 20 min) and PCM&amp;Fan-control (fans were turned ON after 20 min exercising and PCMs were removed after the 70-min exercise). Results demonstrated that the control of electric fans could suppress the mean skin temperature rise to 34.0 °C by over 15 min and also cut down the energy consumption of the HPCS from 15.6 W h to 12.1 W h over the entire 90-min trials. Thus, it is recommended that fans should be turned off at the beginning of hot exposure and switched on once participants felt warm. Our findings also showed that the removal of fully melted PCM packs from the HPCS could enhance the evaporative cooling effect brought about by air circulation. The removal of melted PCMs significantly reduced the physical load by 37.3% and ratings of perceived exertion (RPE) were decreased by 3.5–4.2 RPE units. This could also help quickly restore the PCM energy for future usage. In summary, cooling strategies demonstrated in this work could improve HPCS&apos;s overall cooling performance on workers while working in the studied hot environment.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jtherbio.2020.102655</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-06 17:24:50)(Screen): rectal temp?; Kate Hutchins (2023-02-24 15:51:34)(Screen): only include control and fan only conditions; </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">92</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>38</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effect of a cooling strategy combining forearm water immersion and a low dose of ice slurry ingestion on physiological response and subsequent exercise performance in the heat</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Thermal Biology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Although numerous studies have shown the benefits of cooling strategies for reducing thermal strain and subsequent exercise performance in the heat, few studies have focused on a combination of external and internal cooling. Therefore, the purpose of the present study was to examine the impact of a cooling strategy combining forearm water immersion and a low dose of ice slurry ingestion on physiological response and subsequent exercise performance in the heat. Eight non-heat-acclimated males participated in this study. After reaching a rectal temperature of 38.5 °C through a bout of cycling exercise in the heat (35 °C, 60% relative humidity), the participants were subjected to one of the following four conditions for a 15-min period: W: forearm cooling; ICE: ice slurry (–1 °C) ingestion; MIX: both W and ICE, and CON: no cooling intervention. After the intervention, the participants performed time to exhaustion (TTE) cycling exercise at 75% V˙O2max. The rate of decrease in rectal temperature in the MIX group was significantly lower than that in the CON group from 6 min to the end of the cooling intervention period (P &lt; 0.05). In addition, mean skin temperature, heart rate, physiological strain index, and perceptual strain were significantly reduced for MIX and W compared with ICE and CON. However, TTE was longer for ICE compared with the other interventions. These results suggest the effectiveness of the newly developed cooling strategy combining external and internal cooling for reducing thermal strain in a short-term recovery period during exercise in the heat.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jtherbio.2020.102530</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-17 18:53:10)(Select): Forearm immersion trial only; </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">89</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>39</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Intermittent wetting clothing as a cooling strategy for body heat strain alleviation of vulnerable populations during a severe heatwave incident</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Thermal Biology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Many documented studies have demonstrated the human mortality rate increases during severe heatwaves. There remains a need for further explore ecologically valid cooling strategies to alleviate body heat strain during extreme heatwaves. The main aim of this work was to explore whether intermittent wetting clothing can be served as an ecologically valid cooling strategy to mitigate heat stress on inactive vulnerable populations not having access to air-conditioning during a severe heatwave. Ten young male subjects underwent two 90-min separate trials: a dry clothing trial (i.e., CON) and a wetted clothing cooling trial (i.e., WEC). A set of light summer wear was chosen and intermittently wetted by tap water at intervals of every 30 min. Physiological and perceptual responses of subjects were examined and compared. All trials were performed in a chamber with an air temperature of 43 ± 0.5 °C, RH= 57 ± 5% and an air velocity of 0.15 ± 0.05 m/s (WBGT=37.35 °C). Results demonstrated that WEC, compared with CON, could significantly reduce both the mean skin temperature and the core temperature throughout the 5–90th min and 25–90th min of the trial, respectively (p &lt; 0.05). Besides, WEC could also remarkable reduce local skin temperatures at those body sites covered by wet clothing (p &lt; 0.05). In comparison, no significant difference was found between WEC and CON on perceptual responses. Further, it was also found from PHS simulations that conditions with a partial water vapour pressure ≤ 3.1–3.5 kPa would not induce pronounced core temperature rises at 43 °C. Finally, it may be concluded that intermittent wetting clothing could be served as an ecologically valid cooling strategy to reduce thermophysiological strain of vulnerable populations while seating during humid heatwaves and thereby improve their health and safety.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jtherbio.2018.11.012</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 16:08:05)(Select): Heat wave? I am leaning yes, to discuss; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 11:13:19)(Select): Amb Cond: 43°C 57% seated exposure 90 min
Cooling Cond: wetted clothing every 30 mins (water 25°C) versus not wetted (control)
Tc: pill
Tc end exposure: 38.9 control and 38.6 cooling

NOTE: similar to heat wave sim and percooling; Kate Hutchins (2023-02-28 14:37:19)(Screen): kind of heatwave simulation study; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">33-41</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">79</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>40</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">An investigation of thermophysiological responses of human while using four personal cooling strategies during heatwaves</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Thermal Biology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study aimed to examine how human body thermophysiologically responds to four commonly used cooling strategies (i.e., electric fan cooling [AirFC], evaporative cooling clothing [EvapCC], hybrid cooling, i.e., evaporative cooling clothing combined with electric fan cooling [EvapCC&amp;AirFC] and liquid cooling clothing [LiqCC]) during heatwaves. An adaptive ‘Newton’ manikin was used to predict human physiological responses while using these four cooling systems. Four heatwave conditions were selected, i.e., 36 °C, 33% RH (hot-dry, denoted as HD1), 36 °C, 67% RH (hot-humid, denoted as HH1), 40 °C, 27% RH (extremely hot-dry, denoted as HD2) and 40 °C, 54% RH (extremely hot-humid, denoted as HH2). A metabolic rate of 2.5 METs was used to mimic moderate work while sitting at either home or outdoors. AirFC was only found to bring cooling benefits in HD1 and HH1. EvapCC was effective in both HD1 and HD2. LiqCC showed similar cooling benefits compared to EvapCC in HD1 and HD2, and also displayed cooling benefits in HH1. EvapCC&amp;AirFC was discovered to be most effective cooling strategy in the four studied conditions. Concerning their practical applications, EvapCC&amp;AirFC was recommended to inactive populations while staying indoors during different heatwave conditions, and EvapCC and LiqCC were more suitable for active populations while working/exercising in hot-dry conditions and hot-humid conditions, respectively.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jtherbio.2017.05.007</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 16:30:36)(Select): Thermal manikin do we keep?; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-11 17:53:30)(Select): Cooling Cond: fan, evap cooling clothing, evap cooling clothing + fan, liquid cooling clothing
Thermal manikin
4x heat wave conditions
Ex Con: 2 METs; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">37-44</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">70</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>41</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Firefighter feedback during active cooling: A useful tool for heat stress management?</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Thermal Biology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Monitoring an individual&apos;s thermic state in the workplace requires reliable feedback of their core temperature. However, core temperature measurement technology is expensive, invasive and often impractical in operational environments, warranting investigation of surrogate measures which could be used to predict core temperature. This study examines an alternative measure of an individual&apos;s thermic state, thermal sensation, which presents a more manageable and practical solution for Australian firefighters operating on the fireground. Across three environmental conditions (cold, warm, hot &amp; humid), 49 Australian volunteer firefighters performed a 20-min fire suppression activity, immediately followed by 20min of active cooling using hand and forearm immersion techniques. Core temperature (Tc) and thermal sensation (TS) were measured across the rehabilitation period at five minute intervals. Despite the decline in Tc and TS throughout the rehabilitation period, there was little similarity in the magnitude or rate of decline between each measure in any of the ambient conditions. Moderate to strong correlations existed between Tc and TS in the cool (0.41, p&lt;0.05) and hot &amp; humid (0.57, p&lt;0.05) conditions, however this was resultant in strong correlation during the earlier stages of rehabilitation (first five minutes), which were not evident in the latter stages. Linear regression revealed TS to be a poor predictor of Tc in all conditions (SEE=0.45-0.54°C) with a strong trend for TS to over-predict Tc (77-80% of the time). There is minimal evidence to suggest that ratings of thermal sensation, which represent a psychophysical assessment of an individual&apos;s thermal comfort, are an accurate reflection of the response of an individual&apos;s core temperature. Ratings of thermal sensation can be highly variable amongst individuals, likely moderated by local skin temperature. In account of these findings, fire managers require a more reliable source of information to guide decisions of heat stress management.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jtherbio.2014.10.003</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 15:38:41)(Select): No control. B and C conditions look like viable inclusions; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">66-71</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">46</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>42</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Strategies to combat heat strain during and after firefighting</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Thermal Biology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The use of phase change cool vests during firefighting and the efficacy of 20 min cold water hand immersion following such activity was investigated. Core temperature was unaffected by cool vest wear, as was skin temperature, sweat rate and heart rate, and cannot be recommended for use. There was a trend for core temperature decline to be accelerated by hand immersion after 10 min, but this trend disappeared after 20 min. Hand immersion had no substantive effect on core temperature attenuation in firefighters who had partially removed their clothing, consumed cold water and sat in a cool and ventilated room. © 2007 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jtherbio.2006.12.001</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 12:18:52)(Select): What are we doing about the control for this? 15C room vs 15C room+hand immersion is not great as it is like combination cooling (i.e. AC + immersion); Kate Hutchins (2023-03-08 17:48:01)(Select): STUDY 3
Ex Cond: sim fire rescue activities heated and unheated conditions
Cooling Cond: hand/forearm immersion - 10°C (15°C room), seated recovery (15°C room)
Tc: pill
Tc @ End Ex: 38.5°C; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">109-116</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">32</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>43</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effect of water temperature on cooling efficiency during hyperthermia in humans</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Applied Physiology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">We evaluated the cooling rate of hyperthermic subjects, as measured by rectal temperature (Tre), during immersion in a range of water temperatures. On 4 separate days, seven subjects (4 men, 3 women) exercised at 65% maximal oxygen consumption at an ambient temperature of 39°C until Tre increased to 40°C (45.4 ± 4.1 min). After exercise, the subjects were immersed in a circulated water bath controlled at 2, 8, 14, or 20°C until Tre returned to 37.5°C. No difference in cooling rate was observed between the immersions at 8, 14, and 20°C despite the differences in the skin surface-to-water temperature gradient, possibly because of the presence of shivering at 8 and 14°C. Compared with the other conditions, however, the rate of cooling (0.35 ± 0.14°C/min) was significantly greater during the 2°C water immersion, in which shivering was seldom observed. This rate was almost twice as much as the other conditions (P &lt; 0.05). Our results suggest that 2°C water is the most effective immersion treatment for exercise-induced hyperthermia.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1152/japplphysiol.00541.2002</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 15:18:23)(Select): May be duplicate data for the other similar included study (need to check); Kate Hutchins (2023-03-15 16:52:12)(Select): Tc: rectal
Amb Cond: 38.8°C 36% but increased to 58%
Ex Cond: 65% Vo2 treadmill
Cooling Cond: whole-body immersion 2, 8, 14 and 20°C

Note: no control condition ; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1317-1323</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">94</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>44</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Fanning as an alternative to air conditioning – A sustainable solution for reducing indoor occupational heat stress</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Energy and Buildings</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">We assessed whether increasing airflow with an electric fan is similarly effective as decreasing air temperature with air cooling (AC) in preventing heat-related reductions in productivity, and elevations in body temperatures and discomfort in a warm/humid indoor environment. In 48 experimental trials, we compared the reduction in the human heat stress response of sixteen participants during 135 min of intermittent arm ergometry at a fixed heart rate of 110 beats min −1 , from a simulated tropical environment (HOT; 30 °C, 70%RH; wind &amp;lt; 0.2 m s −1 ) to that observed with either a, (i) 7 °C reduction in air temperature (AC; 23 °C, 70%RH, wind &amp;lt; 0.2 m s −1 ); or (ii) facilitated airflow (FAN; 30 °C, 70%RH, wind = 4.2 m s −1 ). Cumulative work was similarly improved (+11%) by FAN compared to AC. Likewise, reductions in rectal temperature, thermal sensation, and thermal discomfort were similar with the two different cooling strategies. Sweat losses in the FAN trial were higher compared to AC but lower than HOT without fanning. In conclusion, fanning offers an effective method for alleviating thermal stress and preventing productivity losses for workers exposed to environmental heat. Moving air instead of chilling it may require a little more sweating, but it can save electricity and hence lower greenhouse gas emissions compared to AC. © 2019 Elsevier B.V.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.enbuild.2019.03.037</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-02-24 15:08:44)(Screen): no control; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">92-98</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">193</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>45</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effects Of Active Cooling Following Simulated Military Work In The Heat...2021 ACSM Annual Meeting &amp; World Congresses [Virtual], June 1 -5, 2021</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medicine &amp; Science in Sports &amp; Exercise</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Wearing military personal protective gear (PPE) under heat stress can significantly inhibit heat dissipation and result in elevated heat strain. The body&apos;s inability to effectively cool while wearing PPE warrants the use of active cooling strategies to improve work capacity and protect military personnel from exertional heat illnesses. PURPOSE: Examine physiological and perceptual effects of mist-fan cooling, forearm immersion cooling, and passive cooling following repeated bouts of military-simulated work wearing military PPE. METHODS: 12 male participants [age:27±6yrs; maximal oxygen consumption(VO2max):57.6±6.2ml/kg/min; body mass:78.3±8.1kg] performed three 50-min bouts of treadmill running and walking (40-70% VO2max) in the heat (36°C, 30% relative humidity). Each exercise bout was followed by 30-min of cooling. Participants completed 3 trials on separate days. The intervention included the utilization of one of three different cooling modalities during the cooling blocks of the trial. The experimental conditions were: 1) mist-fan cooling (MC), 2) forearm immersion (FC), and passive cooling (PC). Rectal temperature (Trec), heart rate (HR), rating of perceived exertion (RPE), thirst, thermal sensation (TS), and fatigue were measured following each exercise bout and cooling block. Two-way repeated measures AN0VAs identified differences between experimental conditions. 0ne-way AN0VA with Bonferroni correction determined the location of significant differences. Significance was set at p ≤ 0.05. RESULTS: Trec immediately following the 3rd bout of exercise for MC, FC, and PC trials was 38.8±0.54°C, 38.74±0.48°C, and 38.5±0.54°C, respectively (p&gt;0.05). There were no significant differences in Trec, HR, thirst, or fatigue, at any time points between conditions. Following cooling block 2, TS was significantly higher in the PC condition (4.6±1.03) versus FC condition (3.9±1.5;p=0.024). RPE was higher in the PC condition (6.7±1.4) versus FC following cooling block 3 (6.41±0.66;p=0.033). CONCLUSION: Although FC reduced TS and RPE during cooling blocks, FC and MC provided no additional cooling benefit compared to PC. Military safety personnel must explore other cooling strategies or mixed-methods to improve cooling potential for warfighters wearing PPE in combat and training settings.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1249/01.mss.0000763316.31667.14</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-17 18:27:08)(Select): If included we need more data and contact authors; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-14 17:10:30)(Select): Conference? - 2021 ACSM Annual Meeting &amp; World Congresses; Kate Hutchins (2023-02-24 12:06:24)(Screen): have considered &apos;passive cooling&apos; as control trial; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">351-351</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">53</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>46</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effects of heat acclimation on hand cooling efficacy following exercise in the heat.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Sports Sciences</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study examined the separate and combined effects of heat acclimation and hand cooling on post-exercise cooling rates following bouts of exercise in the heat. Seventeen non-heat acclimated (NHA) males (mean ± SE; age, 23 ± 1 y; mass, 75.30 ± 2.27 kg; maximal oxygen consumption [VO2max], 54.1 ± 1.3 ml·kg−1·min−1) completed 2 heat stress tests (HST) when NHA, then 10 days of heat acclimation, then 2 HST once heat acclimated (HA) in an environmental chamber (40°C; 40%RH). HSTs were 2 60-min bouts of treadmill exercise (45% VO2max; 2% grade) each followed by 10 min of hand cooling (C) or no cooling (NC). Heat acclimation sessions were 90–240 min of treadmill or stationary bike exercise (60–80% VO2max). Repeated measures ANOVA with Fishers LSDpost hoc(α &lt; 0.05) identified differences. When NHA, C (0.020 ± 0.003°C·min−1) had a greater cooling rate than NC (0.013 ± 0.003°C·min−1) (mean difference [95%CI]; 0.007°C [0.001,0.013],P = 0.035). Once HA, C (0.021 ± 0.002°C·min−1) was similar to NC (0.025 ± 0.002°C·min−1) (0.004°C [−0.003,0.011],P = 0.216). Hand cooling when HA (0.021 ± 0.002°C·min−1) was similar to when NHA (0.020 ± 0.003°C·min−1) (P = 0.77). In conclusion, when NHA, C provided greater cooling rates than NC. Once HA, C and NC provided similar cooling rates.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1080/02640414.2016.1192671</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Shannon Rutherford (2023-01-23 17:51:35)(Screen): not  sure what Hand cooling is.. ; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">828-834</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">35</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>47</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Preliminary Observations on the use of Short-term Ambient Cooling during a Daylong Extreme Heat Exposure on Autophagy in Older Adults</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">FASEB Journal</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aging is associated with impairments in autophagy, which is an integral cellular survival mechanism. Our ongoing work indicates that heat stress may worsen this age-related impairment after a daylong (9-hour) passive heat exposure (40°C) as assessed in peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC). This was paralleled by a greater elevation in body core temperature in older compared to young adults, which together with diminished autophagy, may contribute to compromised health during extreme heat events (EHE). National and international health agencies widely recommend the use of short-term ambient cooling (STAC; e.g., visiting a cooling center) to protect the health of vulnerable individuals during an EHE; however, its effects on body core temperature and autophagic function are currently unclear. We therefore sought to extend upon our previous work by assessing if STAC would mitigate rises in body core temperature, and thus, the heat-related decline in autophagy in older adults during a simulated EHE. We evaluated the hypothesis that in parallel to a reduction in body core temperature, autophagy would be preserved in PBMCs from older adults exposed to STAC during the EHE when compared to those without access to a cool room. To assess this hypothesis, as part of a larger study evaluating thermal strain in older adults, autophagy was characterized in PBMCs of 7 older adults (mean [SD] 71 [5] years; 3 women) prior to and following a 9-h heat exposure (40°C, ∼15% relative humidity [RH]), with 2 h of exposure to a cool room (∼23°C; STAC) for hours 5 and 6. Responses were compared with 10 older adults (71 [3] years; 2 women) who had previously participated in a prolonged 9-h exposure to an EHE (40°C, ∼15% RH). Changes in autophagy were assessed via Western blot for autophagy-related proteins p62 and microtubule associated protein 1 light chain 3 beta (LC3)-II. All proteins were normalized to β-actin and reported as fold changes relative to their respective baseline. Rectal temperature (Tre ) was measured throughout and expressed as a change from baseline. Data were compared between-groups using unpaired t-tests (α=0.05). Following the first 4 h of heat exposure, Tre did not differ between groups (both ∼0.9 [0.3]°C; p&gt;0.99), although following STAC (hour 6) Tre was lower (by 0.8 [0.4]°C; p&lt;0.001) than the non-cooled group. Again, however, no significant difference between groups was observed at the end of the 9-h exposure (both ∼0.9 [0.2]°C; p&gt;0.99). Despite this, p62 protein at end-exposure (9 h) was lower in the STAC group when compared to the noncooled group (0.78 [0.51] vs. 2.57 [2.19]; p=0.03) and this was accompanied by a reduction in LC3-II (0.72 [0.33] vs. 2.13 [1.83]; p=0.04). Given, LC3-II and p62 undergo lysosomal degradation (indicative of normal autophagic function), our preliminary findings indicate STAC may reduce the time spent in a hyperthermic state, thereby preserving autophagy during a simulated EHE in older adults. Further work is required to evaluate if alternate cooling strategies (i.e., fan use) can preserve autophagic function in older adults during prolonged heat stress.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1096/fasebj.2021.35.S1.03744</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-12 18:02:43)(Select): Conference (abstract); Kate Hutchins (2023-02-28 16:40:16)(Screen): simulated heat wave study; </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">35</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>48</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Use of a Water-soaked Garment, with and without an Electric Fan, to Mitigate Thermal Strain in Older Individuals under Heat Wave Conditions</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">FASEB Journal</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">As average global surface temperatures are projected to rise, and heat waves are expected to increase in frequency, duration, and intensity, exposure to high levels of heat stress will occur with greater regularity. Older individuals are particularly vulnerable to heat stress, evidenced by excess hospitalizations and mortality among individuals aged &gt;60 years. With the continue rise of electricity costs coupled with vulnerable regions that do not have easy access to air conditioning, it is imperative to find alternative cooling strategies that are costeffective and accessible for older individuals. The present study evaluated whether wearing a water-soaked t-shirt, with and without electric fan use, mitigates thermal and cardiovascular strain under heat wave conditions. Nine healthy older individuals (68 ± 4 years; five females) completed three, 120-min heat exposures (42.4 ± 0.2°C, 34.2 ± 0.9% relative humidity) on separate occasions while wearing either a dry t-shirt (CON), a t-shirt soaked with 500 ml of tap water (WET), or a t-shirt soaked with 500 ml of tap water while facing an electric fan forcing air at 2.4 ± 0.4 m/s (WET+FAN). Measurements included core and mean skin temperatures, evaporative mass loss, heart rate, and blood pressure. The rise in core temperature was attenuated by ∼0.3°C in WET compared to DRY and WET+FAN during the first hour of heat stress (P &lt; 0.01). At 120 min, the rise in core temperature remained attenuated by ∼0.2 °C in WET compared to DRY (P=0.0016), while other comparisons were not different. After the 120-min heat exposure, changes in body mass, which largely reflect evaporation of sweat and moisture trapped in clothing, were greatest in WET+FAN, followed by WET, and then DRY (P &lt; 0.01). However, sweat losses were lowest in WET, followed by DRY, and then WET+FAN (P &lt; 0.01). Heart rate was lower during the first hour in WET vs. DRY, and at 30 min only in WET vs. WET+FAN (P &lt; 0.01). No differences in mean arterial pressure were found (P = 0.51). In conclusion, simply wearing a water-soaked t-shirt is an effective heat management strategy to mitigate thermal and cardiovascular strain and lower sweat losses in older people exposed to heat wave conditions. Conversely, the cooling benefits of a water-soaked t-shirt are eliminated when used in combination with a fan.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1096/fasebj.2020.34.s1.02438</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-12 17:48:59)(Select): Abstract (conference); Connor Forbes (2023-01-25 10:18:49)(Screen): Very relevant!; </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">34</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>49</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Defining acceptable cold-water immersion times for the treatment of exertional hyperthermia when rectal temperature measurements are not available</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">FASEB Journal</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Exertional hyperthermia is most effectively treated with immediate whole-body cold-water immersion to rapidly cool the body to the safe rectal temperature (Tre) of 38.6°C, which is the cooling limit recommended to negate any risk associated with overcooling hyperthermic individuals. However, the safe use of cold-water immersion is reliant on real-time measurement of Tre to identify the appropriate immersion time, which is often unavailable in emergency situations. The purpose of this study was to determine appropriate immersion times for the immediate treatment of exertional hyperthermia for a range of water temperatures (2°C to 26°C) and following a treatment delay (20 min and 40 min) to guide emergency management in the absence of continuous Tre measurements. Data were extracted from seven published studies (143 experimental sessions) involving 79 participants (65 males, 14 females; age: 26 ± 6 years; height: 177 ± 9 cm; weight, 76.9 ± 13.0 kg; body fat: 17.3 ± 6.9%; peak oxygen consumption: 56.9 ± 7.9 mL/kg/min). In each study, individuals rendered hyperthermic (Tre 39.5-40.0°C) during exercise in the heat were treated immediately with immersion in water at 2°C, 8°C, 14°C, or 26°C. Separate study conditions assessed cold-water immersion (2°C) following a 20 and 40 min treatment delay. From these data, receiver operating characteristics curves were used to define acceptable cooling times (time for Tre to reach 38.6°C) for each condition (all p&lt;0.05). Our analysis revealed that 9 min would be the recommended cooling time for immersion in water temperatures ranging from 2°C to 8°C (average sensitivity at 2°C: 0.84, average sensitivity at 8°C: 0.82; average specificity at 2°C: 0.82, average specificity at 8°C: 0.96). For immersion in water temperatures between 14°C and 20°C, the suggested cooling time was 10 min (average sensitivity: 0.80; average specificity: 0.76), whereas it was 14 min at 26°C (average sensitivity: 0.73; average specificity: 0.79). When the gold standard water temperature of 2°C is available, a cooling time of 11 min is recommended if immersion is delayed between 20 and 40 min (average sensitivity: 0.84; average specificity: 0.94). Our results provide the first clinical guidance to health practitioners for the emergency treatment of exertional hyperthermia using water immersion at a range of water temperatures and following a treatment delay when Tre measurements are unavailable..</style></abstract><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 15:16:18)(Select): Need data but looks ok.; Aaron Bach (2023-03-12 18:10:43)(Select): Conference (abstract); </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">32</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>50</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The effect of fan use and folic acid supplementation on thermal and cardiovascular strain in healthy aged humans during heat exposure</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">FASEB Journal</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Attenuated heat loss and altered cardiovascular adjustments during heat stress are considered important contributing factors to the increased prevalence of death in aged individuals during heat waves. Interventions aimed at reducing thermal and cardiovascular strain during heat stress in the aged are lacking. We therefore examined if fan use (by improving sweat evaporation) or folic acid supplementation (by improving cutaneous vasodilation) can mitigate thermal and cardiovascular strain during heat exposure, as well as modify the limit of thermal compensability in healthy aged humans. Six healthy older individuals (69 ± 3 y, 166 ± 12 cm, 72 ± 16 kg, 2 males/4 females) rested in a thermal chamber at a temperature of 42°C and a relative humidity initially maintained at 30%. After a 30 min baseline period, relative humidity was increased in 2% steps every 5 min until a relative humidity of 70% was reached (100 min). The protocol was performed with no intervention (CON), with a fan that provided ∼4 m/s of air velocity (FAN), and following 6 weeks of folic acid supplementation (FOLIC). Esophageal (Tes) and mean skin (Tsk) temperatures, local forearm cutaneous vascular conductance (laser-Doppler, CVC), forearm vascular conductance (Doppler ultrasound, FVC), local sweat rate (ventilated capsule), heart rate and blood pressure were measured throughout. At 70% relative humidity, fan use and folic acid supplementation both increased CVC relative to control (CON: 1.34 ± 0.24 vs. FAN: 1.95 ± 0.39 vs. FOLIC: 1.81 ± 0.35 units/mmHg, P≤0.05). However, this did not translate into different FVC responses (CON: 4.86 ± 1.95 vs. FAN: 5.08 ± 1.91 vs. FOLIC: 4.41 ± 1.78 mL/min/mmHg, P&gt;0.05). Fan use also increased local sweat rate (0.84 ± 0.27 mg/min/cm2) relative to CON (0.60 ± 0.26 mg/min/cm2, P≤0.05), whereas FOLIC had no effect (0.62 ± 0.21 mg/min/cm2, P=0.64). Relative to CON (Tes: 37.62 ± 0.29°C, Tsk: 38.41 ± 0.25°C), esophageal and mean skin temperatures were greater during FAN (Tes: 37.94 ± 0.63°C, Tsk: 38.97 ± 0.55°C, P≤0.05) but not FOLIC (Tes: 37.58 ± 0.21°C, Tsk: 38.28 ± 0.25°C, P&gt;0.05). In contrast, heart rate and blood pressure were similar during all conditions (both P&gt;0.05). The critical humidity at which an inflection in esophageal temperature was observed did not differ between conditions (CON: 63 ± 2 vs. FAN: 64 ± 5 vs. FOLIC: 63 ± 4%, P=0.64). Under the conditions employed, fan use results in greater esophageal and mean skin temperatures during extreme heat exposure in healthy aged individuals while folic acid supplementation has no effect. Furthermore, neither intervention reduced cardiovascular strain nor did they modify the limit of thermal compensability.</style></abstract><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-12 17:40:15)(Select): just the abstract (conference); </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">30</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>51</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Polar Pod cooling of collegiate athletes during preseason conditioning</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Clinical Journal of Sport Medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Purpose: Among U.S. high school and collegiate athletes, heat illness remains a leading cause of death (1, 2). The purpose of this project is to evaluate the effect of cold trailer exposure during routine football practice breaks versus traditional breaks on core temperature, cooling rate and subjective heat related symptoms. Methods and Study Design: Twenty Division I football offensive linemen volunteered for this study during training camp. Core temperature was monitored via ingestible thermistors. Participants were randomly assigned to either traditional (shade and oral hydration) or “Polar Pod” (closed trailer cooled to approximately 40-50 degrees F with low humidity) during the normally scheduled practice breaks. Core temperatures throughout practice, before and after each break, subjective symptom assessment via the Heat Illness Symptom Questionnaire (HISI) (3) and environmental conditions were recorded. Results: A 1-way ANOVA revealed no significant difference in cooling rate between Polar Pod and traditional breaks (rate = 0.04 and 0.06°C/break, respectively). Subjective symptom assessment was also not different between Polar Pod and traditional breaks (HISI = 2.4 and 2.6, respectively). Further analysis of maximal core temperature and rate of rise during practice is ongoing. Subjective assessment of Polar Pod exposure included responses such as: “refreshed” and “improved energy.” Conclusions: Initial analysis suggests that cold trailer exposure during routine football practice breaks provides no benefit to core temperature change when compared to traditional breaks. There was also no difference in subjective assessment of heat-related symptoms between cold trailer exposure and traditional breaks. However, qualitative feedback from the participants was positive. Significance of Findings: Heat illness is a common problem with potentially devastating results. Utilization of cold trailers during athletic activities is a novel approach in the prevention of heat illness, and allows for whole body cooling of several athletes without extensive equipment removal. Future considerations should include longer exposure times, variations in trailer temperature and laboratory-controlled environmental conditions.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1097/JSM.0000000000000199</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-11 17:10:33)(Select): Tc: ingestible pill
Cooling Cond: control (shade + hydration) Polar Pod (closed trailer cooled to 4°C)
Ex Cond: football practice
Amb Cond: outdoor; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">217</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">25</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>52</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Reduced physiological strain in firefighters using a practical cooling strategy</style></title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The aim of this study was to establish whether a practical cooling strategy reduces the physiological strain during simulated firefighting activities. On two occasions, 12 male firefighters completed two bouts of simulated firefighting activities (separated by a 15-min recovery period) under live fire conditions. During the 15-min recovery period subjects were either cooled via application of an ice vest and hand/forearm water immersion (∼19°C) or remained seated with no cooling (control). At the end of the recovery period core temperature and heart rate were significantly lower in the cooling condition compared with control. Core temperature remained significantly lower throughout bout 2 following cooling. There was also a trend for heart rate to be lower following cooling compared to the control condition (p = 0.053). We conclude that this practical cooling strategy is effective in reducing the physiological strain during simulated firefighting activities.</style></abstract><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 10:30:30)(Select): Ice vest + hand immersion; Aaron Bach (2023-03-12 17:27:34)(Select): Requested full-text; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">485-490</style></pages></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>53</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Safe cooling limits from exercise-induced hyperthermia</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">European Journal of Applied Physiology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">We evaluated the cooling rate of hyperthermic subjects, as measured by three estimates of deep core temperatures (esophageal, rectal and aural canal temperatures), during immersion in a range of water temperatures. The objective of the study was to compare the three indices of core temperature and define safe cooling limits when using rectal temperature to avoid the development of hypothermia. On 4 separate days, seven subjects (four males, three females) exercised for 45.4±4.1 min at 65% V̇O2 at an ambient temperature of 39°C, RH: 36.5%, until rectal temperature (Tre) increased to 40.0°C (39.5°C for two subjects). Following exercise, the subjects were immersed in a circulated water bath controlled at 2, 8, 14 and 20°C until Tre returned to 37.5°C. When Tre reached normothermia during the cooling period (37.5±0.05°C), both esophageal (Tes) (35.6±1.3°C) and aural canal (Tac) (35.9±0.9°C) temperatures were approaching or reaching hypothermia, particularly during immersion in 2°C water (Tes=34.5±1.2°C). On the basis of the heat loss data, the heat gained during the exercise was fully eliminated after 5.4±1.5, 7.9±2.9, 10.4±3.8 and 13.1±2.8 min of immersion in 2, 8, 14 and 20°C water, respectively, with the coldest water showing a significantly faster cooling rate. During the immersion in 2°C water, a decrease of only 1.5°C in Tre resulted in the elimination of 100% of the heat gained during exercise without causing hypothermia. This study would therefore support cooling the core temperature of hyperthermic subjects to a rectal temperature between 37.8°C (during immersion in water &amp;gt;10°C) and 38.6°C (during immersion in water &amp;lt;10°C) to eliminate the heat gained during exercise without causing hypothermia. © Springer-Verlag 2005.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1007/s00421-005-0063-y</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 12:06:12)(Select): Tc: rectal and oesph
Amb Cond: 38.8°C  36.5% but increased to 58% 
Ex Cond: treadmill run 65% until Tc reached 40°C 
Cooling Cond: CWI in 2, 8, 14, 20°C up to clavicle

Note: no control condition
; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">434-445</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">96</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>54</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effects of immersion water temperature on whole-body fluid distribution in humans</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Acta Physiologica Scandinavica</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aim: In this study, we quantified acute changes in the intracellular and extracellular fluid compartments during upright neutral- and cold-water immersion. We hypothesized that, during short-term cold immersion, fluid shifts would be wholly restricted to the extracellular space. Methods: Seven males were immersed 30 days apart: control (33.3° SD 0.6°C); and cold (18.1 ° SD 0.3°C). Posture was controlled for 4 h prior to a 60-min seated immersion. Results: Significant reductions in terminal oesophageal (36.9° ± 0.1°-36.3° ± 0.1°C) and mean skin temperatures (30.3° ± 0.3°-23.0° ± 0.3°C) were observed during the cold, but not the control immersion. Both immersions elicited a reduction in intracellular fluid [20.17 ± 6.02 mL kg-1 (control) vs. 22.72 ± 9.90 mL kg-1], while total body water (TBW) remained stable. However, significant plasma volume (PV) divergence was apparent between the trials at 60 min [12.5 ± 1.0% (control) vs. 6.1 ± 3.1%; P &amp;lt; 0.05], along with a significant haemodilution in the control state (P &amp;lt; 0.05). Plasma atrial natriuretic peptide concentration increased from 18.0 ± 1.6 to 58.7 ± 15.1 ng L-1 (P &amp;lt; 0.05) during cold immersion, consistent with its role in PV regulation. We observed that, regardless of the direction of the PV change, both upright immersions elicited reductions in intracellular fluid. Conclusion: These observations have two implications. First, one cannot assume that PV changes reflect those of the entire extracellular compartment. Second, since immersion also increases interstitial fluid pressure, fluid leaving the interstitium must have been rapidly replaced by intracellular water.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1111/j.1365-201X.2004.01302.x</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 16:11:01)(Select): No heat or exercise/TC &gt;38 applied. Wrong study design; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">3-10</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">182</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>55</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The Influence of Different External Cooling Methods on Thermoregulatory Responses before and after Intense Intermittent Exercise in the Heat</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Strength and Conditioning Research</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The purpose of this study was to determine the effect of different cooling methods on thermoregulation before and after intermittent anaerobic exercise in the heat (38°C). On separate days, 10 men completed 4 conditions consisting of 2 sets of six 30-second sprints (with 30 seconds of rest) at 125% of maximal aerobic power with each set of sprints followed by a cooling procedure. The 4 conditions were the following: passive cooling at room temperature (22°C; PRC), fan cooling (4.0 m·s-1, 22°C; FAC), fan cooling with water spraying (50 ml·min-1; FWC), and a noncooling passive recovery in the heat chamber (38°C; PCC). Each set of 6 sprints was followed by a 12-minute cooling period; after the second 12-minute period, cooling continued until esophageal temperature (Tes) was reduced by 1.0°C. Tes and mean skin temperatures (Tsk) were taken before and during exercise and during all cooling phases. Cooling rates (mean ± SEM) after the second set of sprints (based on Tes) were greater (p &amp;lt; 0.05) in PRC (0.043 ± 0.007) than in the other conditions (FWC = 0.027 ° ± 0.005 °, FAC = 0.03 ° ± 0.004 °, and PCC = 0.021 ° ± 0.003 ° C per minute). Overall decreases in heat content, however, were greater in the FWC (-332.2 ± 27.8) and FAC (-129.9 ± 14.7 kJ) conditions compared with the PRC condition (29.0 ± 14.9 kJ). The time required to lower Tes by 1.0°C with PRC (22.8 ± 1.8) was less than with FAC (30.4 ± 2.7 minutes). Finally, the rate of increase in Tes during the second set of sprints was less in the FAC and FWC conditions (0.15 ° ± 0.01 ° and 0.11 ° ± 0.01 ° C per minute) compared with the PCC and PRC conditions (0.19 ° ± 0.01 ° and 0.18 ° ± 0.01 ° C per minute), suggesting differences in preexercise cooling. Based on cooling rates and the time required to lower Tes by 1.0 ° C, PRC was the most effective method of cooling. The conclusion is different, however, when taking into account changes in heat content since the FAC and FWC conditions were more effective in dissipating heat and in preventing heat gain during the second set of sprints.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1519/1533-4287(2001)015&lt;0247:TIODEC&gt;2.0.CO;2</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">247-254</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">15</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>56</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Passive temperature lability in the elderly</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">European Journal of Applied Physiology and Occupational Physiology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Thermoregulatory responses of nine healthy elderly [seven men and two women; mean age (SD) 73.9 (4.8) years] were compared to those of nine young adult men [26.6 (5.2) years]. They exercised on a cycle ergometer for 20 min at an intensity inducing a heart rate equivalent to 65% of their predicted maximum, and were thereafter immersed in 28°C water. The exercise was conducted to elevate tympanic temperature (T(ty)) and initiate a steady rate of sweating. The post-exercise immersion period induced gradual cooling of T(ty) and changes in T(ty) relative to resting levels (ΔT(ty)) at which sweating abated and shivering commenced were defined as the ΔT(ty) thresholds for the cessation of sweating (T (sw)) and onset of shivering (T(sh)) respectively. In addition to T(ty), oxygen uptake (V̇O2; l·min-1), sweating rate (g·m-2·min-1), and forehead skin blood perfusion were also measured during the trials. The mean (SD) T(sw) occurred at a significantly (P &amp;lt; 0.005) higher ΔT(ty) [0.48 (0.18)°C] in the elderly than in the young adults [0.21 (0.06)°C], while the T(sh) occurred at significantly (P &amp;lt; 0.005) lower ΔT(ty) in the elderly [-0.64 (0.34)°C] than in young adults [-0.22(0.10)°C]. Decreases in ΔT(ty) below the shivering threshold were met with a significantly (P &amp;lt; 0.01) reduced V̇O2. The range of temperature lability between T(sw) and T(sh), defined as the null-zone, was significantly greater in the elderly [1.12 (0.39)°C] than in the young adults [0.43 (0.12)°C], and the slope of the vasoconstrictor response in the null-zone was significantly (P &amp;lt; 0.001) lower in the elderly subjects. The present study demonstrates a greater passive core temperature lability in older individuals, since the effector responses of sweating and shivering were initiated at higher and lower levels of T(ty), respectively. The magnitudes of the effector responses beyond the thresholds were also significantly reduced, suggesting that the elderly may be more susceptible to hypo-/hyperthermia during periods of endogenous and/or exogenous thermal stress.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1007/BF02425488</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 10:17:42)(Select): The cycling was done underwater....; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-08 16:13:00)(Select): Amb Cond: thermoneutral
Ex Cond: 20 min cycling 65% max
Cooling Cond: WI 28°C heat out, NO CONTROL
Tc: Tympanic ; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">278-286</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">73</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>57</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Intermittent Cooling Reduces Perceived Exertion but Has No Effect on Baseball Hitting or Defense Performance in a Hot Environment</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Sports Science and Medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Hot environments can impair the complex cognitive functions that are crucial to baseball hitting and defense. This study investigated the effects of intermittent forehead and neck cooling on the hitting and reactive agility of baseball players in hot environments. Ten male collegiate baseball players played 7-inning intrasquad games in a hot environment (31.1℃-33.4℃), completing one cooling and one control trial in a randomized crossover design. In the cooling trial, the participants placed ice-cold towels on their forehead and neck for 3 min during offensive half innings. Hitting and reactive agility tests, a go/no-go task, and the Stroop Color and Word Test were administered before and after each game. The games in the hot environment significantly increased rectal temperatures to the same level in the control (38.15℃ ± 0.31℃, p &lt; 0.001) and cooling (38.08℃ ± 0.24℃, p &lt; 0.001) trials. Intermittent cooling significantly reduced forehead and tympanic temperatures, perceived exertion, and thermal sensation during the game. Swing power significantly increased after the game, but the exit velocity of batted balls did not significantly differ in both trials. Reactive agility was significantly impaired after the game in the control trial (before: 0.367 ± 0.109 s, after: 0.491 ± 0.212 s, p = 0.008) but displayed a trend of decrease in the cooling trial (before: 0.390 ± 0.183 s, after: 0.518 ± 0.282 s, p = 0.066). The game and cooling intervention had no significant effects on the reaction time or error rate in the go/no-go task and Stroop Color and Word Test. The results showed that intermittent cooling during a baseball game in a hot environment reduces perceived exertion and thermal sensation but has no significant effect on hitting, defense performance, or cognitive function. © 2022, Journal of Sport Science and Medicine. All rights reserved.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.52082/jssm.2022.137</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-15 16:33:19)(Select): Ex Cond: sim offensive baseball game
Tc: Rectal
Amb Cond: outdoor 31-33°C 63-67%
Cooling Cond: standing in shade while placing cold towels on forehead and neck or control (seated in shade)
Tc end ex: 38.08 - 38.15 
Note: cooling occurred throughout breaks in game
; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">137-144</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">21</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>58</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The impact of an ice slurry-induced gastrointestinal heat sink on gastrointestinal and rectal temperatures following exercise</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sports</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Gastrointestinal temperature (Tgint) measurement with a telemetric pill (TP) is increasingly used in exercise science. Contact of cool water with a TP invalidates Tgint assessment. However, what effect a heat sink created in the proximity of a TP may have on the assessment of Tgint remains unknown. We examined the impact of an ice slurry-induced heat sink on Tgint and rectal temperature (Trec) following exercise. After 20 min of seating (20–22◦C, 25–40% relative humidity (RH)), 11 men completed two intersperse exercise periods (31–32◦C, 35% RH) at 75–80% of estimated maximal heart rate until a Trec increase of 1◦C above baseline level. Following the first exercise period, participants were seated for 45 min and ingested 7.5 g·kg−1 of thermoneutral water, whereas, following the second period, they ingested 7.5 g·kg−1 of ice slurry. Both Tgint and Trec were measured continuously. The TPs were swallowed 10 h prior to the experiments. A bias ≤0.27◦C was taken as an indication that Tgint and Trec provided similar core temperature indices. Mean biases and 95% limits of agreement during passive sitting, first exercise, water ingestion, second exercise, and ice slurry ingestion periods were 0.16 ± 0.53, 0.13 ± 0.41, 0.21 ± 0.70, 0.17 ± 0.50, and 0.18 ± 0.66◦C, respectively. The rates of decrease in Tgint and Trec did not differ between the water and ice slurry ingestion periods. Our results indicate that ice slurry ingestion following exercise does not impact TP-derived assessment of Tgint compared with Trec. © 2019 by the authors. Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.3390/sports7090198</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-11 17:26:45)(Select): Ex Cond: sitting in thermneut, running/cycling 80% in heat
Amb Cond: 31°C 35%
Cooling Cond: seated water consumption (20°C 25-40%)
Tc: Rectal
NOTE: exercise protocol followed by water consumption, then repeat exercise then ice slurry. NO control
; </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">7</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>59</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Post-exercise cold-water immersion improves the performance in a subsequent 5-km running trial</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Temperature</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Various post-exercise strategies have been proposed to accelerate recovery during periods of training. However, the effects of water immersion (WI) temperature on recovery amid multiple daily exercise bouts are not well investigated. PURPOSE: To evaluate the effects of cold and warm water immersion temperatures between acute exercise bouts vs. no WI recovery on running performance. METHODS: Nine recreationally trained men (age: 24.0 ± 6.0 years old) participated in four experimental sessions using a crossover design. Each experimental session consisted of unilateral eccentric knee flexion exercise and 90 min of treadmill running at 70% of peak oxygen consumption followed by 15 min of WI at 15°C, 28°C or 38°C or passive recovery seated at room temperature (CON). Four hours following WI or CON, subjects completed a 5 km running time trial. Rectal temperature (Trec), heart rate, and excess post-exercise oxygen consumption (EPOC) were measured. RESULTS: Statistical analyses indicated that time trial performance was not affected by post-exercise recovery by WI (P &gt; .05). The magnitude-based inferences indicated that 15°C (+ 3.6 ± 7.8%) likely and 28°C (+ 3.2 ± 7.5%) possibly improved recovery compared with CON, while the effect of 38°C (- 0.1 ± 12.3%) on recovery was unclear. During WI, heart rate and rectal temperature were not different from CON, but EPOC was higher in 15°C and 28°C compared to CON. Trec in 15°C was lower than CON from the 15th min post WI. EPOC was also greater in 15°C post WI compared to CON. CONCLUSION: WI at 15°C and 28°C following acute exercise likely and possibly, respectively, improved subsequent 5 km running time trial performance. We speculate that the faster recovery in core temperature post-exercise may underlie these improvements in recovery. © 2018, © 2018 Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &amp; Francis Group.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1080/23328940.2018.1495023</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">359-370</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">5</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>60</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Theoretical analysis of evaporative cooling of classic heat stroke patients</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">International Journal of Biometeorology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Heat stroke is a serious health concern globally, which is associated with high mortality. Newer treatments must be designed to improve outcomes. The aim of this study is to evaluate the effect of variations in ambient temperature and wind speed on the rate of cooling in a simulated heat stroke subject using the dynamic model of Wissler. We assume that a 60-year-old 70-kg female suffers classic heat stroke after walking fully exposed to the sun for 4 h while the ambient temperature is 40 °C, relative humidity is 20%, and wind speed is 2.5 m/s−1. Her esophageal and skin temperatures are 41.9 and 40.7 °C at the time of collapse. Cooling is accomplished by misting with lukewarm water while exposed to forced airflow at a temperature of 20 to 40 °C and a velocity of 0.5 or 1 m/s−1. Skin blood flow is assumed to be either normal, one-half of normal, or twice normal. At wind speed of 0.5 m/s−1 and normal skin blood flow, the air temperature decreased from 40 to 20 °C, increased cooling, and reduced time required to reach to a desired temperature of 38 °C. This relationship was also maintained in reduced blood flow states. Increasing wind speed to 1 m/s−1 increased cooling and reduced the time to reach optimal temperature both in normal and reduced skin blood flow states. In conclusion, evaporative cooling methods provide an effective method for cooling classic heat stroke patients. The maximum heat dissipation from the simulated model of Wissler was recorded when the entire body was misted with lukewarm water and applied forced air at 1 m/s at temperature of 20 °C. © 2018, ISB.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1007/s00484-018-1551-1</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Shannon Rutherford (2023-01-23 18:08:28)(Screen): not using actual core data (modelling it)  but findings could be useful?; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1567-1574</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">62</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>61</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Internal and external cooling methods and their effect on body temperature, thermal perception and dexterity</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PLoS ONE</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Objective The present study aimed to compare a range of cooling methods possibly utilised by occupational workers, focusing on their effect on body temperature, perception and manual dexterity. Methods Ten male participants completed eight trials involving 30 min of seated rest followed by 30 min of cooling or control of no cooling (CON) (34C, 58% relative humidity). The cooling methods utilised were: ice cooling vest (CV0), phase change cooling vest melting at 14C (CV14), evaporative cooling vest (CVEV), arm immersion in 10C water (AI), portable water-perfused suit (WPS), heliox inhalation (HE) and ice slushy ingestion (SL). Immediately before and after cooling, participants were assessed for fine (Purdue pegboard task) and gross (grip and pinch strength) manual dexterity. Rectal and skin temperature, as well as thermal sensation and comfort, were monitored throughout. Results Compared with CON, SL was the only method to reduce rectal temperature (P = 0.012). All externally applied cooling methods reduced skin temperature (P&amp;lt;0.05), though CV0 resulted in the lowest skin temperature versus other cooling methods. Participants felt cooler with CV0, CV14, WPS, AI and SL (P&amp;lt;0.05). AI significantly impaired Purdue pegboard performance (P = 0.001), but did not affect grip or pinch strength (P&amp;gt;0.05). Conclusion The present study observed that ice ingestion or ice applied to the skin produced the greatest effect on rectal and skin temperature, respectively. AI should not be utilised if workers require subsequent fine manual dexterity. These results will help inform future studies investigating appropriate pre-cooling methods for the occupational worker. © 2018 Maley et al. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1371/journal.pone.0191416</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-17 15:43:40)(Select): Tc not high enough (37.3-37.4C); Kate Hutchins (2023-03-07 17:50:38)(Select): Ambient Cond: 34.4°C, 58%
Exercise Cond: seated in heat 30 min
Cooling Cond: control (no details), hand/forearm water immersion (10.4°C)
Tc @ End Ex: not reported; </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">13</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>62</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The biophysical and physiological basis for mitigated elevations in heart rate with electric fan use in extreme heat and humidity</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">International Journal of Biometeorology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Electric fan use in extreme heat wave conditions has been thought to be disadvantageous because it might accelerate heat gain to the body via convection. However, it has been recently shown that fan use delays increases in heart rate even at high temperatures (42 °C) in young adults. We here assess the biophysical and physiological mechanisms underlying the apparently beneficial effects of fan use. Eight males (24 ± 3 y; 80.7 ± 11.7 kg; 2.0 ± 0.1 m2) rested at either 36 °C or 42 °C, with (F) or without (NF) electric fan use (4.2 m/s) for 120 min while humidity increased every 7.5 min by 0.3 kPa from a baseline value of 1.6 kPa. Heart rate (HR), local sweat rate (LSR), cutaneous vascular conductance (CVC), core and mean skin temperatures, and the combined convective/radiative heat loss (C+R), evaporative heat balance requirements (Ereq) and maximum evaporative potential (Emax) were assessed. C+R was greater with fan use at 36 °C (F 8 ± 6, NF 2 ± 2 W/m2; P = 0.04) and more negative (greater dry heat gain) with fan use at 42 °C (F −78 ± 4, NF −27 ± 2 W/m2; P &amp;lt; 0.01). Consequently, Ereq was lower at 36 °C (F 38 ± 16, NF 45 ± 3 W/m2; P = 0.04) and greater at 42 °C (F 125 ± 1, NF 74 ± 3 W/m2; P &amp;lt; 0.01) with fan use. However, fan use resulted in a greater Emax at baseline humidity at both 36 °C (F 343 ± 10, NF 153 ± 5 W/m2; P &amp;lt; 0.01) and 42 °C (F 376 ± 13, NF 161 ± 4 W/m2; P &amp;lt; 0.01) and throughout the incremental increases in humidity. Within the humidity range that a rise in HR was prevented by fan use but not without a fan, LSR was higher in NF at both 36 °C (P = 0.04) and 42 °C (P = 0.05), and skin temperature was higher in NF at 42 °C (P = 0.05), but no differences in CVC or core temperatures were observed (all P &amp;gt; 0.05). These results suggest that the delayed increase in heart rate with fan use during extreme heat and humidity is associated with improved evaporative efficiency. © 2016, ISB.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1007/s00484-016-1213-0</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 15:20:53)(Select): Not sure if truely heatwave as humidity is ramped... to discuss; Kate Hutchins (2023-02-24 12:51:29)(Screen): heat wave simulation ; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">313-323</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">61</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>63</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Novel Application of Chemical Cold Packs for Treatment of Exercise-Induced Hyperthermia: A Randomized Controlled Trial</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Wilderness and Environmental Medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Objective Heat-related illness is a common disease with significant morbidity and mortality. Despite no proven efficacy, application of chemical cold packs (CCP) to the skin overlying the large vessels of the neck, groin, and axillae is a traditional recommended cooling modality. The study objective was to compare the cooling rates of CCP applied to these traditional areas vs the glabrous skin surfaces of the cheeks, palms, and soles in exercise-induced hyperthermia. Methods Ten healthy adult male volunteers walked on a treadmill in a heated room (40 ± 0.5 C) while wearing insulated military overgarments until their esophageal temperatures (Tes) reached 39.2 C. Each participant had three heat stress trials on separate days: no treatment followed by randomly ordered traditional (neck, groin, and axillae) cooling and glabrous skin cooling. Results With no treatment, Tes remained stable after the first 5 minutes of the heat trial (ΔTes = 0.12 ± 0.07 C/10 min). Traditional cooling followed a linear decline (ΔTes = 0.17 ± 0.04 C/10 min; P &amp;lt;.001). Glabrous cooling enhanced the treatment effect by a steeper decline (ΔTes = 0.30 ± 0.06 C/10 min; P &amp;lt;.001), significantly different from traditional cooling by 2-way analysis of variance (P &amp;lt;.001). Conclusions Application of CCP to glabrous skin surfaces was more effective for treating exercise-induced heat stress than the traditional CCP cooling intervention. This novel cooling technique may be beneficial as an adjunctive treatment for heat-related illness in the prehospital environment. © 2015 Wilderness Medical Society.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.wem.2014.11.006</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">173-179</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">26</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>64</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The effect of selective head-neck cooling on physiological and cognitive functions in healthy volunteers</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Translational Neuroscience</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">In general, brain temperatures are elevated during physical sporting activities; therefore, reducing brain temperature shortly after a sports-related concussion (SRC) could be a promising intervention technique. The main objective of this study was to examine the effects of head and neck cooling on physiological and cognitive function in normal healthy volunteers. Twelve healthy volunteers underwent two different sessions of combined head and neck cooling, one session with a cold pack and one session with a room temperature pack. Physiological measurements included: systolic/diastolic blood pressure, pulse oximetry, heart rate, and sublingual and tympanic temperature. Cognitive assessment included: processing speed, executive function, and working memory tasks. Physiological measurements were taken pre-, mid- and post-cooling, while cognitive assessments were done before and after cooling. The order of the sessions was randomized. There was a significant decrease in tympanic temperature across both sessions; however more cooling occurred when the cold pack was in the device. There was no significant decrease in sublingual temperature across either session. The observed heart rates, pulse oximetry, systolic and diastolic blood pressure during the sessions were all within range of a normal healthy adult. Cognitive assessment remained stable across each session for both pre- and post-cooling. We propose that optimizing brain temperature management after brain injury using head and neck cooling technology may represent a sensible, practical, and effective strategy to potentially enhance recovery and perhaps minimize the subsequent short and long term consequences from SRC. © 2015 Kevin Jackson et al.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1515/tnsci-2015-0012</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">131-138</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">6</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>65</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Influence of cold-water immersion on limb and cutaneous blood flow after exercise</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PURPOSE: This study aimed to determine the influence of cold (8 C) and cool (22 C) water immersion on femoral artery and cutaneous blood flow after exercise. METHODS: Twelve men completed a continuous cycle exercise protocol at 70% peak oxygen uptake until a core temperature of 38 C was attained. Subjects were then immersed semireclined into 8 C or 22 C water to the iliac crest for 10 min or rested. Rectal and thigh skin temperature, deep and superficial muscle temperature, thigh and calf skin blood flow (laser Doppler flowmetry), and superficial femoral artery blood flow (duplex ultrasound) were measured before and up to 30 min after immersion. Indices of vascular conductance were calculated (flux and blood flow/mean arterial pressure). RESULTS: Reductions in rectal temperature were similar (0.6 C-0.7 C) in all three trials (P = 0.38). The mean ± SD thigh skin temperature during recovery was 25.4 C ± 3.8 C in the 8 C trial, which was lower than the 28.2 C ± 1.4 C and 33.78 C ± 1.0 C in the 22 C and control trials, respectively (P &lt; 0.001). Recovery muscle temperature was also lowest in the 8 C trial (P &lt; 0.01). Femoral artery conductance was similar after immersion in both cooling conditions and was lower (∼55%) compared with the control condition 30 min after immersion (P &lt; 0.01). Similarly, there was greater thigh (P &lt; 0.01) and calf (P &lt; 0.05) cutaneous vasoconstriction during and after immersion in both cooling conditions relative to the control condition. CONCLUSION: Colder water temperatures may be more effective in the treatment of exercise-induced muscle damage and injury rehabilitation by virtue of greater reductions in muscle temperature and not muscle blood flow. Copyright © 2013 by the American College of Sports Medicine.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1249/MSS.0b013e31829d8e2e</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-17 15:45:54)(Select): Tc is so close... Is 38 the number we want?; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-14 17:08:32)(Select): Amb Cond: 22-24°C
Ex Cond: 70% cycling until 38°C
Cooling Cond: immersion hips down 22°C and seated control (22-24°C air)
Tc: rectal
Tc end ex: 37.8
; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2277-2285</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">45</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>66</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Acute cardiovascular effects of firefighting and active cooling during rehabilitation</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Occupational and Environmental Medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">OBJECTIVES: To determine the cardiovascular and hemostatic effects of fire suppression and postexposure active cooling. METHODS: Forty-four firefighters were evaluated before and after a 12-minute live-fire drill. Next, 50 firefighters performing the same drill were randomized to undergo postfire forearm immersion in 10°C water or standard rehabilitation. RESULTS: In the first study, heart rate and core body temperature increased and serum C-reactive protein decreased but there were no significant changes in fibrinogen, sE-selectin, or sL-selectin. The second study demonstrated an increase in blood coagulability, leukocyte count, factors VIII and X, cortisol, and glucose, and a decrease in plasminogen and sP-selectin. Active cooling reduced mean core temperature, heart rate, and leukocyte count. CONCLUSIONS: Live-fire exposure increased core temperature, heart rate, coagulability, and leukocyte count; all except coagulability were reduced by active cooling. Copyright © 2012 by American College of Occupational and Environmental Medicine.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1097/JOM.0b013e3182619018</style></electronic-resource-num><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1413-1420</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">54</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>67</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Interpretation of aural temperatures during exercise, hyperthermia, and cooling therapy.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medicine, Exercise, Nutrition &amp; Health</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This paper presented research data relevant to the interpretation of aural temperature (Tau) measured via an infrared temperature scanner (ITS). Tau was measured during two laboratory studies and one clinical field test. Study A compared Tau to the rectal (Tre) and mean skin temperatures of highly trained males who exercised in controlled environments (24 degree C and 38 degree C) for 20 min. Study B compared Tau to Tre and esophageal temperatures (Tes) in healthy, middle-aged men who were immersed in hot water (40 degree C) for 25 min. Study C compared Tau to Tre in hyperthermic distance runners (maximal Tre: 40.0 - 41.8 degree C) who were treated for heat illness subsequent to an 11.5-km foot race. The results indicated that: Study A, the difference between Tau and Tre was greater (p less than 0.05) during exercise in 24 degree C (versus 38 degree C); Study B, during hot-water immersion, Tau responded rapidly and similarly to Tes, whereas Tre responded slowly; Study C, during cooling therapy for hyperthermia, Tau responded slowly, but Tre cooled rapidly; Study C, the Tre minus Tau difference was greatest in the runners who experienced the most severe hyperthermia (r = 0.76, p less than 0.001). These data suggest that ITS measurements vary, depending on environmental and patient factors surrounding the measurement of Tau.</style></abstract><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-12 17:25:57)(Select): No full-text; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">9-16</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">3</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>68</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Optimum room temperature during rest periods between repetitive exercises under heat stress</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Environmental Ergonomics: THE ERGONOMICS OF HUMAN COMFORT, HEALTH AND PERFORMANCE IN THE THERMAL ENVIRONMENT</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Four healthy male volunteers (22.0 +/- 0.8 years) were asked to perform three repeats of 20 min of exercise, at a work rate of 75 W, on a bicycle ergometer for three times in a climatic chamber controlled at a dry-bulb temperature of 35 degrees C, 60% relative humidity, and a wet-bulb globe temperature of 31.5 degrees C. Between the work periods, they were asked to sit stationary for 15 min in an attached air-conditioned room. The experiment was repeated with the temperature of the attached room (T-a) ranging from 20 to 30 degrees C. The average increase in esophageal temperature (T-es) was largest when T-a was 20 degrees C, followed by 22 &gt; 26 &gt; 30 &gt; 24 C. At a T-a of 24 degrees C or less, most subjects showed an increase in T-es even inside the air-conditioned room and a temporary decrease of T-es right after the reentry to the climatic chamber. The lower the T-a the more the skin surface temperature decreased. The inverse elevation and initial drop of T-es are likely to be caused by vasoconstriction on the skin surface and by subsequent recanalization between the skin surface and core. Considering that none of the results suggested that the optimum temperature should be 26 degrees C or more, we suggest that the optimum room air temperature for short rests provided for heat-exposed physical workers should be around 22-24 degrees C.
AD  - Univ Occupat &amp; Environm Hlth, Dept Hlth Policy &amp; Management, Kitakyushi, Japan&#13;C3  - University of Occupational &amp; Environmental Health - Japan&#13;PU  - ELSEVIER SCIENCE BV</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/S1572-347X(05)80015-1
WE  - Conference Proceedings Citation Index - Science (CPCI-S)&#13;WE  - Conference Proceedings Citation Index - Social Science &amp;amp; Humanities (CPCI-SSH)&#13;AN  - WOS:000231046300015</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 15:05:18)(Select): The highest Te observed during the experiment among the four subjects was 37.9C; Kate Hutchins (2023-02-24 12:15:39)(Screen): here I have considered &apos;moving into cooler room&apos; as a cooling intervention but may not be low cost ; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">85-90</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">3</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>69</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cooling hyperthermic firefighters by immersing forearms and hands in 10 degrees C and 20 degrees C water</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">AVIATION SPACE AND ENVIRONMENTAL MEDICINE</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Introduction: Firefighters experience significant heat stress while working with heavy gear in a hot, humid environment. This study compared the cooling effectiveness of immersing the forearms and hands in 10 and 20 degrees C water. Methods: Six men (33 :+/- 10 yr; 180 +/- 4 cm; 78 +/- 9 kg; 19 +/- 5% body fat) wore firefighter &apos;turn-out gear&apos; (heavy clothing and breathing apparatus weighing 27 kg) in a protocol including three 20-min exercise bouts (step test, 78 W, 40 degrees C air, 40% RH) each followed by a 20-min rest/cooling (21 degrees C air); i.e., 60 min of exercise, 60 min of cooling. Turn-out gear was removed during rest/cooling periods and subjects either rested (Control), immersed their hands in 10 or 20&apos;C water (H-1 0, H-20), or immersed their hands and forearms in 10 or 20 degrees C water (HF-10, HF-20). Results: In 20 degrees C water, hand immersion did not reduce core temperature compared with Control; however, including forearm immersion decreased core temperature below Control values after both the second and final exercise periods (p &lt; 0.001). In 10 degrees C water, adding forearm with hand immersion produced a lower core temperature (0.8 degrees C above baseline) than all other conditions (1.1 to 1.4 degrees C above baseline) after the final exercise period (p &lt; 0.001). Sweat loss during Control 0 458 g) was greater than all active cooling protocols (1146 g) (p &lt; 0.001), which were not different from each other. Discussion: Hand and forearm immersion in cool water is simple, reduces heat strain, and may increase work performance in a hot, humid environment. With 20&apos;C water, forearms should be immersed with the hands to be effective. At lower water temperatures, forearm and/or hand immersion will be effective, although forearm immersion will decrease core temperature further.
AD  - Univ Manitoba, Hlth Leisure &amp; Human Performance Res Inst, Exercise &amp; Environm Med Lab, Winnipeg, MB R3T 2N2, Canada&#13;C3  - University of Manitoba&#13;PU  - AEROSPACE MEDICAL ASSOC</style></abstract><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 15:01:59)(Select): End exercise bout #1 Tac = 37.8. Sol close to 38C... do we want to adjust figure down?; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-14 17:29:29)(Select): Tc: aural canal
Ex Cond: loaded 3x 20 min stepping exercise
Amb Cond: 40°C 40%
Cooling Cond: control (21°C), hand immersion 20°C, hand and forearm 20°C, hand immersion 10°C, hand and forearm (10°C)

NOTE: core temp measure; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">561-567
WE  - Science Citation Index Expanded (SCI-EXPANDED)&#13;AN  - WOS:000246862200004</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">78</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>70</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Strategies for increasing evaporative cooling during simulated desert patrol mission.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ergonomics</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The study evaluated the efficiency of two heat dissipation strategies under simulated desert patrol missions. Ten men participated in four trials, during which they walked on a treadmill (45°C, 20% relative humidity), carrying a load of 35 kg; two 50-min walks were separated by a 20-min rest. Cooling strategies, provided by an ambient air-ventilated vest (active cooling condition, AC), or water spraying of the skin during the rest (passive cooling condition, PC), in addition to reduced clothing and open zippers, were compared to conditions with full protective (FP) clothing and naked condition (NC). Skin temperature was higher during NC (37.9 ± 0.4°C;p &lt; 0.001), and rectal temperature and heart rate were higher during FP (38.6 ± 0.4°C,p &lt; 0.001 and 145 ± 12,p &lt; 0.001, respectively), compared to other conditions. Four subjects terminated the trial prematurely due to signs of heat exhaustion in FP. Both cooling strategies substantially improved evaporative cooling. Practitioner Summary:Cooling strategies, provided by an ambient air-ventilated vest and water spraying of the skin, were compared to conditions with full protective clothing and a naked condition during a simulated desert patrol mission. Both cooling strategies improved evaporative cooling and reduced heat strain, compared to the full protection condition.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1080/00140139.2015.1061142</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-08 17:11:28)(Select): Amb Cond: 45°C 20%
Ex Cond: 2x 50 min walks, backpack
Cooling Cond: removed clothing layers water spray (45°C) and fanned, naked control, full protective uniform control
Tc: rectal
Tc @ End Ex: 38.3°C
  ; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">298-309</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">59</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>71</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The impact of different cooling modalities on the physiological responses in firefighters during strenuous work performed in high environmental temperatures</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">European Journal of Applied Physiology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study investigated the impact of ice vests and hand/forearm immersion on accelerating the physiological recovery between two bouts of strenuous exercise in the heat [mean (SD), 49.1(1.3)°C, RH 12 (1)]. On four occasions, eight firefighters completed two 20-min bouts of treadmill walking (5 km h, 7.5% gradient) while wearing standard firefighter protective clothing. Each bout was separated by a 15-min recovery period, during which one of four conditions were administered: ice vest (VEST), hand/forearm immersion (W), ice vest combined with hand/forearm immersion (VEST + W) and control (CON). Core temperature was significantly lower at the end of the recovery period in the VEST + W (37.97 ± 0.23°C) and W (37.96 ± 0.19°C) compared with the VEST (38.21 ± 0.12°C) and CON (38.29 ± 0.25°C) conditions and remained consistently lower throughout the second bout of exercise. Heart rate responses during the recovery period and bout 2 were similar between the VEST + W and W conditions which were significantly lower compared with the VEST and CON which did not differ from each other. Mean skin temperature was significantly lower at the start of bout 2 in the cooling conditions compared with CON; these differences reduced as exercise progressed. These findings demonstrate that hand/forearm immersion (∼19°C) is more effective than ice vests in reducing the physiological strain when firefighters re-enter structural fires after short rest periods. Combining ice vests with hand/forearm immersion provides no additional benefit. © 2010 Springer-Verlag.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1007/s00421-010-1714-1</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-11 17:18:19)(Select): Tc: ingestible pill
Ex Cond: loaded 20 min walking 5 km 7.5%
Amb Cond: 50°C 13%
Cooling Cond: seated control (18°C air con), sit in water filled reservoir chair hands and forearms immersed (Kore Kooler Chair, 19°C water + 18°C air con)
Tc end ex: 38.2°C
NOTE: considering cooling chair as similar to simple arm immersion; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">959-967</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">111</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>72</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Age Modulates Physiological Responses during Fan Use under Extreme Heat and Humidity.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medicine &amp; Science in Sports &amp; Exercise</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Purpose: We examined the effect of electric fan use on cardiovascular and thermoregulatory responses of nine young (26 ± 3 yr) and nine aged (68 ± 4 yr) adults exposed to extreme heat and humidity. Methods: While resting at a temperature of 42°C, relative humidity increased from 30% to 70% in 2% increments every 5 min. On randomized days, the protocol was repeated without or with fan use. HR, core (Tcore) and mean skin (Tsk) temperatures were measured continuously. Whole-body sweat loss was measured from changes in nude body weight. Other measures of cardiovascular (cardiac output), thermoregulatory (local cutaneous and forearm vascular conductance, local sweat rate), and perceptual (thermal and thirst sensations) responses were also examined. Results: When averaged over the entire protocol, fan use resulted in a small reduction of HR (-2 bpm, 95% confidence interval [CI], -8 to 3), and slightly greater Tcore (+0.05°C; 95% CI, -0.13 to 0.23) and Tsk (+0.03°C; 95% CI, -0.36 to 0.42) in young adults. In contrast, fan use resulted in greater HR (+5 bpm; 95% CI, 0-10), Tcore (+0.20°C; 95% CI, 0.00-0.41), and Tsk (+0.47°C; 95% CI, 0.18-0.76) in aged adults. A greater whole-body sweat loss during fan use was observed in young (+0.2 kg; 95% CI, -0.2 to 0.6) but not aged (0.0 kg; 95% CI, -0.2 to 0.2) adults. Greater local sweat rate and cutaneous vascular conductance were observed with fan use in aged adults. Other measures of cardiovascular, thermoregulatory, and perceptual responses were unaffected by fan use in both groups. Conclusions: During extreme heat and humidity, fan use elevates physiological strain in aged, but not young, adults.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1249/MSS.0000000000001348</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 14:59:26)(Select): Have to check this is a different data set to the JAMA letter; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 10:36:38)(Select): Tc: oesoph
Amb Cond: 42°C 30%, RH increased gradually to 70% throughout protocol (100 min), amb temp changed to 31°C (~60 min)
Cooling Cond: fan and no fan (control)
Tes end exposure: 37.5°C; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2333-2342</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">49</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>73</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cold-water immersion decreases cerebral oxygenation but improves recovery after intermittent-sprint exercise in the heat</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Scandinavian journal of medicine &amp; science in sports</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study examined the effects of post-exercise cooling on recovery of neuromuscular, physiological, and cerebral hemodynamic responses after intermittent-sprint exercise in the heat. Nine participants underwent three post-exercise recovery trials, including a control (CONT), mixed-method cooling (MIX), and cold-water immersion (10 °C; CWI). Voluntary force and activation were assessed simultaneously with cerebral oxygenation (near-infrared spectroscopy) pre- and post-exercise, post-intervention, and 1-h and 24-h post-exercise. Measures of heart rate, core temperature, skin temperature, muscle damage, and inflammation were also collected. Both cooling interventions reduced heart rate, core, and skin temperature post-intervention (P &lt; 0.05). CWI hastened the recovery of voluntary force by 12.7 ± 11.7% (mean ± SD) and 16.3 ± 10.5% 1-h post-exercise compared to MIX and CONT, respectively (P &lt; 0.01). Voluntary force remained elevated by 16.1 ± 20.5% 24-h post-exercise after CWI compared to CONT (P &lt; 0.05). Central activation was increased post-intervention and 1-h post-exercise with CWI compared to CONT (P &lt; 0.05), without differences between conditions 24-h post-exercise (P &gt; 0.05). CWI reduced cerebral oxygenation compared to MIX and CONT post-intervention (P &lt; 0.01). Furthermore, cooling interventions reduced cortisol 1-h post-exercise (P &lt; 0.01), although only CWI blunted creatine kinase 24-h post-exercise compared to CONT (P &lt; 0.05). Accordingly, improvements in neuromuscular recovery after post-exercise cooling appear to be disassociated with cerebral oxygenation, rather reflecting reductions in thermoregulatory demands to sustain force production.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1111/sms.12060</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-08 16:03:37)(Select): Amb Cond: indoor track (32°C 42%)
Ex Cond: shuttle runs, max sprints repeat bouts with rest periods
Cooling Cond: ice packs hams/quads, control (32°C 42%)
Tc: Telemetric capsule
Tc @ End Ex: ~38.8°C
; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">656-666</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">24</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>74</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Comparison of body cooling methods on physiological and perceptual measures of mildly hyperthermic athletes</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Strength and Conditioning Research</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">DeMartini, JK, Ranalli, GF, Casa, DJ, Lopez, RM, Ganio, MS, Stearns, RL, McDermott, BP, Armstrong, LE, and Maresh, CM. Comparison of body cooling methods on physiological and perceptual measures of mildly hyperthermic athletes. J Strength Cond Res 25(8): 2065-2074, 2011-Hyperthermia is common among athletes and in a variety of environments. The purpose of this study was to evaluate the effectiveness of cooling methods on core body temperature, heart rate (HR), and perceptual readings in individuals after exercise. Sixteen subjects (age: 24 ± 6 years, height: 182± 7 cm, weight: 74.03 ± 9.17 kg, and body fat: 17.08 ± 6.23%) completed 10 exercise sessions in warm conditions (WBGT: 26.64 ± 4.71°C) followed by body cooling by 10 different methods. Cooling methods included cold water immersion (CWI), shade, Port-a-Cool® (FAN), Emergency Cold Containment System® (ECCS), Rehab. Hood® (HOOD), Game Ready Active Cooling Vest™ (GRV), Nike Ice VestTM (NIV), ice buckets (IBs), and ice towels (IT). These cooling modes were compared with a control (SUN). Rectal temperature (Tre), HR, thermal sensation, thirst sensation, and a 56-question Environmental Symptoms Questionnaire (ESQ) were used to assess physiological and perceptual data. Average Tre after exercise across all trials was 38.73 ± 0.12°C. After 10 minutes of cooling, CWI (20.65±0.29°C), ECCS (20.68±0.24°C), and IB (20.74 ± 0.34°C) had significantly (p , 0.006) greater decreases in Tre compared with that in SUN (20.42 ± 0.15°C). The HR after 10 minutes of cooling was significantly (p &lt; 0.006) lower for CWI (82 ± 15 b·min-1), ECCS (87 ± 14 b·min -1), and IT (84 ± 15 b·min-1) when compared with SUN (101 6 15 b·min-1). The thermal sensation between modalities was all significantly (p &lt; 0.006) lower (CWI: 1.5 ± 0.5; Fan: 3.0 ± 1.0; ECCS: 4.5 ± 1.0; Hood: 4.5 ± 0.5; GRV: 4.0 ± 0.5; NIV: 4.5 ± 1.0; IB: 4.0 ± 1.0; IT: 3.0 ± 1.0) when compared with SUN (5.5±0.5), except for Shade (5.0±1.0). There were no significant differences (p&gt; 0.006) in thirst sensation between modalities. The ESQ scores were significantly (p &lt; 0.006) lower for CWI (1 ± 6), Fan (4±5), and IT (3±8) compared with that for SUN (13±12). In conclusion, when athletes experience mild hyperthermia, CWI, ECCS, and IB resulted in a significantly greater decrease in Tre. These cooling strategies are recommended to decrease Tre during a brief recovery period between exercise bouts. © 2011 National Strength and Conditioning Association.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1519/JSC.0b013e3182259b1d</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-08 16:23:32)(Select): Amb Cond: 26.64 WBGT outside
Ex. Cond: soccer, frisbee, bree-ball games (1 hr bouts)
Tc: rectal
Cooling Cond: shade, ice towels (7 towels head, neck, torso, extremities - 14°C), ice bucket (hand to forearm + feet to mid-calf immersed - 14°C), Port-a-Cool fan, control (26.64°C)
Tc @ Ex End: 38.73°C
; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2065-2074</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">25</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>75</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Heat strain is reduced at different rates with hand, foot, forearm or lower leg cooling</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Elsevier Ergonomics Book Series</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Heat strain in aircrew is exacerbated when personal protective equipment is worn, due to the restriction of sweat evaporation. The most realistic solution to this problem in the military would be to adopt a cooling garment that removed heat from the body surface by direct conduction. Previous work has indicated that heat may be extracted more effectively from the limbs than the torso of the body: the approach traditionally used in conductive cooling garments. This experiment was conducted to test the hypothesis that heat extraction rates when a hand or foot was cooled were greater than that for cooling a forearm or lower leg. Twenty male subjects undertook a repeated-measures study in which heat strain was induced by exercising in a hot climate followed by natural cooling (control) or the application of cooling to the hand, foot, forearm or lower leg. Cooling interventions were undertaken by immersing the site in water at 10°C, but avoiding direct contact with the water by using a plastic bag. Cooling rates were determined from changes in mean body temperature calculated from insulated auditory canal and mean skin temperatures. Mean body temperature and heart rate fell at faster rates in all water-cooling conditions compared to the control (p&lt;0.05). The hand was the most effective and the lower leg the least effective, with forearm and foot being similar and intermediate to these two (p&lt;0.05). Assuming that the cooling rate for two hands is approximately double the rate of cooling for a single hand, and similarly for the other body sites, cooling both hands would extract heat at up to 200 W, similar to the rate of metabolic heat production of rotary-wing aircrew during flight. Cooling the other sites would cool at between 120 and 155 W. It is not known if the cooling achieved using multiple sites would be additive. © 2005 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/S1572-347X(05)80016-3</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 15:20:31)(Select): &quot;When the Tac of subjects reached 38.7~ the exercise was stopped&quot;; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-15 17:21:28)(Select): Amb Cond: 37.5°C
Ex Cond: stepping at moderate rate wearing PPE until Tac 38.7°C
Cooling Cond: control, application of cooling to hand, foot, forearm or leg (water immersion 10°C)
Tc: rectal and Tac
Tc end ex: ??; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">91-95</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">3</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>76</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cardiac and Thermal Strain of Elderly Adults Exposed to Extreme Heat and Humidity With and Without Electric Fan Use.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">JAMA: Journal of the American Medical Association</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This article presents a study on the effect of fan use on heart rate and core temperature of older people exposed to extreme heat and humidity. It discusses the methods used in the study, the increase in heart rate and core temperature resulting from fan use, and findings on sweat loss in young adults.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1001/jama.2016.10550</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-07 18:22:52)(Select): Heat Wave Sim: 42°C 30% 30 min, 2% increase every 5 min to 70%
Cooling Cond: fan or no fan 
Tc: esoph
Tc Range: ~36.3 - 37.8°C; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">989-991</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">316</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>77</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Physiologic and Perceptual Responses to Cold- Shower Cooling After Exercise-Induced Hyperthermia.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Athletic Training (Allen Press)</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Context: Exercise conducted in hot, humid environments increases the risk for exertional heat stroke (EHS). The current recommended treatment of EHS is cold-water immersion; however, limitations may require the use of alternative resources such as a cold shower (CS) or dousing with a hose to cool EHS patients. Objective: To investigate the cooling effectiveness of a CS after exercise-induced hyperthermia. Design: Randomized, crossover controlled study. Setting: Environmental chamber (temperature = 33.4°C ± 2.1°C; relative humidity = 27.1% ± 1.4%). Patients or Other Participants: Seventeen participants (10 male, 7 female; height=1.75 ± 0.07 m, body mass=70.4 ± 8.7 kg, body surface area = 1.85 ± 0.13 m2, age range = 19-35 years) volunteered. Intervention(s): On 2 occasions, participants completed matched-intensity volitional exercise on an ergometer or treadmill to elevate rectal temperature to ≤39°C or until participant fatigue prevented continuation (reaching at least 38.5°C). They were then either treated with a CS (20.8°C ± 0.80°C) or seated in the chamber (control [CON] condition) for 15 minutes. Main Outcome Measure(s): Rectal temperature, calculated cooling rate, heart rate, and perceptual measures (thermal sensation and perceived muscle pain). Results: The rectal temperature (P=.98), heart rate (P=.85), thermal sensation (P = .69), and muscle pain (P = .31) were not different during exercise for the CS and CON trials (P &gt; .05). Overall, the cooling rate was faster during CS (0.07°C/min ± 0.03°C/min) than during CON (0.04°C/min ± 0.03°C/min; t16 = 2.77, P=.01). Heart-rate changes were greater during CS (45 ± 20 beats per minute) compared with CON (27 ± 10 beats per minute; t16=3.32, P=.004). Thermal sensation was reduced to a greater extent with CS than with CON (F3,45= 41.12, P &lt; .001). Conclusions: Although the CS facilitated cooling rates faster than no treatment, clinicians should continue to advocate for accepted cooling modalities and use CS only if no other validated means of cooling are available.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.4085/1062-6050-51.4.01</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-08 16:31:22)(Select): Amb Cond: 33.4°C 27%
Tc: rectal
Ex Cond: self-selected cycle/run/intensity etc &lt;50 min
Cooling Cond: control (33.4°C 27%), sprayed with hose 20.8°C, 15 min (in heat)
Tc @ Ex End: 39.0°C; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">252-257</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">51</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>78</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Comparison of active cooling devices with passive cooling for rehabilitation of firefighters performing exercise in thermal protective clothing: a report from the Fireground Rehab Evaluation (FIRE) trial.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Prehospital Emergency Care</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Background. Thermal protective clothing (TPC) worn by firefighters provides considerable protection from the external environment during structural fire suppression. However, TPC is associated with physiologic derangements that may have adverse cardiovascular consequences. These derangements should be treated during on-scene rehabilitation periods. Objective. To examine heart rate and core temperature responses during the application of four active cooling devices, currently being marketed to the fire service for on-scene rehabilitation, and compare them with passive cooling in a moderate temperature (approximately 24°C) and with an infusion of cold (4°C) saline. Methods. Subjects exercised while they were wearing TPC in a heated room. Following an initial exercise period (bout 1), the subjects exited the room, removed the TPC, and for 20 minutes cooled passively at room temperature, received an infusion of cold normal saline, or were cooled by one of four devices (fan, forearm immersion in water, hand cooling, or water-perfused cooling vest). After cooling, the subjects donned the TPC and entered the heated room for another 50-minute exercise period (bout 2). Results. The subjects were not able to fully recover core temperature during a 20-minute rehabilitation period when provided rehydration and the opportunity to completely remove the TPC. Exercise durations were shorter during bout 2 when compared with bout 1 but did not differ by cooling intervention. The overall magnitudes and rates of cooling and heart rate recovery did not differ by intervention. Conclusions. No clear advantage was identified when active cooling devices and cold intravenous saline were compared with passive cooling in a moderate temperature after treadmill exercise in TPC.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.3109/10903121003770654</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-14 17:00:21)(Select): Amb cond: 35°C
Ex Cond: 50 min loaded treadmill walking protocol sim of fire suppression
Cooling Cond: forearm and hand immersion (14°C Kore Kooler), fan, passive (24°C).
Tc: pill
Tc end ex: 38.5°C

; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">300-309</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">14</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>79</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Active versus passive cooling during work in warm environments while wearing firefighting protective clothing.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Occupational &amp; Environmental Hygiene</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study examined whether active or passive cooling during intermittent work reduced the heat strain associated with wearing firefighting protective clothing (FPC) and self-contained breathing apparatus (SCBA) in the heat (35 degrees C, 50% relative humidity). Fifteen male Toronto firefighters participated in the heat-stress trials. Subjects walked at 4.5 km x h[-1] with 0% elevation on an intermittent work (50 min) and rest (30 min) schedule. Work continued until rectal temperature (T[re]) reached 39.5 degrees C, or heart rate (HR) reached 95% of maximum or exhaustion. One of three cooling strategies, forearm submersion (FS), mister (M), and passive cooling (PC) were employed during the rest phases. Tolerance time (TT) and total work time (WT) (min) were significantly increased during FS (178.7 +/- 13.0 and 124.7 +/- 7.94, respectively) and M (139.1 +/- 8.28 and 95.1 +/- 4.96, respectively), compared with PC (108.0 +/- 3.59 and 78.0 +/- 3.59). Furthermore, TT and WT were significantly greater in FS compared with M. Rates of T[re] increase, HR and T[sk] were significantly lower during active compared with passive cooling. In addition, HR and T[re] values in FS were significantly lower compared with M after the first rest phase. During the first rest phase, T[re] dropped significantly during FS (approximately 0.4 degrees C) compared with M (approximately 0.08 degrees C) while PC increased (approximately 0.2 degrees C). By the end of the second rest period Tre was 0.9 degrees C lower in FS compared with M. The current findings suggest that there is a definite advantage when utilizing forearm submersion compared with other methods of active or passive cooling while wearing FPC and SCBA in the heat.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1080/15459620490475216</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-08 17:25:47)(Select): Amb Cond: 35°C 50%
Ex Cond: walking work/rest bout weighted/uniform
Cooling Cond:  passive (chamber temp), forearm submersion, misting fan (minimal details given)
Tc: rectal; Kate Hutchins (2023-02-24 12:27:12)(Screen): I am considering &apos;passive cooling&apos; as control condition here; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">521-531</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>80</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Keeping older individuals cool in hot and moderately humid conditions: wetted clothing with and without an electric fan</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of applied physiology (Bethesda, Md. : 1985)</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The present study evaluated whether wearing a water-soaked t-shirt, with or without electric fan use, mitigates thermal and cardiovascular strain in older individuals exposed to hot and moderately humid conditions. Nine healthy older individuals (68 ± 4 yr; five women) completed three 120-min heat exposures (42.4 ± 0.2°C, 34.2 ± 0.9% relative humidity) on separate days while wearing a dry t-shirt (CON), a t-shirt soaked with 500 ml of tap water (WET), or a t-shirt soaked with 500 ml of tap water while facing an electric fan (2.4 ± 0.4 m/s; WET+FAN). Measurements included core and skin temperatures, evaporative mass losses, heart rate, and blood pressure. In the WET condition, elevations in core temperature were attenuated compared with DRY from 30 to 120 min and compared with WET+FAN from 30 to 90 min (P &lt; 0.05). Evaporative mass losses (inclusive of sweat and water losses from the shirt) were greatest in WET+FAN, followed by WET, and then DRY (P &lt; 0.01). Sweat losses were lowest in WET, followed by DRY, and then WET+FAN (P &lt; 0.01). Heart rate was lower only at 60 min in WET versus DRY (P = 0.01). No differences in mean arterial pressure were observed (P = 0.51). In conclusion, wearing a water-soaked t-shirt without, but not with, electric fan use is an effective heat management strategy to mitigate thermal strain and lower sweat losses in older individuals exposed to hot and moderately humid conditions.NEW &amp; NOTEWORTHY In older individuals exposed to hot and moderately humid environments, electric fan use coupled with a water-soaked t-shirt exacerbates sweat losses without mitigating heat strain compared with a dry t-shirt. However, wearing a water-soaked t-shirt without fan use reduces sweat losses and attenuates heat strain compared with a dry t-shirt and a fan/water-soaked t-shirt combination. These findings suggest wearing a water-soaked t-shirt is an effective heat-management strategy for older individuals during heat waves when air conditioning is inaccessible.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1152/japplphysiol.00786.2019</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-08 17:17:30)(Select): Tc: pill
Amb. Cond: 120 min heat (42°C 34%)
Ex Cond: resting
Cooling Cond: dry t-shirt, wet t-shirt + fan, wet t-shirt + no fan ; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">604-611</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">128</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>81</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effect of Cold Shower on Recovery From High-Intensity Cycling in the Heat</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of strength and conditioning research</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ajjimaporn, A, Chaunchaiyakul, R, Pitsamai, S, and Widjaja, W. Effect of cold shower on recovery from high-intensity cycling in the heat. J Strength Cond Res 33(8): 2233-2240, 2019-Post-exercise cooling, e.g., cold water immersion has shown beneficial cardiovascular and hormonal effects during recovery from exercise in a hot environment. However, not much is known about the effects of a cold water shower (CWS) as a recovery intervention. This study examined the effects of a CWS on heart rate (HR), core temperature (Tc), salivary cortisol, and thermal comfort sensation (TCS) after exercise in the heat. Nine healthy male subjects (age, 21 ± 1 year) performed 45 minutes of cycling in a hot environment (35° C, 40-60% relative humidity) at 65% of peak oxygen uptake. Thereafter, subjects underwent the CWS condition (15 minutes, 15° C water shower) or control (SIT25; 15 minutes passive recovery in 25° C room) in a randomized crossover design. After each 15 minutes, subjects sat in a 25° C room for another 2-hour recovery. Heart rate, Tc, and TCS were recorded before and immediately after exercise, immediately after CWS or SIT25, and at 30 minutes, 1, and 2 hours during additional recovery. Salivary cortisol was collected at the same time points except at 30 minutes of the additional recovery period. Thermal comfort sensation was higher immediately after CWS (+4; very comfortable) than SIT25 (+1; just comfortable). The change of HR decreased faster with CWS (-18.3 ± 2.3%) than with SIT25 (-7.0 ± 4.6%) at the first 30-minute recovery time point (p &lt; 0.01). No differences between recovery conditions were observed for the Tc or salivary cortisol at any time point during the 2-hour recovery period. The findings demonstrate that a 15-minute, 15° C CWS was not effective in reducing Tc or salivary cortisol during recovery from exercise in a hot environment. However, CWS can promote TCS by facilitating a faster HR recovery after 30-minute postintervention compared with passive recovery. The cooling benefits of a CWS could be only recommended to reduce cardiac stress after routine workout in a hot environment.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1519/JSC.0000000000003017</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 09:59:47)(Select): Is the control really a true control here...?; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-08 16:40:21)(Select): Cooling Cond: cold water shower (15°C water), passive recovery (25°C 40-60%)
Ex Cond: 45 min cycling 65%
Amb Cond: 35°C 40-60%
Tc: pill
Tc @ End Ex: 38.3°C; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2233-2240</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">33</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>82</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Physiological and Perceived Effects of Forearm or Head Cooling During Simulated Firefighting Activity and Rehabilitation</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of athletic training</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">CONTEXT:  Cooling devices aim to protect firefighters by attenuating a rise in body temperature. Devices for head cooling (HC) while firefighting and forearm cooling (FC) during rehabilitation (RHB) intervals are commonly marketed, but research regarding their efficacy is limited.
OBJECTIVE:  To investigate the physiological and perceived effects of HC and FC during firefighting drills and RHB.
DESIGN:  Randomized controlled clinical trial.
SETTING:  Firefighter training center.
PATIENTS OR OTHER PARTICIPANTS:  Twenty-seven male career firefighters (age = 39 ± 7 years; height = 169 ± 7 cm; weight = 95.4 ± 16.8 kg).
INTERVENTION(S):  Firefighters were randomly assigned to 1 condition: HC (n = 9), in which participants completed drills wearing a cold gel pack inside their helmet; FC (n = 8), in which participants sat on a collapsible chair with water-immersion arm troughs during RHB; or control (n = 10), in which participants used no cooling devices. Firefighters completed four 15-minute drills (D1-D4) wearing full bunker gear and breathing apparatus. Participants had a 15-min RHB after D2 (RHB1) and D4 (RHB2).
MAIN OUTCOME MEASURE(S):  Change (Δ) in gastrointestinal temperature (TGI), heart rate (HR), physiological strain index, and perceived thermal sensation.
RESULTS:  The TGI increased similarly in the HC and control groups, respectively (D1: 0.57°C ± 0.41°C, 0.73°C ± 0.30°C; D2: 0.92°C ± 0.28°C, 0.85°C ± 0.27°C; D3: -0.37°C ± 0.34°C, -0.01°C ± 0.72°C; D4: 0.25°C ± 0.42°C, 0.57°C ± 0.26°C; P &gt; .05). The ΔHR, Δ physiological strain index, and Δ thermal sensation were similar between the HC and control groups during drills (P &gt; .05). The FC group demonstrated a decreased TGI compared with the control group after RHB1 (-1.61°C ± 0.35°C versus -0.23°C ± 0.34°C; P &lt; .001) and RHB2 (-1.40°C ± 0.38°C versus -0.38°C ± 0.24°C; P &lt; .001). The physiological strain index score decreased in the FC group compared with the control group after RHB1 (-7.9 ± 1.3 versus -2.6 ± 1.7; P &lt; .001) and RHB2 (-7.9 ± 1.6 versus -3.6 ± 1.1; P &lt; .001), but no differences between groups were demonstrated for ΔHR or Δ thermal sensation (P &gt; .05).
CONCLUSIONS:  The HC did not attenuate rises in physiological or perceptual variables during firefighting drills. The FC effectively reduced TGI and the physiological strain index score but not HR or thermal sensation during RHB. Clinicians and firefighters should not recommend the use of HC during firefighting but can consider using FC during RHB intervals in the field.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.4085/1062-6050-51.10.09</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-11 17:35:27)(Select): Tc: ingestible pill
Amb Cond: outdoor (33°C 27%)
Ex Cond: loaded firefighting drills
Cooling Cond: control, forearm cooling (Kore Koler Chair, hands + forearms, 5°C water), head cooling (helmet shaped gel pack)
Tc end ex: range 38.7-39.4°C
NOTE: would not include heat cooling as practical cooling method; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">927-935</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">51</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>83</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">A comparison of cooling techniques in firefighters after a live burn evolution.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Prehospital emergency care : official journal of the National Association of EMS Physicians and the National Association of State EMS Directors</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">We compared the use of two active cooling devices with passive cooling in a moderate-temperature (≈ 22 °C) environment on heart rate (HR) and core temperature (T(c)) recovery when applied to firefighters following 20 minutes of fire suppression. Firefighters (23 men, two women) performed 20 minutes of fire suppression at a live-fire evolution. Immediately following the evolution, the subjects removed their thermal protective clothing and were randomized to receive forearm immersion (FI), ice water perfused cooling vest (CV), or passive (P) cooling in an air-conditioned medical trailer for 30 minutes. Heart rate and deep gastric temperature were monitored every 5 minutes during recovery. A single 20-minute bout of fire suppression resulted in near-maximal mean ± standard deviation HR (175 ± 13 b min(-1), P; 172 ± 20 b·min(-1), FI; 177 ± 12 b·min(-1), CV) when compared with baseline (p &lt; 0.001), a rapid and substantial rise in T(c) (38.2° ± 0.7°, P; 38.3° ± 0.4°, FI; 38.3° ± 0.3°, CV) compared with baseline (p &lt; 0.001), and body mass lost from sweating of nearly 1 kilogram. Cooling rates (°C·min) differed (p = 0.036) by device, with FI (0.05 ± 0.04) providing higher rates than P (0.03 ± 0.02) or CV (0.03 ± 0.04), although differences over 30 minutes were small and recovery of body temperature was incomplete in all groups. During 30 minutes of recovery following a 20-minute bout of fire suppression in a training academy setting, there is a slightly higher cooling rate for FI and no apparent benefit to CV when compared with P cooling in a moderate temperature environment.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.3109/10903127.2010.545482</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 11:41:52)(Select): Tc: pill
Ex Cond: sim live fire evolution in ensemble
Cooling Cond: forearm and hand immersion (Kore Kooler, 21°C water, 22°C air), passive air conditioning (22°C) 
Amb Cond: ???
Tc: end ex: 38.3°C; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">226-232</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">15</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>84</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Post-exercise cooling techniques in hot, humid conditions</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">European Journal of Applied Physiology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Major sporting events are often held in hot and humid environmental conditions. Cooling techniques have been used to reduce the risk of heat illness following exercise. This study compared the efficacy of five cooling techniques, hand immersion (HI), whole body fanning (WBF), an air cooled garment (ACG), a liquid cooled garment (LCG) and a phase change garment (PCG), against a natural cooling control condition (CON) over two periods between and following exercise bouts in 31°C, 70%RH air. Nine males [age 22 (3) years; height 1.80 (0.04) m; mass 69.80 (7.10) kg] exercised on a treadmill at a maximal sustainable work intensity until rectal temperature (Tre) reached 38.5°C following which they underwent a resting recovery (0-15 min; COOL 1). They then recommenced exercise until Tre again reached 38.5°C and then undertook 30 min of cooling with (0-15 min; COOL 2A), and without face fanning (15-30 min; COOL 2B). Based on mean body temperature changes (COOL 1), WBF was most effective in extracting heat: CON 99 W; WBF: 235 W; PCG: 141 W; HI: 162 W; ACG: 101 W; LCG: 49 W) as a consequence of evaporating more sweat. Therefore, WBF represents a cheap and practical means of post-exercise cooling in hot, humid conditions in a sporting setting. © Springer-Verlag 2009.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1007/s00421-009-1135-1</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-11 17:45:21)(Select): Ex Cond: self-paced treadmill until Tc 38.5 
Amb Cond: 31°C 70%
Cooling Cond: control (seated in heat), hand immersion (17°C water), whole body fanning (no face), face fanning.
NOTE: exercise followed by first round of cooling then repeat exercise then second round of cooling combined with face fanning (i.e., hand immersion + face fanning, whole body fanning + face fanning). 
Tc: rectal temp; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">385-396</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">107</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>85</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Hand immersion in cold water alleviating physiological strain and increasing tolerance to uncompensable heat stress</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">European Journal of Applied Physiology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The current study examines the use of hand immersion in cold water to alleviate physiological strain caused by exercising in a hot climate while wearing NBC protective garments. Seventeen heat acclimated subjects wearing a semi-permeable NBC protective garment and a light bulletproof vest were exposed to a 125 min exercise-heat stress (35°C, 50% RH; 5 km/h, 5% incline). The heat stress exposure routine included 5 min rest in the chamber followed by two 50:10 min work-rest cycles. During the control trial (CO), there was no intervention, whilst in the intervention condition the subjects immersed their hands and forearms in a 10°C water bath (HI). The results demonstrated that hand immersion in cold water significantly reduced physiological strain. In the CO exposure during the first and second resting periods, the average rectal temperature (Tre) practically did not decrease. With hand immersion, the mean (SD) Tre decreased by 0.45 (0.05°C) and 0.48°C (0.06°C) during the first and second rest periods respectively (P &amp;lt; 0.005). Significant decreases in skin temperature, sweat rate, heart rate, and heat storage was also noted in the HI vs. the CO trials. Tolerance time in the HI exposure were longer than in the CO exposure (only 12 subjects in the CO trial endured the entire heat exposure session, as opposed to all 17 subjects in the HI group). It is concluded that hand immersion in cold water for 10 min is an effective method for decreasing the physiological strain caused by exercising under heat stress while wearing NBC protective garments. The method is convenient, simple, and allows longer working periods in hot or contaminated areas with shorter resting periods. © Springer-Verlag 2008.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1007/s00421-008-0693-y</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-15 16:38:57)(Select): Amb Cond: 35°C 50%
Ex Cond: 50 min treadmill walking, 10 min rest (seated in chamber) repeated 2x
Cooling Cond: hand immersion (10°C) and control (sitting in heat)
Tc: rectal
Tc end ex: ~38°C; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">303-309</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">104</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>86</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effect of 3 min whole-body and lower limb cold water immersion on subsequent performance of agility, sprint, and intermittent endurance exercise</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Frontiers in Physiology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The aim of this study was to investigate the effects of whole-body cold-water immersion (WCWI) and lower-limb cold-water immersion (LCWI) employed during a 15-min recovery period on the subsequent exercise performance as well as to determine the physiological and perceptual parameters in the heat (39°C). Eleven males performed team-sports-specific tests outdoors. The exercise program consisted of two identical exercise protocols (1 and 2) separated by a 15-min recovery period. The participants completed the same tests in each exercise protocol, in the following order: agility t test (t-test), 20-m sprint test (20M-ST), and Yo-Yo Intermittent Endurance Test Level 1 (Yo-Yo). During the recovery period, a 3-min recovery intervention of a passively seated rest (control, CON), WCWI, or LCWI was performed. The t-test and 20M-ST for the CON group were significantly longer during exercise protocol 2, but they were not significantly different between the two exercise protocols for the WCWI and LCWI groups. The completed Yo-Yo distance for the CON and LCWI groups was shorter during exercise protocol 2, but it was not significantly different between the two exercise protocols for the WCWI group. The chest temperature (Tchest), upper arm temperature (Tarm), thigh temperature (Tthigh), mean skin temperature (Tskin), and thermal sensation (TS) values were lower for the WCWI group than for the CON group; but only the Tthigh, Tskin, and TS values were lower for the LCWI group compared to the CON group. The Tchest, Tarm, Tskin, and TS values after the intervention were lower for the WCWI group than for the LCWI group. None of the three intervention conditions affected the core temperature (Tcore), heart rate (HR), or rating of perceived exertion (RPE). These results suggest that WCWI at 15°C for 3 min during the 15-min recovery period attenuates the impairment of agility, sprint, and intermittent-endurance performance during exercise protocol 2, but LCWI only ameliorates the reduction of agility and sprint performance. Furthermore, the ergogenic effects of WCWI and LCWI in the heat are due, at least in part, to a decrease of the Tskin and improvement of perceived strain. Copyright © 2022 Zhang, Ren and Zheng.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.3389/fphys.2022.981773</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kate Hutchins (2023-03-07 18:08:39)(Select): Amb Cond: multi-day outdoors (WBGT 39.6-39.8°C)
Exercise Cond: agility test, sprints, yoyo, passive recovery between each
Cooling Cond: passing (in heat), leg CWI (both 15°C)
Tc: BodyCap
Tc @ Ex End: ~38.3°C


; </style></notes><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">13</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>87</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effects of Wrist Cooling on Recovery From Exercise-Induced Heat Stress With Firefighting Personal Protective Equipment.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Occupational &amp; Environmental Medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Objective: To determine the effects of wrist cooling on recovery from exercise-induced heat stress (EIHS) from wearing firefighting personal protective equipment (PPE) and self-contained breathing apparatus. Methods: Using a single-blind, counterbalanced, crossover-design, in 11 healthy men, we measured heart rate (HR), HR variability (HRV), core temperature ( r Core), thermal strain (TS), and fatigue at rest, during 30-minute of exercise in PPE+SCBA, and during recovery while wearing a wrist cooling band (control[off] vs cool[on]). Results: No differences were observed between trials at baseline or during exercise, in HR, TCorc, TS, or fatigue. Time to 50% and recovery were not different between trials. Upon recovery, TCore was lower, while HR, fatigue, HRV, and TS were relatively indifferent with cooling. Conclusion: Wrist cooling after EIHS only modestly enhanced recovery, questioning its implementation during on-scene rehabilitation of firefighters.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1097/JOM.0000000000001436</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Exclusion reason: Not practical cooling intervention; Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 15:45:31)(Select): Not practical cooling $200 device; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-11 17:50:46)(Select): Tc: telemetry pill
Amb Cond: 21°C 12%
Cooling Cond: DhamaSport cooling band (7°C) and control (no detail)
Ex Cond: loaded walking 5% 
Tc end ex: 37.9°C; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1049-1055</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">60</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>88</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Extremity cooling for heat stress mitigation in military and occupational settings</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Thermal Biology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Physical work, high ambient temperature and wearing protective clothing can elevate body temperature and cardiovascular strain sufficiently to degrade performance and induce heat-related illnesses. We have recently developed an Arm Immersion Cooling System (AICS) for use in military training environments and this paper will review literature supporting such an approach and provide details regarding its construction. Extremity cooling in cool or cold water can accelerate body (core temperature) cooling from 0.2 to 1.0. °C/10. min vs. control conditions, depending on the size/surface area of the extremity immersed. Arm immersion up to the elbow results in greater heat loss than hand- or foot-only immersion and may reduce cardiovascular strain by lowering heart rate by 10-25 beats/min and increase work tolerance time by up to 60%. The findings from studies in this paper support the use of AICS prototypes, which have been incorporated as part of the heat stress mitigation procedures employed in US Army Ranger Training and may have great application for sports and occupational use. © 2013.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jtherbio.2013.03.010</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Exclusion reason: Wrong study design; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-08 15:54:08)(Select): literature review; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">305-310</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">38</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>89</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effect of cold-water immersion duration on body temperature and muscle function</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Sports Sciences</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">This study compared the effect of 5, 10 and 20 min of cold-water (14°C) immersion on rectal and muscle temperature and neuromuscular function. Twelve cyclists performed four cycling time-to-exhaustion trials in hot conditions (40°C and 40%rh), followed 25 min later by cold-water immersion for 5, 10 or 20 min or 20 min in room temperature (24°C; control). Rectal temperature was measured continuously, and muscle temperature was measured before, immediately after and 45 min after the time-to-exhaustion-test, as well as before and after water immersion. Sixty-second maximal voluntary isometric torque and isokinetic torque of the knee extensors were measured before, immediately after and 55 min after time-to-exhaustion-test. A greater rate of decrease in rectal temperature was observed in all water immersion conditions 45-80 min after time-to-exhaustion-test compared with control. Compared with control, muscle temperature 45 min after time-to-exhaustion-test was lower for all water immersion conditions; however, muscle temperature was lower for the 10- and 20-min conditions compared with 5 min. Isometric torque measured 55 min after time-to-exhaustion-test was lower for all conditions. Isokinetic torque was lower for all conditions immediately and 55-min post-time-to-exhaustion-test. Of the durations measured, 5 min of cold-water immersion appeared as the most appropriate duration for reducing rectal temperature but limiting decreases in muscle temperature. © 2009 Taylor &amp; Francis.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1080/02640410903207424</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Exclusion reason: Not practical cooling intervention; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 11:03:02)(Select): Ex Cond: cycling time to exhaust @ ventilatory threshold
Amb Cond: 40°C 40%
Cooling Cond:  5, 10, 20 min of CWI to sternum (14°C) or seated control (air temp 24°C)
Tc: rectal

NOTE:  CWI protocol not considered practical cooling method; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">987-993</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">27</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>90</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">A practical cooling strategy for reducing the physiological strain associated with firefighting activity in the heat</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ergonomics</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The aim of this study was to establish whether a practical cooling strategy reduces the physiological strain during simulated firefighting activity in the heat. On two separate occasions under high ambient temperatures (49.6 ± 1.8°C, relative humidity (RH) 13 ± 0;2%), nine male firefighters wearing protective clothing completed two 20-min bouts of treadmill walking (5 km/h, 7.5% gradient) separated by a 15-min recovery period, during which firefighters were either cooled (cool) via application of an ice vest and hand and forearm water immersion (° 19°C) or remained seated without cooling (control). There was no significant difference between trials in any of the dependent variables during the first bout of exercise. Core body temperature (37.72 ± 0.34 vs. 38.21 ± 0.17°C), heart rate (HR) (81 ± 9 vs. 96 ± 17 beats/min) and mean skin temperature (31.22 ± 1.04°C vs. 33.31 ± 1°C) were significantly lower following the recovery period in cool compared with control (p &lt; 0.05). Core body temperature remained consistently lower (0.49 ± 0.02°C; p &lt; 0.01) throughout the second bout of activity in cool compared to control. Mean skin temperature, HR and thermal sensation were significantly lower during bout 2 in cool compared with control (p &lt; 0.05). It is concluded that this practical cooling strategy is effective at reducing the physiological strain associated with demanding firefighting activity under high ambient temperatures.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1080/00140130802707675</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Exclusion reason: Not practical cooling intervention; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 11:50:25)(Select): Tc: pill
Amb Cond: 40°C 13%
Ex Cond: loaded treadmill walking 20 min
Cooling Cond: ice vest while immersing arms in Kore Kooler chair (19°C) and control seated in 21°C

Note: ice vest and immersion combined not considered practical cooling method; Aaron Bach (2023-03-16 10:30:43)(Select): Ice vest + hand immersion; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">413-420</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">52</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>91</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Is performance of intermittent intense exercise enhanced by use of a commercial palm cooling device?</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of strength and conditioning research / National Strength &amp; Conditioning Association</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The purpose of this study was to determine if using the CoreControl Rapid Thermal Exchange (RTX), a commercial palm cooling device, during active rest periods of multiple set training is an effective means to increase performance. Ten volunteers (5 men, 5 women) completed a VO2max test on a motorized treadmill and 3 interval running tests on a human powered treadmill. This treadmill allowed the subjects to quickly reach their running speed while allowing for measurement of distance, speed, and force. During the interval running tests the subjects completed eight 30-second intervals at a hard/fast pace followed by a 90-second walking or light jogging recovery period. During the recovery period, the subjects placed their left hand on 1 of 3 media: the RTX held at 15 degrees C (R), a 15 degrees C standard refrigerant gel pack (P), or nothing at all (C). Although there were differences in core temperature (Tc), subjective heat stress ratings, distance, and power generated between intervals, there were no significant differences (p &lt; 0.05) found between treatments for any of these variables, nor was the interaction effect of interval*treatment found to be significant. Mean distance completed per trial was 717.1 m +/- 124.4 m (R), 724.8 m +/- 130.3 m (P), and 728.6 m +/- 110.6 m (C). Change in Tc from baseline to end-test averaged 1.41 degrees C +/- 0.37 degrees C (R), 1.41 degrees C +/- 0.39 degrees C (P), and 1.41 degrees C +/- 0.59 degrees C (C). There were no significant differences (p &lt; 0.05) in Tc, heart rate (HR), or VO2 between intervals or treatments. We conclude that the RTX, in its current iteration, is ineffective at improving performance and/or mitigating thermal stress during high-intensity intermittent exercise.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1519/JSC.0b013e3181b1f6a7</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Exclusion reason: Not post-cooling; Aaron Bach (2023-03-19 16:28:26)(Select): Cooling applied before Tc &gt;38 and continued working throughout; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-08 17:58:04)(Select): Amb Cond: thermoneutral 21°C 30-50%
Tc: pill
Ex Cond: incremental sprinting/jog/walking protocol
Cooling Cond: control, ice packs (15°C)
Note: cooling took place during recovery period which was walking/jogging; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2666-2672</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">23</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>92</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cooling Capacity of Transpulmonary Cooling and Cold-Water Immersion After Exercise-Induced Hyperthermia.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Athletic Training (Allen Press)</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Context: Cold-water immersion (CWI) may not be feasible in some remote settings, prompting the identification of alternative cooling methods as adjunct treatment modalities for exertional heat stroke (EHS). Objective: To determine the differences in cooling capacities between CWI and the inhalation of cooled air. Design: Randomized controlled clinical trial. Setting: Laboratory. Patients or Other Participants: A total of 12 recreationally active participants (7 men, 5 women; age = 26 6 4 years, height = 170.6 6 10.1 cm, mass = 76.0 6 18.0 kg, body fat = 18.5% 6 9.7%, peak oxygen uptake = 42.7 6 8.9 mLkg-1 min-1 ). Intervention(s): After exercise in a hot environment (408C and 40% relative humidity), participants were randomized to 3 cooling conditions: cooling during passive rest (PASS; control), CWI, and the Polar Breeze thermal rehabilitation machine (PB) with which participants inspired cooled air (22.28C 6 1.08C). Main Outcome Measure(s): Rectal temperature (TREC) and heart rate were continuously measured throughout cooling until TREC reached 38.258C. Results: Cooling rates during CWI (0.188Cmin-1 6 0.068Cmin-1 ) were greater than those during PASS (mean difference [95% CI] of 0.168Cmin-1 [0.138Cmin--1, 0.198Cmin-1 ]; P, .001) and PB (0.158Cmin-1 [0.128Cmin-1 , 0.168Cmin-1 ]; P, .001). Elapsed time to reach a TREC of 38.258C was also faster with CWI (9.71 6 3.30 minutes) than PASS (58.1 minutes [77.1, 39.9 minutes]; P, .001) and PB (46.8 minutes [65.5, 28.2 minutes]; P, .001). Differences in cooling rates and time to reach a TREC of 38.258C between PASS and PB were not different (P . .05). Conclusions: Transpulmonary cooling via cooled-air inhalation did not promote an optimal cooling rate (.0.158Cmin-1 ) for the successful treatment of EHS. In remote settings where EHS is a risk, access and use of treatment methods via CWI or cold-water dousing are imperative to ensuring survival.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.4085/1062-6050-0146.20</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Exclusion reason: Not practical cooling intervention; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-07 17:37:33)(Select): EXCLUDE - no at home cooling method

Ambient Cond: hot, dry
Exercise: incline walk/jog, 3x 20 min interval
Tc @ exercise completion: 39.83, 39.72, 39.86
Cooling Cond: passive (40,40%), cool air breathing device, CWI (1.5°C); </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">383-388</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">56</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>93</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effect of a Cooling Kit on Physiology and Performance Following Exercise in the Heat.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Journal of Sport Rehabilitation</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Context: Exercising in the heat leads to an increase in body temperature that can increase the risk of heat illness or cause detriments in exercise performance. Objective: To examine a phase change heat emergency kit (HEK) on thermoregulatory and perceptual responses and subsequent exercise performance following exercise in the heat. Design: Two randomized crossover trials that consisted of 30 minutes of exercise, 15 minutes of treatment (T1), performance testing (5-10-5 pro-agility test and 1500-m run), and another 15 minutes of treatment (T2) identical to T1. Setting: Outdoors in the heat (wet-bulb globe temperature: 31.5°C [1.8°C] and relative humidity: 59.0% [5.6%]). Participants: Twenty-six (13 men and 13 women) individuals (aged 20–27 y). Interventions: Treatment was performed with HEK and without HEK (control, CON) modality. Main Outcome Measures: Gastrointestinal temperature, mean skin temperature, thirst sensation, and muscle pain. Results: Maximum gastrointestinal temperature following exercise and performance was not different between trials (P &gt;.05). Cooling rate was faster during T1 CON (0.053°C/min [0.049°C/min]) compared with HEK (0.043°C/min [0.032°C/min]; P =.01). Mean skin temperature was lower in HEK during T1 (P &lt;.001) and T2 (P =.05). T2 thirst was lower in CON (P =.02). Muscle pain was lower in HEK in T2 (P =.03). Performance was not altered (P &gt;.05). Conclusions: HEK improved perception but did not enhance cooling or performance following exercise in the heat. HEK is therefore not recommended to facilitate recovery, treat hyperthermia, or improve performance.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1123/jsr.2016-0116</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Exclusion reason: Not practical cooling intervention; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 12:12:45)(Select): Amb Cond: outdoors 32°C 53% / 31°C 63%
Ex Cond: 30 min self paced frisbee/soccer then 15 min cooling
Cooling Cond: use of heat emergency kit (PCM clothing ensemble) and control (lying down) all cond occurred in the shade
Tc: pill

Note: heat emergency kit is not considered practical cooling method
 ; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">413-418</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">27</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>94</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Air-conditioned benches lower core temperature faster than traditional benches in exercising athletes.</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Clinical Journal of Sport Medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Exclusion reason: No full-text; Aaron Bach (2023-03-12 17:30:19)(Select): No full-text; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">185-185</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">18</style></volume></record><record><database name="EndNote.enl" path="c:\EndNote.enl">EndNote.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="16.0">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>95</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="s55prpsswfsepue0xz25pxai2p909xtzszzv">undefined</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Report">27</ref-type><contributors><authors></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Physiological and subjective responses to cooling devices on firefighting protective clothing</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">European Journal of Applied Physiology</style></secondary-title></titles><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The aim of the present study was to examine the effectiveness of ice-packs (ICE) and phase change material (PCM) cooling devices in reducing physiological load based on subjects&apos; physiological and subjective responses while the subjects exercised on a bicycle ergometer while wearing firefighting protective clothing in a relatively high temperature environment (30°C, 50%RH). Subjects were eight graduate students, aged 25.9 years (SD 3.2). Each subject participated in four 50-min exposures: control (CON), ICE, PCM of 5°C [PCM(5)] and 20°C [PCM(20)]. Each subject rested in a pre-test room for 10 min before entering the test-room where they rested for another 10 min, followed by 30 min-exercise and a 10 min-recovery period. The exercise intensity was set at 55%VO2max. Cooling effects were evaluated by measuring rectal temperature (Tre), mean skin temperature (Tsk), body weight loss and subjective responses. An increase in Tre for PCM(5) and PCM(20) which was less than that for CON and ICE was observed. The increases in Tsk were depressed using cooling devices, but the cooling effects of PCMs were greater than ICE. The subjects with CON felt hotter and wetter than those in the other conditions. The larger surface cooling area, higher melting temperature and softer material of PCMs which reduces absorption capacity caused a decrease in Tre and Tsk for PCM(5) and PCM(20) which was more than that for CON and ICE. Furthermore, PCM(20) does not require refrigeration. These results suggest that PCM(20) is more effective than other cooling devices in reducing the physiological load while wearing firefighting protective clothing. © Springer-Verlag 2008.</style></abstract><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1007/s00421-007-0665-7</style></electronic-resource-num><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Exclusion reason: Not practical cooling intervention; Kate Hutchins (2023-03-16 10:49:23)(Select): Cooling Cond: no cooling (control), ice packs inserted in to mesh vest, PCM packs inserted into mesh vest
Ex Cond: cycling in firefighting ensemble
Tc: rectal

NOTE: ice and PCM packs not considered practical cooling method + per-cooling protocol; </style></notes><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">369-374</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">104</style></volume></record></records></xml>