<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><xml><records><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>340</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">340</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Baudard, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Yavchitz, A.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ravaud, P.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Perrodeau, E.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Boutron, I.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Université Paris Descartes, Sorbonne Paris Cité, Paris, France.&#xD;Centre de Recherche Epidémiologie et Statistique, INSERM U1153, Paris, France.&#xD;Université Paris Descartes, Sorbonne Paris Cité, Paris, France amelie.yavchitz@aphp.fr.&#xD;Cochrane France, Paris, France.&#xD;Centre d&apos;Épidémiologie Clinique, Hôpital Hôtel-Dieu, Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris, 75004 Paris, France.&#xD;Department of Epidemiology, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University, New York, NY, USA.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Impact of searching clinical trial registries in systematic reviews of pharmaceutical treatments: methodological systematic review and reanalysis of meta-analyses</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Bmj</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Bmj</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">j448</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">356</style></volume><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2017/02/19</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Databases, Pharmaceutical</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Meta-Analysis as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Randomized Controlled Trials as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Registries</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2017</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Feb 17</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">0959-8138 (Print)&#xD;0959-8138</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">28213479</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Objective To evaluate the impact of searching clinical trial registries in systematic reviews.Design Methodological systematic review and reanalyses of meta-analyses.Data sources Medline was searched to identify systematic reviews of randomised controlled trials (RCTs) assessing pharmaceutical treatments published between June 2014 and January 2015. For all systematic reviews that did not report a trial registry search but reported the information to perform it, the World Health Organization International Trials Registry Platform (WHO ICTRP search portal) was searched for completed or terminated RCTs not originally included in the systematic review.Data extraction For each systematic review, two researchers independently extracted the outcomes analysed, the number of patients included, and the treatment effect estimated. For each RCT identified, two researchers independently determined whether the results were available (ie, posted, published, or available on the sponsor website) and extracted the data. When additional data were retrieved, we reanalysed meta-analyses and calculated the weight of the additional RCTs and the change in summary statistics by comparison with the original meta-analysis.Results Among 223 selected systematic reviews, 116 (52%) did not report a search of trial registries; 21 of these did not report the information to perform the search (key words, search date). A search was performed for 95 systematic reviews; for 54 (57%), no additional RCTs were found and for 41 (43%) 122 additional RCTs were identified. The search allowed for increasing the number of patients by more than 10% in 19 systematic reviews, 20% in 10, 30% in seven, and 50% in four. Moreover, 63 RCTs had results available; the results for 45 could be included in a meta-analysis. 14 systematic reviews including 45 RCTs were reanalysed. The weight of the additional RCTs in the recalculated meta-analyses ranged from 0% to 58% and was greater than 10% in five of 14 systematic reviews, 20% in three, and 50% in one. The change in summary statistics ranged from 0% to 29% and was greater than 10% for five of 14 systematic reviews and greater than 20% for two. However, none of the changes to summary effect estimates led to a qualitative change in the interpretation of the results once the new trials were added.Conclusions Trial registries are an important source for identifying additional RCTs. The additional number of RCTs and patients included if a search were performed varied across systematic reviews.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1756-1833&#xD;Baudard, Marie&#xD;Yavchitz, Amélie&#xD;Ravaud, Philippe&#xD;Perrodeau, Elodie&#xD;Boutron, Isabelle&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Review&#xD;Systematic Review&#xD;BMJ. 2017 Feb 17;356:j448. doi: 10.1136/bmj.j448.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC5421496 www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf and declare: no support from any organisation for the submitted work; no financial relationships with any organisations that might have an interest in the submitted work in the previous three years; no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</style></custom2><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1136/bmj.j448</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>643</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">643</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Boeker, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Vach, W.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Motschall, E.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Department of Medical Biometry and Medical Informatics, University Medical Center Freiburg, Stefan-Meier-Str, 26, Freiburg i, Br, 79104, Germany. martin.boeker@uniklinik-freiburg.de.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Google Scholar as replacement for systematic literature searches: good relative recall and precision are not enough</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BMC Med Res Methodol</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BMC Med Res Methodol</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">131</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">13</style></volume><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2013/10/29</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Abstracting and Indexing</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Algorithms</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Data Mining/methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Internet</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medline</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Search Engine/*standards</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2013</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Oct 26</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1471-2288</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">24160679</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: Recent research indicates a high recall in Google Scholar searches for systematic reviews. These reports raised high expectations of Google Scholar as a unified and easy to use search interface. However, studies on the coverage of Google Scholar rarely used the search interface in a realistic approach but instead merely checked for the existence of gold standard references. In addition, the severe limitations of the Google Search interface must be taken into consideration when comparing with professional literature retrieval tools.The objectives of this work are to measure the relative recall and precision of searches with Google Scholar under conditions which are derived from structured search procedures conventional in scientific literature retrieval; and to provide an overview of current advantages and disadvantages of the Google Scholar search interface in scientific literature retrieval. METHODS: General and MEDLINE-specific search strategies were retrieved from 14 Cochrane systematic reviews. Cochrane systematic review search strategies were translated to Google Scholar search expression as good as possible under consideration of the original search semantics. The references of the included studies from the Cochrane reviews were checked for their inclusion in the result sets of the Google Scholar searches. Relative recall and precision were calculated. RESULTS: We investigated Cochrane reviews with a number of included references between 11 and 70 with a total of 396 references. The Google Scholar searches resulted in sets between 4,320 and 67,800 and a total of 291,190 hits. The relative recall of the Google Scholar searches had a minimum of 76.2% and a maximum of 100% (7 searches). The precision of the Google Scholar searches had a minimum of 0.05% and a maximum of 0.92%. The overall relative recall for all searches was 92.9%, the overall precision was 0.13%. CONCLUSION: The reported relative recall must be interpreted with care. It is a quality indicator of Google Scholar confined to an experimental setting which is unavailable in systematic retrieval due to the severe limitations of the Google Scholar search interface. Currently, Google Scholar does not provide necessary elements for systematic scientific literature retrieval such as tools for incremental query optimization, export of a large number of references, a visual search builder or a history function. Google Scholar is not ready as a professional searching tool for tasks where structured retrieval methodology is necessary.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1471-2288&#xD;Boeker, Martin&#xD;Vach, Werner&#xD;Motschall, Edith&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t&#xD;BMC Med Res Methodol. 2013 Oct 26;13:131. doi: 10.1186/1471-2288-13-131.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC3840556</style></custom2><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1186/1471-2288-13-131</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>421</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">421</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Bramer, W. M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Giustini, D.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kramer, B. M.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Erasmus MC, University Medical Center Rotterdam, Medical Library, PO Box 2040, 3000 CA, Rotterdam, The Netherlands. w.bramer@erasmusmc.nl.&#xD;The University of British Columbia, UBC Biomedical Branch Library, Gordon and Leslie Diamond Health Care Centre, 2775 Laurel Street, Floor 2, Vancouver, BC, V5Z 1 M9, Canada. dean.giustini@ubc.ca.&#xD;Utrecht University Library, PO Box 80125, 3508 TC, Utrecht, The Netherlands. b.m.r.kramer@uu.nl.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Comparing the coverage, recall, and precision of searches for 120 systematic reviews in Embase, MEDLINE, and Google Scholar: a prospective study</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Syst Rev</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Syst Rev</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">39</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">5</style></volume><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2016/03/05</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Databases, Bibliographic/*standards</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*standards</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medline</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Prospective Studies</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2016</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Mar 1</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2046-4053</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">26932789</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: Previously, we reported on the low recall of Google Scholar (GS) for systematic review (SR) searching. Here, we test our conclusions further in a prospective study by comparing the coverage, recall, and precision of SR search strategies previously performed in Embase, MEDLINE, and GS. METHODS: The original search results from Embase and MEDLINE and the first 1000 results of GS for librarian-mediated SR searches were recorded. Once the inclusion-exclusion process for the resulting SR was complete, search results from all three databases were screened for the SR&apos;s included references. All three databases were then searched post hoc for included references not found in the original search results. RESULTS: We checked 4795 included references from 120 SRs against the original search results. Coverage of GS was high (97.2 %) but marginally lower than Embase and MEDLINE combined (97.5 %). MEDLINE on its own achieved 92.3 % coverage. Total recall of Embase/MEDLINE combined was 81.6 % for all included references, compared to GS at 72.8 % and MEDLINE alone at 72.6 %. However, only 46.4 % of the included references were among the downloadable first 1000 references in GS. When examining data for each SR, the traditional databases&apos; recall was better than GS, even when taking into account included references listed beyond the first 1000 search results. Finally, precision of the first 1000 references of GS is comparable to searches in Embase and MEDLINE combined. CONCLUSIONS: Although overall coverage and recall of GS are high for many searches, the database does not achieve full coverage as some researchers found in previous research. Further, being able to view only the first 1000 records in GS severely reduces its recall percentages. If GS would enable the browsing of records beyond the first 1000, its recall would increase but not sufficiently to be used alone in SR searching. Time needed to screen results would also increase considerably. These results support our assertion that neither GS nor one of the other databases investigated, is on its own, an acceptable database to support systematic review searching.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2046-4053&#xD;Bramer, Wichor M&#xD;Giustini, Dean&#xD;Kramer, Bianca M R&#xD;Comparative Study&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Syst Rev. 2016 Mar 1;5:39. doi: 10.1186/s13643-016-0215-7.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC4772334</style></custom2><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1186/s13643-016-0215-7</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>626</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">626</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Bramer, W. M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Giustini, D.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kramer, B. M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Anderson, P.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Erasmus MC - University Medical Center Rotterdam, Medical Library, PO Box 2040, 3000 CA, Rotterdam, The Netherlands. w.bramer@erasmusmc.nl.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">The comparative recall of Google Scholar versus PubMed in identical searches for biomedical systematic reviews: a review of searches used in systematic reviews</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Syst Rev</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Syst Rev</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">115</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2</style></volume><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2013/12/24</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods/*statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Internet</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PubMed/statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Search Engine/statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Systematic Reviews as Topic</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2013</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Dec 23</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2046-4053</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">24360284</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: The usefulness of Google Scholar (GS) as a bibliographic database for biomedical systematic review (SR) searching is a subject of current interest and debate in research circles. Recent research has suggested GS might even be used alone in SR searching. This assertion is challenged here by testing whether GS can locate all studies included in 21 previously published SRs. Second, it examines the recall of GS, taking into account the maximum number of items that can be viewed, and tests whether more complete searches created by an information specialist will improve recall compared to the searches used in the 21 published SRs. METHODS: The authors identified 21 biomedical SRs that had used GS and PubMed as information sources and reported their use of identical, reproducible search strategies in both databases. These search strategies were rerun in GS and PubMed, and analyzed as to their coverage and recall. Efforts were made to improve searches that underperformed in each database. RESULTS: GS&apos; overall coverage was higher than PubMed (98% versus 91%) and overall recall is higher in GS: 80% of the references included in the 21 SRs were returned by the original searches in GS versus 68% in PubMed. Only 72% of the included references could be used as they were listed among the first 1,000 hits (the maximum number shown). Practical precision (the number of included references retrieved in the first 1,000, divided by 1,000) was on average 1.9%, which is only slightly lower than in other published SRs. Improving searches with the lowest recall resulted in an increase in recall from 48% to 66% in GS and, in PubMed, from 60% to 85%. CONCLUSIONS: Although its coverage and precision are acceptable, GS, because of its incomplete recall, should not be used as a single source in SR searching. A specialized, curated medical database such as PubMed provides experienced searchers with tools and functionality that help improve recall, and numerous options in order to optimize precision. Searches for SRs should be performed by experienced searchers creating searches that maximize recall for as many databases as deemed necessary by the search expert.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2046-4053&#xD;Bramer, Wichor M&#xD;Giustini, Dean&#xD;Kramer, Bianca Mr&#xD;Anderson, Pf&#xD;Comparative Study&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Syst Rev. 2013 Dec 23;2:115. doi: 10.1186/2046-4053-2-115.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC3882110</style></custom2><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1186/2046-4053-2-115</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>278</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">278</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Brueton, V.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Tierney, J. F.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Stenning, S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Rait, G.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Florence Nightingale Faculty of Nursing and Midwifery, Department of Adult Nursing, King&apos;s College London, 57 Waterloo Road, London, SE1 8WA, United Kingdom. valerie.brueton@kcl.ac.uk.&#xD;MRC Clinical Trials Unit at UCL, Aviation House, 125 Kingsway, London, WC2B 6NH, United Kingdom.&#xD;PRIMENT Clinical Trials Unit, Research Department of Primary Care and Population Health, Royal Free and University College Medical School, Rowland Hill Street, London, NW3 2PF, United Kingdom.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Identifying additional studies for a systematic review of retention strategies in randomised controlled trials: making contact with trials units and trial methodologists</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Syst Rev</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Syst Rev</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">167</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">6</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2017/08/24</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Abstracting and Indexing</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Databases, Bibliographic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Information Storage and Retrieval/methods/standards</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Randomized Controlled Trials as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Selection Bias</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Methodology review</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Personal communication</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Searching for methodological research</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Survey</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Systematic review methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Unpublished data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">identifying additional eligible studies to include in a Cochrane systematic review</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">and was conducted in full knowledge of the senior management at the MRC CTU. Consent</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">to participate in the survey was considered given when the CTU key contact replied</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">to the initial email. The Cochrane review contributed to a PhD thesis. Ethics</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">approval for a qualitative study associated with the PhD thesis was sought from the</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">University College London Ethics Committee UCL 2342/002. CONSENT FOR PUBLICATION: No</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">individual person’s data was used for this research. COMPETING INTERESTS: The</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">authors declare that they have no competing interests. PUBLISHER’S NOTE: Springer</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">institutional affiliations.</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2017</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aug 22</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2046-4053</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">28830570</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: Search strategies for systematic reviews aim to identify all evidence relevant to the research question posed. Reports of methodological research can be difficult to find leading to biased results in systematic reviews of research methodology. Evidence suggests that contact with investigators can help to identify unpublished research. To identify additional eligible randomised controlled trials (RCTs) for a Cochrane systematic review of strategies to improve retention in RCTs, we conducted a survey of UK clinical trials units (CTUs) and made contact with RCT methodologists. METHODS: Key contacts for all UK CTUs were sent a personalised email with a short questionnaire and summary protocol of the Cochrane methodology review. The questionnaire asked whether a RCT evaluating strategies to improve retention embedded in a RCT had ever been conducted by the CTU. Questions about the stage of completion and publication of such RCTs were included. The summary protocol outlined the aims, eligibility criteria, examples of types of retention strategies, and the primary outcome for the systematic review. Personal communication with RCT methodologists and presentations of preliminary results of the review at conferences were also used to identify additional eligible RCTs. We checked the results of our standard searches to see if eligible studies identified through these additional methods were also found using our standard searches. RESULTS: We identified 14 of the 38 RCTs included in the Cochrane methodology review by contacting trials units and methodologists. Eleven of the 14 RCTs identified by these methods were either published in grey literature, in press or unpublished. Three remaining RCTs were fully published at the time. Six of the RCTs identified were not found through any other searches. The RCTs identified represented data for 6 of 14 RCTs of incentive strategies (52% of randomised participants included in the review), and 6 of 14 RCTs of communication strategies (52% of randomised participants included in the Cochrane review). Data were unavailable for two of the RCTs identified. CONCLUSIONS: Methodological evaluations embedded in RCTs may be unpublished, published in the grey literature or where published, poorly indexed in bibliographic databases. To identify such studies and minimise selection bias in systematic reviews of methodological evaluations, reviewers should consider contacting CTUs and trial methodologists.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2046-4053&#xD;Brueton, Valerie&#xD;Orcid: 0000-0003-2694-1469&#xD;Tierney, Jayne F&#xD;Stenning, Sally&#xD;Rait, Greta&#xD;MC_EX_UU_G0800814/MRC_/Medical Research Council/United Kingdom&#xD;MC_U122792695/MRC_/Medical Research Council/United Kingdom&#xD;MC_UU_12023/24/MRC_/Medical Research Council/United Kingdom&#xD;PHSRN 30/MRC_/Medical Research Council/United Kingdom&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Review&#xD;Systematic Review&#xD;Syst Rev. 2017 Aug 22;6(1):167. doi: 10.1186/s13643-017-0549-9.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC5568351</style></custom2><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1186/s13643-017-0549-9</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>1</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">1</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Casey, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Raynor, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Jacob, C.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sharp, S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">McFarlane, E.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Services, National Institute for Health and Care Excellence.&#xD;Centre for Guidelines, National Institute for Health and Care Excellence.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Improving the precision of search strategies for guideline surveillance</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Res Synth Methods</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Res Synth Methods</style></full-title></periodical><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2020/09/29</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">databases, bibliographic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">information storage and retrieval</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">search precision</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">search recall</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">search strategy</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2020</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sep 28</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1759-2879</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">32985071</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">INTRODUCTION AND AIM: NICE guideline surveillance determines whether previously published guidelines need updating. The surveillance process must balance time constraints with methodological rigour. It includes a rapid review to identify new evidence to contradict, reinforce or clarify guideline recommendations. Despite this approach, the screening burden can still be high. Applying additional search techniques may increase the precision of the database searches. METHODS: A retrospective analysis was conducted on five surveillance reviews with less than 2% of the studies included after screening. Modified searches were run in MEDLINE, Embase and PsycINFO (where appropriate) to test the impact of additional search techniques: focused subject headings, subheadings, frequency operators and title only searches. Modified searches were compared to original search results to determine: the retrieval of included studies, the precision of the search and the number needed to read. Studies not retrieved by the modified search were checked to determine if the surveillance decision would have been affected. RESULTS: The additional search techniques tested indicated that a combination of focused subject headings and frequency operators could improve the precision of surveillance searches. The modified search retrieved all the original studies included in the surveillance review for three of the reviews tested. Some of the original included studies were not retrieved for two reviews but the missing studies would not have affected the surveillance decision. CONCLUSIONS: Combining focused subject headings and frequency operators is a viable option for improving the precision of surveillance searches without compromising recall and without impacting the surveillance decision. This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1759-2887&#xD;Casey, Monica&#xD;Orcid: 0000-0002-9483-9012&#xD;Raynor, Michael&#xD;Jacob, Catherine&#xD;Sharp, Stephen&#xD;McFarlane, Emma&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;England&#xD;Res Synth Methods. 2020 Sep 28. doi: 10.1002/jrsm.1461.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1002/jrsm.1461</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>559</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">559</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Choong, M. K.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Galgani, F.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Dunn, A. G.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Tsafnat, G.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Centre for Health Informatics, Australian Institute of Health Innovation, University of New South Wales, Kensington NSW, Australia.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Automatic evidence retrieval for systematic reviews</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Med Internet Res</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Med Internet Res</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">e223</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">16</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2014/10/03</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Databases, Factual</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Evidence-Based Medicine</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medical Informatics/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Registries</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">information storage and retrieval</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">medical informatics</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2014</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Oct 1</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1439-4456 (Print)&#xD;1438-8871</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">25274020</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: Snowballing involves recursively pursuing relevant references cited in the retrieved literature and adding them to the search results. Snowballing is an alternative approach to discover additional evidence that was not retrieved through conventional search. Snowballing&apos;s effectiveness makes it best practice in systematic reviews despite being time-consuming and tedious. OBJECTIVE: Our goal was to evaluate an automatic method for citation snowballing&apos;s capacity to identify and retrieve the full text and/or abstracts of cited articles. METHODS: Using 20 review articles that contained 949 citations to journal or conference articles, we manually searched Microsoft Academic Search (MAS) and identified 78.0% (740/949) of the cited articles that were present in the database. We compared the performance of the automatic citation snowballing method against the results of this manual search, measuring precision, recall, and F1 score. RESULTS: The automatic method was able to correctly identify 633 (as proportion of included citations: recall=66.7%, F1 score=79.3%; as proportion of citations in MAS: recall=85.5%, F1 score=91.2%) of citations with high precision (97.7%), and retrieved the full text or abstract for 490 (recall=82.9%, precision=92.1%, F1 score=87.3%) of the 633 correctly retrieved citations. CONCLUSIONS: The proposed method for automatic citation snowballing is accurate and is capable of obtaining the full texts or abstracts for a substantial proportion of the scholarly citations in review articles. By automating the process of citation snowballing, it may be possible to reduce the time and effort of common evidence surveillance tasks such as keeping trial registries up to date and conducting systematic reviews.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1438-8871&#xD;Choong, Miew Keen&#xD;Orcid: 0000-0003-0352-5585&#xD;Galgani, Filippo&#xD;Orcid: 0000-0002-3553-3611&#xD;Dunn, Adam G&#xD;Orcid: 0000-0002-1720-8209&#xD;Tsafnat, Guy&#xD;Orcid: 0000-0003-4353-2026&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t&#xD;J Med Internet Res. 2014 Oct 1;16(10):e223. doi: 10.2196/jmir.3369.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC4211030</style></custom2><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.2196/jmir.3369</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>19</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">19</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Clark, J. M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sanders, S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Carter, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Honeyman, D.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cleo, G.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Auld, Y.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Booth, D.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Condron, P.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Dalais, C.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Bateup, S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Linthwaite, B.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">May, N.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Munn, J.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ramsay, L.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Rickett, K.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Rutter, C.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Smith, A.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sondergeld, P.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Wallin, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Jones, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Beller, E.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Institute for Evidence-Based Healthcare, Bond University, Robina, Queensland, Australia, jclark@bond.edu.au, https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0133-1613.&#xD;Institute for Evidence-Based Healthcare, Bond University, Robina, Queensland, Australia, ssanders@bond.edu.au.&#xD;Institute for Evidence-Based Healthcare, Bond University, Robina, Queensland, Australia, macarter@bond.edu.au.&#xD;Bond University Library, Bond University, Robina, Queensland, Australia, d_honeyman@hotmail.com.&#xD;Institute for Evidence-Based Healthcare, Bond University, Robina, Queensland, Australia, gcleo@bond.edu.au.&#xD;Gold Coast Health Library Service, Gold Coast University Hospital, Southport, Queensland, Australia, Yvonne.Auld@health.qld.gov.au.&#xD;University Library, University of Newcastle, Callaghan, New South Wales, Australia, debbie.booth@newcastle.edu.au.&#xD;University Library, University of Melbourne, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, p.condron@unimelb.edu.au.&#xD;University Library, University of Queensland, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia, c.dalais@library.uq.edu.au.&#xD;Bond University Library, Bond University, Robina, Queensland, Australia, sbateup@bond.edu.au.&#xD;Bond University Library, Bond University, Robina, Queensland, Australia, blinthwa@bond.edu.au.&#xD;Sturt Library, Flinders University, Adelaide, South Australia, Australia, nikki.may@sa.gov.au.&#xD;Centre for Teaching and Learning, Southern Cross University, Coffs Harbour, New South Wales, Australia, Joanne.Munn@scu.edu.au.&#xD;University Library, Australian Catholic University, Banyo, Queensland, Australia, Lindy.Ramsay@acu.edu.au.&#xD;University Library, University of Queensland, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia, k.rickett@library.uq.edu.au.&#xD;University Library, Queensland University of Technology, Kelvin Grove, Queensland, Australia, c.rutter@qut.edu.au.&#xD;Hunter New England Health Libraries, New South Wales (NSW) Health, Hunter Region, New South Wales, Australia, Angela.Smith@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au.&#xD;University Library, Queensland University of Technology, Kelvin Grove, Queensland, Australia, p.sondergeld@qut.edu.au.&#xD;University Library, Southern Cross University, Coffs Harbour, New South Wales, Australia, jam232@gmail.com.&#xD;Institute for Evidence-Based Healthcare, Bond University, Robina, Queensland, Australia, majones@bond.edu.au.&#xD;Institute for Evidence-Based Healthcare, Bond University, Robina, Queensland, Australia, ebeller@bond.edu.au.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Improving the translation of search strategies using the Polyglot Search Translator: a randomized controlled trial</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Med Libr Assoc</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Med Libr Assoc</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">195-207</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">108</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2020/04/08</style></edition><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2020</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Apr</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1536-5050 (Print)&#xD;1536-5050</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">32256231</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: Searching for studies to include in a systematic review (SR) is a time- and labor-intensive process with searches of multiple databases recommended. To reduce the time spent translating search strings across databases, a tool called the Polyglot Search Translator (PST) was developed. The authors evaluated whether using the PST as a search translation aid reduces the time required to translate search strings without increasing errors. METHODS: In a randomized trial, twenty participants were randomly allocated ten database search strings and then randomly assigned to translate five with the assistance of the PST (PST-A method) and five without the assistance of the PST (manual method). We compared the time taken to translate search strings, the number of errors made, and how close the number of references retrieved by a translated search was to the number retrieved by a reference standard translation. RESULTS: Sixteen participants performed 174 translations using the PST-A method and 192 translations using the manual method. The mean time taken to translate a search string with the PST-A method was 31 minutes versus 45 minutes by the manual method (mean difference: 14 minutes). The mean number of errors made per translation by the PST-A method was 8.6 versus 14.6 by the manual method. Large variation in the number of references retrieved makes results for this outcome inconclusive, although the number of references retrieved by the PST-A method was closer to the reference standard translation than the manual method. CONCLUSION: When used to assist with translating search strings across databases, the PST can increase the speed of translation without increasing errors. Errors in search translations can still be a problem, and search specialists should be aware of this.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1558-9439&#xD;Clark, Justin Michael&#xD;Sanders, Sharon&#xD;Carter, Matthew&#xD;Honeyman, David&#xD;Cleo, Gina&#xD;Auld, Yvonne&#xD;Booth, Debbie&#xD;Condron, Patrick&#xD;Dalais, Christine&#xD;Bateup, Sarah&#xD;Linthwaite, Bronwyn&#xD;May, Nikki&#xD;Munn, Jo&#xD;Ramsay, Lindy&#xD;Rickett, Kirsty&#xD;Rutter, Cameron&#xD;Smith, Angela&#xD;Sondergeld, Peter&#xD;Wallin, Margie&#xD;Jones, Mark&#xD;Beller, Elaine&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;J Med Libr Assoc. 2020 Apr;108(2):195-207. doi: 10.5195/jmla.2020.834. Epub 2020 Apr 1.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC7069833 developing the Polyglot Search Translator from the Australian Library Information Association. All other authors declare that they have no other competing interests.</style></custom2><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.5195/jmla.2020.834</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>1154</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">1154</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Clark, O. A.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Castro, A. A.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Instituto do Radium, Campinas, São Paulo, Brazil. clark@evidencias.com</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Searching the Literatura Latino Americana e do Caribe em Ciências da Saúde (LILACS) database improves systematic reviews</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Int J Epidemiol</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Int J Epidemiol</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">112-4</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">31</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2002/03/27</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Caribbean Region</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Databases, Bibliographic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Latin America</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Meta-Analysis as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2002</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Feb</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">0300-5771 (Print)&#xD;0300-5771</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">11914305</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: An unbiased systematic review (SR) should analyse as many articles as possible in order to provide the best evidence available. However, many SR use only databases with high English-language content as sources for articles. Literatura Latino Americana e do Caribe em Ciências da Saúde (LILACS) indexes 670 journals from the Latin American and Caribbean health literature but is seldom used in these SR. Our objective is to evaluate if LILACS should be used as a routine source of articles for SR. METHODS: First we identified SR published in 1997 in five medical journals with a high impact factor. Then we searched LILACS for articles that could match the inclusion criteria of these SR. We also checked if the authors had already identified these articles located in LILACS. RESULTS: In all, 64 SR were identified. Two had already searched LILACS and were excluded. In 39 of 62 (63%) SR a LILACS search identified articles that matched the inclusion criteria. In 5 (8%) our search was inconclusive and in 18 (29%) no articles were found in LILACS. Therefore, in 71% (44/72) of cases, a LILACS search could have been useful to the authors. This proportion remains the same if we consider only the 37 SR that performed a meta-analysis. In only one case had the article identified in LILACS already been located elsewhere by the authors&apos; strategy. CONCLUSION: LILACS is an under-explored and unique source of articles whose use can improve the quality of systematic reviews. This database should be used as a routine source to identify studies for systematic reviews.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Clark, Otavio Augusto Camara&#xD;Castro, Aldemar Araujo&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t&#xD;England&#xD;Int J Epidemiol. 2002 Feb;31(1):112-4. doi: 10.1093/ije/31.1.112.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1093/ije/31.1.112</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>1059</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">1059</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Crumley, E. T.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Wiebe, N.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cramer, K.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Klassen, T. P.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Hartling, L.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">HealthInfo &amp; Searching Practice Inc., Edmonton, Canada. ecrumley@telus.net</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Which resources should be used to identify RCT/CCTs for systematic reviews: a systematic review</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BMC Med Res Methodol</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BMC Med Res Methodol</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">24</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">5</style></volume><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2005/08/12</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Databases, Bibliographic/*standards/statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Guidelines as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Services/standards/statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Meta-Analysis as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Periodicals as Topic/*standards</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Randomized Controlled Trials as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Registries/*standards</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2005</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aug 10</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1471-2288</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">16092960</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: Systematic reviewers seek to comprehensively search for relevant studies and summarize these to present the most valid estimate of intervention effectiveness. The more resources searched, the higher the yield, and thus time and costs required to conduct a systematic review. While there is an abundance of evidence to suggest how extensive a search for randomized controlled trials (RCTs) should be, it is neither conclusive nor consistent. This systematic review was conducted in order to assess the value of different resources to identify trials for inclusion in systematic reviews. METHODS: Seven electronic databases, four journals and Cochrane Colloquia were searched. Key authors were contacted and references of relevant articles screened. Included studies compared two or more sources to find RCTs or controlled clinical trials (CCTs). A checklist was developed and applied to assess quality of reporting. Data were extracted by one reviewer and checked by a second. Medians and ranges for precision and recall were calculated; results were grouped by comparison. Meta-analysis was not performed due to large heterogeneity. Subgroup analyses were conducted for: search strategy (Cochrane, Simple, Complex, Index), expertise of the searcher (Cochrane, librarian, non-librarian), and study design (RCT and CCT). RESULTS: Sixty-four studies representing 13 electronic databases met inclusion criteria. The most common comparisons were MEDLINE vs. handsearching (n = 23), MEDLINE vs. MEDLINE+handsearching (n = 13), and MEDLINE vs. reference standard (n = 13). Quality was low, particularly for the reporting of study selection methodology. Overall, recall and precision varied substantially by comparison and ranged from 0 to 100% and 0 to 99%, respectively. The trial registries performed the best with median recall of 89% (range 84, 95) and median precision of 96.5% (96, 97), although these results are based on a small number of studies. Inadequate or inappropriate indexing was the reason most cited for missing studies. Complex and Cochrane search strategies (SS) performed better than Simple SS. CONCLUSION: Multiple-source comprehensive searches are necessary to identify all RCTs for a systematic review, although indexing needs to be improved. Although trial registries demonstrated the highest recall and precision, the Cochrane SS or a Complex SS in consultation with a librarian are recommended. Continued efforts to develop CENTRAL should be supported.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1471-2288&#xD;Crumley, Ellen T&#xD;Wiebe, Natasha&#xD;Cramer, Kristie&#xD;Klassen, Terry P&#xD;Hartling, Lisa&#xD;Comparative Study&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t&#xD;Review&#xD;Systematic Review&#xD;BMC Med Res Methodol. 2005 Aug 10;5:24. doi: 10.1186/1471-2288-5-24.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC1232852</style></custom2><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1186/1471-2288-5-24</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>1054</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">1054</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Day, D.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Furlan, A.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Irvin, E.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Bombardier, C.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Institute for Work &amp; Health, Toronto, ON, Canada. dday@iwh.on.ca</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Simplified search strategies were effective in identifying clinical trials of pharmaceuticals and physical modalities</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Clin Epidemiol</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Clin Epidemiol</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">874-81</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">58</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">9</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2005/09/20</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Anti-Inflammatory Agents, Non-Steroidal/therapeutic use</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Arthritis, Rheumatoid/drug therapy</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Back Pain/therapy</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Clinical Trials as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Databases, Bibliographic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Lactones/therapeutic use</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medline</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Musculoskeletal Diseases/drug therapy/*therapy</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Neck Pain/therapy</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sensitivity and Specificity</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sulfones/therapeutic use</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2005</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sep</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">0895-4356 (Print)&#xD;0895-4356</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">16167387</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVES: Assess the efficacy of simplified search strategies and identify the best electronic bibliographic database for clinical trials in the field of musculoskeletal disorders and pain. METHODS: Clinical trials within selected reviews from the Cochrane Back, Musculoskeletal, and PaPaS Review Groups were searched using MEDLINE, EMBASE, CINAHL, and CENTRAL to identify which database included the highest percentage of trials. Simplified search strategies for each review were devised and compared to the original, more complex strategy for sensitivity, specificity and precision. RESULTS: Individually, MEDLINE, and EMBASE included 90 and 89% of the relevant studies respectively, and 94% when combined. CENTRAL contained 87% and CINAHL 31%. Generally, simplified search strategies (two to four lines) had higher specificity than the original strategies (approximately 27 lines). Sensitivity was also high, but varied according to intervention. Super simple search strategies (one to two lines) proved as sensitive, but were slightly less specific, depending on the intervention. Both simple and super simple search strategies were often more precise than the original. CONCLUSION: Simplified search strategies are an effective, efficient way to search for clinical trials. They work best when the intervention is a pharmaceutical or a well-defined physical treatment. Their sensitivity, however, is not adequate for conducting systematic reviews.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Day, Doreen&#xD;Furlan, Andrea&#xD;Irvin, Emma&#xD;Bombardier, Claire&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t&#xD;United States&#xD;J Clin Epidemiol. 2005 Sep;58(9):874-81. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2005.02.005.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2005.02.005</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>365</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">365</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Duffy, S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">de Kock, S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Misso, K.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Noake, C.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ross, J.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Stirk, L.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Supplementary searches of PubMed to improve currency of MEDLINE and MEDLINE In-Process searches via Ovid</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Med Libr Assoc</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Med Libr Assoc</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">309-312</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">104</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">4</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2016/11/09</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Databases, Bibliographic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*medline</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*PubMed</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Time Factors</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Databases, Bibliographic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medline</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medical Subject Headings</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PubMed</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2016</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Oct</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1536-5050 (Print)&#xD;1536-5050</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">27822154</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">OBJECTIVE: The research investigated whether conducting a supplementary search of PubMed in addition to the main MEDLINE (Ovid) search for a systematic review is worthwhile and to ascertain whether this PubMed search can be conducted quickly and if it retrieves unique, recently published, and ahead-of-print studies that are subsequently considered for inclusion in the final systematic review. METHODS: Searches of PubMed were conducted after MEDLINE (Ovid) and MEDLINE In-Process (Ovid) searches had been completed for seven recent reviews. The searches were limited to records not in MEDLINE or MEDLINE In-Process (Ovid). RESULTS: Additional unique records were identified for all of the investigated reviews. Search strategies were adapted quickly to run in PubMed, and reviewer screening of the results was not time consuming. For each of the investigated reviews, studies were ordered for full screening; in six cases, studies retrieved from the supplementary PubMed searches were included in the final systematic review. CONCLUSION: Supplementary searching of PubMed for studies unavailable elsewhere is worthwhile and improves the currency of the systematic reviews.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1558-9439&#xD;Duffy, Steven&#xD;de Kock, Shelley&#xD;Misso, Kate&#xD;Noake, Caro&#xD;Ross, Janine&#xD;Stirk, Lisa&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;J Med Libr Assoc. 2016 Oct;104(4):309-312. doi: 10.3163/1536-5050.104.4.011.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC5079494</style></custom2><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.3163/1536-5050.104.4.011</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>6</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">6</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ewald, H.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Klerings, I.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Wagner, G.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Heise, T. L.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Dobrescu, A. I.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Armijo-Olivo, S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Stratil, J. M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Lhachimi, S. K.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Mittermayr, T.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Gartlehner, G.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Nussbaumer-Streit, B.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Hemkens, L. G.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Department of Clinical Research, Basel Institute for Clinical Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University Hospital Basel, University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland; Swiss Tropical and Public Health Institute, Basel, Switzerland; University Medical Library, University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland.&#xD;Cochrane Austria, Department of Evidence-based Medicine and Evaluation, Danube University Krems, Krems, Austria.&#xD;Leibniz Institute for Prevention Research and Epidemiology (BIPS), Bremen, Germany; Institute for Public Health and Nursing Research (IPP), Health Sciences Bremen, University of Bremen, Bremen, Germany.&#xD;Faculty of Rehabilitation Medicine, University of Alberta &amp; Institute of Health Economics, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada; University of Applied Sciences, Faculty of Business and Social Sciences, Osnabrück, Germany.&#xD;Institute for Medical Information Processing, Biometry and Epidemiology, Pettenkofer School of Public Health, LMU Munich, Munich, Germany.&#xD;Ludwig Boltzmann Institute for Health Technology Assessment, Austria.&#xD;Cochrane Austria, Department of Evidence-based Medicine and Evaluation, Danube University Krems, Krems, Austria; RTI International, Research Triangle Park, NC, USA.&#xD;Department of Clinical Research, Basel Institute for Clinical Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University Hospital Basel, University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland. Electronic address: Lars.Hemkens@usb.ch.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Abbreviated and comprehensive literature searches led to identical or very similar effect estimates: a meta-epidemiological study</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Clin Epidemiol</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Clin Epidemiol</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1-12</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">128</style></volume><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2020/08/12</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Bibliographic database</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Meta-epidemiological study</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Precision</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Rapid review</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Search strategy</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Systematic review</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2020</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aug 8</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">0895-4356</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">32781114</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">OBJECTIVES: The objective of this study was to assess the agreement of treatment effect estimates from meta-analyses based on abbreviated or comprehensive literature searches. STUDY DESIGN AND SETTING: This was a meta-epidemiological study. We abbreviated 47 comprehensive Cochrane review searches and searched MEDLINE/Embase/CENTRAL alone, in combination, with/without checking references (658 new searches). We compared one meta-analysis from each review with recalculated ones based on abbreviated searches. RESULTS: The 47 original meta-analyses included 444 trials (median 6 per review [interquartile range (IQR) 3-11]) with 360045 participants (median 1,371 per review [IQR 685-8,041]). Depending on the search approach, abbreviated searches led to identical effect estimates in 34-79% of meta-analyses, to different effect estimates with the same direction and level of statistical significance in 15-51%, and to opposite effects (or effects could not be estimated anymore) in 6-13%. The deviation of effect sizes was zero in 50% of the meta-analyses and in 75% not larger than 1.07-fold. Effect estimates of abbreviated searches were not consistently smaller or larger (median ratio of odds ratio 1 [IQR 1-1.01]) but more imprecise (1.02-1.06-fold larger standard errors). CONCLUSION: Abbreviated literature searches often led to identical or very similar effect estimates as comprehensive searches with slightly increased confidence intervals. Relevant deviations may occur.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1878-5921&#xD;Ewald, Hannah&#xD;Klerings, Irma&#xD;Wagner, Gernot&#xD;Heise, Thomas L&#xD;Dobrescu, Andreea Iulia&#xD;Armijo-Olivo, Susan&#xD;Stratil, Jan M&#xD;Lhachimi, Stefan K&#xD;Mittermayr, Tarquin&#xD;Gartlehner, Gerald&#xD;Nussbaumer-Streit, Barbara&#xD;Hemkens, Lars G&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;United States&#xD;J Clin Epidemiol. 2020 Aug 8;128:1-12. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2020.08.002.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2020.08.002</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>1163</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">1163</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Eysenbach, G.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Tuische, J.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Diepgen, T. L.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Department of Clinical Social Medicine, University of Heidelberg, Germany. ey@yi.com</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Evaluation of the usefulness of Internet searches to identify unpublished clinical trials for systematic reviews</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Med Inform Internet Med</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Med Inform Internet Med</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">203-18</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">26</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">3</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2001/11/15</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Data Collection</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Evidence-Based Medicine</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Germany</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Information Storage and Retrieval</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Internet</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Meta-Analysis as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Pilot Projects</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Publication Bias</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Randomized Controlled Trials as Topic</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2001</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Jul-Sep</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1463-9238 (Print)&#xD;1463-9238</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">11706930</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PRIMARY OBJECTIVE: To avoid selection and publication bias, systematic reviewers should employ a broad range of search techniques and make efforts to locate unpublished studies. We tried to establish whether searches on the World Wide Web (WWW) are useful to identify additional unpublished and ongoing clinical trials. RESEARCH DESIGN: Search strategies seven Cochrane systematic reviews were retrospectively adapted for the WWW in an attempt to find additional randomized controlled trials. METHODS AND PROCEDURES: A search strategy with the general pattern &apos;study methodology NEAR intervention NEAR condition&apos; for the Internet search engine AltaVista was evaluated by measuring search time, recall of Internet searches for published studies; precision (proportion of webpages containing hints to relevant published and unpublished randomized clinical trials); number of additional unpublished or ongoing studies found on the Internet. MAIN OUTCOMES AND RESULTS: We reviewed 429 webpages in 21 hours and found hints to 14 unpublished, ongoing or recently finished trials, at least 9 were considered relevant for 4 systematic reviews. The recall of Internet searches to find references to published studies ranged between 0% and 43.6%, the precision for hints to published or unpublished studies range between 0% and 20.2%. CONCLUSIONS: Information on unpublished and particularly ongoing trials can be found on the Internet. A potential problem is the appraisal of non-peer reviewed electronic publications with questionable quality. More powerful search tools are needed. An &apos;Open Trial Initiative&apos; is proposed to define a syntax for publishing trials on the web and to ensure interoperability of trial registers, so that special search engines can harvest information on ongoing and complete clinical trials.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Eysenbach, G&#xD;Tuische, J&#xD;Diepgen, T L&#xD;Evaluation Study&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;England&#xD;Med Inform Internet Med. 2001 Jul-Sep;26(3):203-18. doi: 10.1080/14639230110075459.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1080/14639230110075459</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>917</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">917</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Freeman, M. K.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Lauderdale, S. A.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kendrach, M. G.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Woolley, T. W.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">McWhorter School of Pharmacy, Samford University, Birmingham, AL 35229, USA. mkelly@samford.edu</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Google Scholar versus PubMed in locating primary literature to answer drug-related questions</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ann Pharmacother</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ann Pharmacother</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">478-84</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">43</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">3</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2009/03/06</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Access to Information</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Databases, Bibliographic/*statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Internet/*statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medical Subject Headings</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Pharmaceutical Preparations</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PubMed/*statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2009</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Mar</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1060-0280</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">19261965</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: Google Scholar linked more visitors to biomedical journal Web sites than did PubMed after the database&apos;s initial release; however, its usefulness in locating primary literature articles is unknown. OBJECTIVE: To assess in both databases the availability of primary literature target articles; total number of citations; availability of free, full-text journal articles; and number of primary literature target articles retrieved by year within the first 100 citations of the search results. METHODS: Drug information question reviews published in The Annals of Pharmacotherapy Drug Information Rounds column served as targets to determine the retrieval ability of Google Scholar and PubMed searches. Reviews printed in this column from January 2006 to June 2007 were eligible for study inclusion. Articles were chosen if at least 2 key words of the printed article were included in the PubMed Medical Subject Heading (MeSH) database, and these terms were searched in both databases. RESULTS: Twenty-two of 33 (67%) eligible Drug Information Rounds articles met the inclusion criteria. The median number of primary literature articles used in each of these articles was 6.5 (IQR 4.8, 8.3; mean +/- SD 8 +/- 5.4). No significant differences were found for the mean number of target primary literature articles located within the first 100 citations in Google Scholar and PubMed searches (5.1 +/- 3.9 vs 5.3 +/- 3.3; p = 0.868). Google Scholar searches located more total results than PubMed (2211.6 +/- 3999.5 vs 44.2 +/- 47.4; p = 0.019). The availability of free, full-text journal articles per Drug Information Rounds article was similar between the databases (1.8 +/- 1.7 vs 2.3 +/- 1.7; p = 0.325). More primary literature articles published prior to 2000 were located with Google Scholar searches compared with PubMed (62.8% vs 34.9%; p = 0.017); however, no statistically significant differences between the databases were observed for articles published after 2000 (66.4 vs 77.1; p = 0.074). CONCLUSIONS: No significant differences were identified in the number of target primary literature articles located between databases. PubMed searches yielded fewer total citations than Google Scholar results; however, PubMed appears to be more specific than Google Scholar for locating relevant primary literature articles.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1542-6270&#xD;Freeman, Maisha Kelly&#xD;Lauderdale, Stacy A&#xD;Kendrach, Michael G&#xD;Woolley, Thomas W&#xD;Comparative Study&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;United States&#xD;Ann Pharmacother. 2009 Mar;43(3):478-84. doi: 10.1345/aph.1L223. Epub 2009 Mar 3.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1345/aph.1L223</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>815</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">815</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Hemens, B. J.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Haynes, R. B.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Department of Clinical Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Health Information Research Unit, CRL-133, McMaster University, 1280 Main Street West, Hamilton L8S 4K1, Ontario, Canada.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">McMaster Premium LiteratUre Service (PLUS) performed well for identifying new studies for updated Cochrane reviews</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Clin Epidemiol</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Clin Epidemiol</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">62-72.e1</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">65</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2011/08/23</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Algorithms</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Databases as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Evidence-Based Medicine</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medline</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Meta-Analysis as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Research Design</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2012</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Jan</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">0895-4356</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">21856121</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">OBJECTIVE: We compared the performance of McMaster Premium LiteratUre Service (PLUS) and Clinical Queries (CQs) to that of the Cochrane Controlled Trials Register, MEDLINE, and EMBASE for locating studies added during an update of reviews. STUDY DESIGN AND SETTING: A sample of new studies in updated Cochrane systematic reviews was used as a reference standard. Searches were performed for each study in each database. Where a new study was not indexed in PLUS, we examined the effect on the review of excluding the study. RESULTS: Ninety-eight updated Cochrane reviews were identified. For the 87 reviews with a usable meta-analysis, PLUS contained all new studies for 13 reviews. No statistically significant difference between PLUS and non-PLUS new studies was found when ratio of odds ratios (RORs) were pooled across 39 reviews (ROR(⊕/⊖): 0.99; 95% confidence interval: 0.87-1.14). Thirty-five updated reviews had no new studies indexed in PLUS, but conclusions were seldom altered by addition of new studies. CONCLUSIONS: PLUS included less than a quarter of the new studies in Cochrane updates, but most reviews appeared unaffected by the omission of these studies. Reviewers should consider adopting PLUS and CQ filters to improve the efficiency of keeping their reviews up to date.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1878-5921&#xD;Hemens, Brian J&#xD;Haynes, R Brian&#xD;FRN86465/Canadian Institutes of Health Research/Canada&#xD;Comparative Study&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t&#xD;United States&#xD;J Clin Epidemiol. 2012 Jan;65(1):62-72.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2011.02.010.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2011.02.010</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>24</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">24</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Janssens, Acjw</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Gwinn, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Brockman, J. E.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Powell, K.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Goodman, M.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Department of Epidemiology, Rollins School of Public Health, Emory University, 1518 Clifton Road NE, Atlanta, GA, 30322, USA. cecile.janssens@emory.edu.&#xD;Department of Epidemiology, Rollins School of Public Health, Emory University, 1518 Clifton Road NE, Atlanta, GA, 30322, USA.&#xD;Woodruff Health Sciences Center Library, Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Novel citation-based search method for scientific literature: a validation study</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BMC Med Res Methodol</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BMC Med Res Methodol</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">25</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">20</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2020/02/08</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Citation</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Co-citation</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Keywords</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Literature search</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Meta-analysis</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Systematic review</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">JEB, KP, MG declare no competing interests.</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2020</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Feb 7</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1471-2288</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">32028894</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: We recently developed CoCites, a citation-based search method that is designed to be more efficient than traditional keyword-based methods. The method begins with identification of one or more highly relevant publications (query articles) and consists of two searches: the co-citation search, which ranks publications on their co-citation frequency with the query articles, and the citation search, which ranks publications on frequency of all citations that cite or are cited by the query articles. METHODS: We aimed to reproduce the literature searches of published systematic reviews and meta-analyses and assess whether CoCites retrieves all eligible articles while screening fewer titles. RESULTS: A total of 250 reviews were included. CoCites retrieved a median of 75% of the articles that were included in the original reviews. The percentage of retrieved articles was higher (88%) when the query articles were cited more frequently and when they had more overlap in their citations. Applying CoCites to only the highest-cited article yielded similar results. The co-citation and citation searches combined were more efficient when the review authors had screened more than 500 titles, but not when they had screened less. CONCLUSIONS: CoCites is an efficient and accurate method for finding relevant related articles. The method uses the expert knowledge of authors to rank related articles, does not depend on keyword selection and requires no special expertise to build search queries. The method is transparent and reproducible.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1471-2288&#xD;Janssens, A Cecile J W&#xD;Orcid: 0000-0002-6153-4976&#xD;Gwinn, Marta&#xD;Brockman, J Elaine&#xD;Powell, Kimberley&#xD;Goodman, Michael&#xD;R01 LM012372/LM/NLM NIH HHS/United States&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural&#xD;BMC Med Res Methodol. 2020 Feb 7;20(1):25. doi: 10.1186/s12874-020-0907-5.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC7006380</style></custom2><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1186/s12874-020-0907-5</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>302</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">302</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Rice, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ali, M. U.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Fitzpatrick-Lewis, D.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Kenny, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Raina, P.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sherifali, D.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">McMaster Evidence Review and Synthesis Centre, McMaster University, 1280 Main St. W., McMaster Innovation Park, Room 207A, Hamilton, Ontario L8S 4K1, Canada; Department of Health Research Methods, Evidence and Impact, Faculty of Health Sciences, McMaster University, Hamilton, Ontario L8L 2X2, Canada.&#xD;McMaster Evidence Review and Synthesis Centre, McMaster University, 1280 Main St. W., McMaster Innovation Park, Room 207A, Hamilton, Ontario L8S 4K1, Canada; School of Nursing, Faculty of Health Sciences, McMaster University, Health Sciences Centre Room HSC-3N25F, 1280 Main Street West, Hamilton, Ontario L8S 4K1, Canada.&#xD;McMaster Evidence Review and Synthesis Centre, McMaster University, 1280 Main St. W., McMaster Innovation Park, Room 207A, Hamilton, Ontario L8S 4K1, Canada; School of Nursing, Faculty of Health Sciences, McMaster University, Health Sciences Centre Room HSC-3N25F, 1280 Main Street West, Hamilton, Ontario L8S 4K1, Canada. Electronic address: dsherif@mcmaster.ca.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Testing the effectiveness of simplified search strategies for updating systematic reviews</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Clin Epidemiol</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Clin Epidemiol</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">148-153</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">88</style></volume><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2017/06/20</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Effective</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Search strategy</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Systematic reviews</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Updating</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2017</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aug</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">0895-4356</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">28625563</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">OBJECTIVE: The objective of the study was to test the overall effectiveness of a simplified search strategy (SSS) for updating systematic reviews. STUDY DESIGN AND METHODS: We identified nine systematic reviews undertaken by our research group for which both comprehensive and SSS updates were performed. Three relevant performance measures were estimated, that is, sensitivity, precision, and number needed to read (NNR). RESULTS: The update reference searches for all nine included systematic reviews identified a total of 55,099 citations that were screened resulting in final inclusion of 163 randomized controlled trials. As compared with reference search, the SSS resulted in 8,239 hits and had a median sensitivity of 83.3%, while precision and NNR were 4.5 times better. During analysis, we found that the SSS performed better for clinically focused topics, with a median sensitivity of 100% and precision and NNR 6 times better than for the reference searches. For broader topics, the sensitivity of the SSS was 80% while precision and NNR were 5.4 times better compared with reference search. CONCLUSION: SSS performed well for clinically focused topics and, with a median sensitivity of 100%, could be a viable alternative to a conventional comprehensive search strategy for updating this type of systematic reviews particularly considering the budget constraints and the volume of new literature being published. For broader topics, 80% sensitivity is likely to be considered too low for a systematic review update in most cases, although it might be acceptable if updating a scoping or rapid review.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1878-5921&#xD;Rice, Maureen&#xD;Ali, Muhammad Usman&#xD;Fitzpatrick-Lewis, Donna&#xD;Kenny, Meghan&#xD;Raina, Parminder&#xD;Sherifali, Diana&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;United States&#xD;J Clin Epidemiol. 2017 Aug;88:148-153. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2017.06.005. Epub 2017 Jun 16.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2017.06.005</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>603</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">603</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Volpato, E. S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Betini, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">El Dib, R.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Testing search strategies for systematic reviews in the Medline literature database through PubMed</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Eval Clin Pract</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Eval Clin Pract</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">117-20</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">20</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2014/04/23</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cross-Sectional Studies</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medline</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PubMed/*organization &amp; administration</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2014</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Apr</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1356-1294</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">24754051</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: A high-quality electronic search is essential in ensuring accuracy and completeness in retrieved records for the conducting of a systematic review. OBJECTIVE: We analysed the available sample of search strategies to identify the best method for searching in Medline through PubMed, considering the use or not of parenthesis, double quotation marks, truncation and use of a simple search or search history. METHODS: In our cross-sectional study of search strategies, we selected and analysed the available searches performed during evidence-based medicine classes and in systematic reviews conducted in the Botucatu Medical School, UNESP, Brazil. RESULTS: We analysed 120 search strategies. With regard to the use of phrase searches with parenthesis, there was no difference between the results with and without parenthesis and simple searches or search history tools in 100% of the sample analysed (P = 1.0). The number of results retrieved by the searches analysed was smaller using double quotations marks and using truncation compared with the standard strategy (P = 0.04 and P = 0.08, respectively). CONCLUSIONS: There is no need to use phrase-searching parenthesis to retrieve studies; however, we recommend the use of double quotation marks when an investigator attempts to retrieve articles in which a term appears to be exactly the same as what was proposed in the search form. Furthermore, we do not recommend the use of truncation in search strategies in the Medline via PubMed. Although the results of simple searches or search history tools were the same, we recommend using the latter.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1365-2753&#xD;Volpato, Enilze S N&#xD;Betini, Marluci&#xD;El Dib, Regina&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t&#xD;England&#xD;J Eval Clin Pract. 2014 Apr;20(2):117-20. doi: 10.1111/jep.12094.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1111/jep.12094</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>229</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">229</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Volpato, E. S. N.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Betini, M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Puga, M. E.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Agarwal, A.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cataneo, A. J. M.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Oliveira, L. D.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Bazan, R.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Braz, L. G.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Pereira, J. E. G.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">El Dib, R.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PhD. Doctoral Student, Postgraduate Program on Anesthesiology, Health Sciences Library, Faculdade de Medicina de Botucatu (FMB), Universidade Estadual Paulista (UNESP), Botucatu (SP), Brazil.&#xD;PhD. Coordinator, Coordenadoria da Rede de Bibliotecas da UNIFESP (CRBU), Universidade Federal de São Paulo (UNIFESP), São Paulo (SP), Brazil.&#xD;Undergraduate Medical Student, School of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada, and Department of Health Research Methods, Evidence and Impact, McMaster University, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada.&#xD;MD, PhD. Full Professor, Department of Surgery and Orthopedics, Faculdade de Medicina de Botucatu, Universidade Estadual Paulista (UNESP), Botucatu (SP), Brazil.&#xD;MSc, PhD. Associate Professor, Department of Biosciences and Oral Diagnosis, Institute of Science and Technology, Universidade Estadual Paulista (UNESP), São José dos Campos (SP), Brazil.&#xD;MD. Assistant Professor, Department of Neurology, Faculdade de Medicina de Botucatu, Universidade Estadual Paulista (UNESP), Botucatu (SP), Brazil.&#xD;MD. Assistant Professor, Department of Anesthesiology, Faculdade de Medicina de Botucatu, Universidade Estadual Paulista (UNESP), Botucatu (SP), Brazil.&#xD;MD. Doctoral Student, Postgraduate Program on Anesthesiology, Faculdade de Medicina de Botucatu, Universidade Estadual Paulista (UNESP), Botucatu (SP), Brazil.&#xD;MSc, PhD. Assistant Professor, Department of Anesthesiology, Faculdade de Medicina de Botucatu, Universidade Estadual Paulista (UNESP), Botucatu (SP), Brazil; Assistant Professor, Department of Biosciences and Oral Diagnosis, Institute of Science and Technology, Universidade Estadual Paulista (UNESP), São José dos Campos (SP), Brazil; and Research Collaborator, Institute of Urology, McMaster University, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Strategies to optimize MEDLINE and EMBASE search strategies for anesthesiology systematic reviews. An experimental study</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sao Paulo Med J</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sao Paulo Med J</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">103-108</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">136</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2018/01/18</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Anesthesiology</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medline</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Search Engine/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Subject Headings</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2018</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Mar-Apr</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1516-3180</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">29340504</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: A high-quality electronic search is essential for ensuring accuracy and comprehensiveness among the records retrieved when conducting systematic reviews. Therefore, we aimed to identify the most efficient method for searching in both MEDLINE (through PubMed) and EMBASE, covering search terms with variant spellings, direct and indirect orders, and associations with MeSH and EMTREE terms (or lack thereof). DESIGN AND SETTING: Experimental study. UNESP, Brazil. METHODS: We selected and analyzed 37 search strategies that had specifically been developed for the field of anesthesiology. These search strategies were adapted in order to cover all potentially relevant search terms, with regard to variant spellings and direct and indirect orders, in the most efficient manner. RESULTS: When the strategies included variant spellings and direct and indirect orders, these adapted versions of the search strategies selected retrieved the same number of search results in MEDLINE (mean of 61.3%) and a higher number in EMBASE (mean of 63.9%) in the sample analyzed. The numbers of results retrieved through the searches analyzed here were not identical with and without associated use of MeSH and EMTREE terms. However, association of these terms from both controlled vocabularies retrieved a larger number of records than did the use of either one of them. CONCLUSIONS: In view of these results, we recommend that the search terms used should include both preferred and non-preferred terms (i.e. variant spellings and direct/indirect order of the same term) and associated MeSH and EMTREE terms, in order to develop highly-sensitive search strategies for systematic reviews.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1806-9460&#xD;Volpato, Enilze de Souza Nogueira&#xD;Orcid: 0000-0002-9796-9402&#xD;Betini, Marluci&#xD;Puga, Maria Eduarda&#xD;Agarwal, Arnav&#xD;Cataneo, Antônio José Maria&#xD;Oliveira, Luciane Dias de&#xD;Bazan, Rodrigo&#xD;Braz, Leandro Gobbo&#xD;Pereira, José Eduardo Guimarães&#xD;El Dib, Regina&#xD;Comparative Study&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Brazil&#xD;Sao Paulo Med J. 2018 Jan 15;136(2):103-108. doi: 10.1590/1516-3180.2017.0277100917. Print 2018 Mar-Apr.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1590/1516-3180.2017.0277100917</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>494</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">494</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Waffenschmidt, S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Guddat, C.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Institute for Quality and Efficiency in Healthcare, Im Mediapark 8, 50670, Cologne, Germany.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Searches for randomized controlled trials of drugs in MEDLINE and EMBASE using only generic drug names compared with searches applied in current practice in systematic reviews</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Res Synth Methods</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Res Synth Methods</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">188-94</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">6</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2015/06/24</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Data Mining/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Databases, Bibliographic/*statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Drug Evaluation</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Drug Labeling/classification/statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Drugs, Generic/*classification</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">MEDLINE/statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Natural Language Processing</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Randomized Controlled Trials as Topic/*statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Vocabulary, Controlled</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">comprehensive literature search for SRs</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">generic drug name</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">information storage and retrieval</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">randomized controlled trials as topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">review literature as topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">search strategy</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2015</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Jun</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1759-2879</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">26099486</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: It is unclear which terms should be included in bibliographic searches for randomized controlled trials (RCTs) of drugs, and identifying relevant drug terms can be extremely laborious. The aim of our analysis was to determine whether a bibliographic search using only the generic drug name produces sufficient results for the generation of informative systematic reviews (SRs). METHODS: We conducted a retrospective analysis of relevant references included in SRs of drugs. We determined the proportion of references identified by a simplified technique consisting of a systematic search for RCTs in MEDLINE and EMBASE via the search interface Ovid and using only the truncated generic drug name in all search fields. We calculated aggregated sensitivity and also evaluated the unidentified references. RESULTS: Forty-eight SRs contained 873 primary publications, of which we found 829 in MEDLINE and 757 in EMBASE (&quot;gold standard&quot;). The simplified search identified 823 of the 829 MEDLINE references (sensitivity 99.3%) and 754 of the 757 EMBASE references (99.6%). Ultimately, only three references could not be found by additional searches. CONCLUSION: Our findings indicate that when searching for RCTs of drugs in MEDLINE and EMBASE, a search using the truncated generic drug name in all fields produces sufficient results.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1759-2887&#xD;Waffenschmidt, Siw&#xD;Guddat, Charlotte&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t&#xD;England&#xD;Res Synth Methods. 2015 Jun;6(2):188-94. doi: 10.1002/jrsm.1138.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1002/jrsm.1138</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>1009</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">1009</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Wong, S. S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Wilczynski, N. L.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Haynes, R. B.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">School of Nutrition, Faculty of Community Services, Ryerson University, 350 Victoria Street, Toronto, Ontario, M5B 2K3 Canada. sharonw@ryerson.ca</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Comparison of top-performing search strategies for detecting clinically sound treatment studies and systematic reviews in MEDLINE and EMBASE</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Med Libr Assoc</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Med Libr Assoc</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">451-5</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">94</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">4</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2006/11/04</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Databases, Bibliographic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods/statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*medline</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medical Subject Headings</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2006</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Oct</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1536-5050 (Print)&#xD;1536-5050</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">17082841</style></accession-num><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1558-9439&#xD;Wong, Sharon S-L&#xD;Wilczynski, Nancy L&#xD;Haynes, R Brian&#xD;R01 LM006866/LM/NLM NIH HHS/United States&#xD;5R01LM06866-04/LM/NLM NIH HHS/United States&#xD;Comparative Study&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural&#xD;J Med Libr Assoc. 2006 Oct;94(4):451-5.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC1629423</style></custom2><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>819</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">819</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Young, S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Duffull, S. B.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">School of Pharmacy, University of Otago, Dunedin, New Zealand.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">A learning-based approach for performing an in-depth literature search using MEDLINE</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Clin Pharm Ther</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Clin Pharm Ther</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">504-12</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">36</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">4</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2011/07/07</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Algorithms</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Evidence-Based Medicine</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">HIV Infections/therapy</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*medline</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medical Subject Headings</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Pharmaceutical Services/organization &amp; administration</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Review Literature as Topic</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2011</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aug</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">0269-4727</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">21729115</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">WHAT IS KNOWN AND OBJECTIVE: Exhaustive literature searching is a core requirement for developing guidelines for evidence-based practice. MEDLINE is typically used. Searching requires the user to identify appropriate search terms, called Medical Subject Headings (MeSH) and refine the search to retrieve relevant articles. The objective of this study was to develop and test a learning algorithm for conducting a thorough literature search. METHODS: A learning algorithm to effectively utilize MeSH terms is presented. This algorithm creates combinations of available MeSH terms from which a search is conducted. The algorithm was applied to search MEDLINE (January 1950 to Janaury 2008) focusing on the impact of pharmaceutical care in HIV-infected patients. The number of relevant articles retrieved from the learning algorithm search was then compared against a static search with a fixed set of keywords implemented by an independent user. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION: The learning algorithm retrieved 1670 articles with six relevant articles identified. The static search retrieved a total of 49 articles, with three being relevant. These three articles were also located from the learning algorithm-based search. WHAT IS KNOWN AND CONCLUSION: Performing a literature search for retrieving evidence-based studies can be a daunting and error-prone process. The introduction of automatic, learning tools for searching is desirable and we present a possible approach.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1365-2710&#xD;Young, S&#xD;Duffull, S B&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t&#xD;England&#xD;J Clin Pharm Ther. 2011 Aug;36(4):504-12. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2710.2010.01204.x. Epub 2010 Oct 26.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1111/j.1365-2710.2010.01204.x</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>855</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">855</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Yousefi-Nooraie, R.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Irani, S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Mortaz-Hedjri, S.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Shakiba, B.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Research Fellow, Center for Academic and Health Policies, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran Researcher, Systematic Review Study Group, Students&apos; Scientific Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran and Resident of Otorhinolaryngology: Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran Researcher, Systematic Review Study Group, Students&apos; Scientific Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Comparison of the efficacy of three PubMed search filters in finding randomized controlled trials to answer clinical questions</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Eval Clin Pract</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">J Eval Clin Pract</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">723-6</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">19</style></volume><number><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">5</style></number><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2010/09/18</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Bibliometrics</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Evidence-Based Medicine/instrumentation/methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods/standards</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*PubMed</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Randomized Controlled Trials as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Reference Standards</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Software/*standards</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PubMed</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">clinical trials</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">precision</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">recall</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">search filters</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2013</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Oct</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1356-1294</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">20846321</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">OBJECTIVE: The aim of this study was to compare the performance of three search methods in the retrieval of relevant clinical trials from PubMed to answer specific clinical questions. METHODS: Included studies of a sample of 100 Cochrane reviews which recorded in PubMed were considered as the reference standard. The search queries were formulated based on the systematic review titles. Precision, recall and number of retrieved records for limiting the results to clinical trial publication type, and using sensitive and specific clinical queries filters were compared. The number of keywords, presence of specific names of intervention and syndrome in the search keywords were used in a model to predict the recalls and precisions. RESULTS: The Clinical queries-sensitive search strategy retrieved the largest number of records (33) and had the highest recall (41.6%) and lowest precision (4.8%). The presence of specific intervention name was the only significant predictor of all recalls and precisions (P = 0.016). CONCLUSION: The recall and precision of combination of simple clinical search queries and methodological search filters to find clinical trials in various subjects were considerably low. The limit field strategy yielded in higher precision and fewer retrieved records and approximately similar recall, compared with the clinical queries-sensitive strategy. Presence of specific intervention name in the search keywords increased both recall and precision.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1365-2753&#xD;Yousefi-Nooraie, Reza&#xD;Irani, Shirin&#xD;Mortaz-Hedjri, Soroush&#xD;Shakiba, Behnam&#xD;Comparative Study&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t&#xD;England&#xD;J Eval Clin Pract. 2013 Oct;19(5):723-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2753.2010.01554.x. Epub 2010 Sep 16.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1111/j.1365-2753.2010.01554.x</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>64</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">64</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Yu, Y.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Xu, E.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Xia, E.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Huang, H.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Hao, B.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Zhang, S.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">IBM Research China, Beijing, China.&#xD;Tsinghua University, Beijing, China.</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">A Method to Accelerate and Visualize Iterative Clinical Paper Searching</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Stud Health Technol Inform</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Stud Health Technol Inform</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1332-1336</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">264</style></volume><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2019/08/24</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cluster Analysis</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Research Personnel</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Bibliometrics</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Literature Based Discovery</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Paper</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2019</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Aug 21</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">0926-9630</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">31438142</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Clinical paper searching is a major task for clinical researchers to collect authoritative and up-to-date evidences to support their research works and clinical practices. Currently, this task needs huge amount of labor work. Researchers usually spend a lot of time searching on the online repository and iterating many times to get the final paper list. Systematic review is a special case, in which the paper searching process is a critical step. To address this challenge, this paper introduces a method to streamline the iterative paper searching process. It automatically selects the most probably matched papers, and then generates new search strategy. All the intermediate results are visualized based on the paper citation graph. It assembles technologies such as PageRank and Topic-based clustering to accelerate the paper searching tasks. The precision, recall, and execution time of the proposed method are then evaluated by comparing with published systematic reviews.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1879-8365&#xD;Yu, Yiqin&#xD;Xu, Enliang&#xD;Xia, Eryu&#xD;Huang, He&#xD;Hao, Bibo&#xD;Zhang, Shilei&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Netherlands&#xD;Stud Health Technol Inform. 2019 Aug 21;264:1332-1336. doi: 10.3233/SHTI190443.</style></notes><urls></urls><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.3233/shti190443</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record><record><database name="Search SR screened results.enl" path="\\staff.ad.bond.edu.au\home\cforbes\Profile\Documents\Search SR screened results.enl">Search SR screened results.enl</database><source-app name="EndNote" version="19.3">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>1030</rec-number><foreign-keys><key app="EN" db-id="d522sr25c5z09be2ff255xtc2vzpasv2pe9t">1030</key></foreign-keys><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Zhang, L.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Ajiferuke, I.</style></author><author><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sampson, M.</style></author></authors></contributors><auth-address><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Natural Sciences Library, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Canada. li.zhang@usask.ca</style></auth-address><titles><title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Optimizing search strategies to identify randomized controlled trials in MEDLINE</style></title><secondary-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BMC Med Res Methodol</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BMC Med Res Methodol</style></full-title></periodical><pages><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">23</style></pages><volume><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">6</style></volume><edition><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2006/05/11</style></edition><keywords><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Abstracting and Indexing</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Cross-Over Studies</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Efficiency</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Humans</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Information Storage and Retrieval/*methods</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">MEDLINE/*statistics &amp; numerical data</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Medical Subject Headings</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Meta-Analysis as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">*Randomized Controlled Trials as Topic</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Reproducibility of Results</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Sensitivity and Specificity</style></keyword><keyword><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Time and Motion Studies</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">2006</style></year><pub-dates><date><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">May 9</style></date></pub-dates></dates><isbn><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1471-2288</style></isbn><accession-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">16684359</style></accession-num><abstract><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">BACKGROUND: The Cochrane Highly Sensitive Search Strategy (HSSS), which contains three phases, is widely used to identify Randomized Controlled Trials (RCTs) in MEDLINE. Lefebvre and Clarke suggest that reviewers might consider using four revisions of the HSSS. The objective of this study is to validate these four revisions: combining the free text terms volunteer, crossover, versus, and the Medical Subject Heading CROSS-OVER STUDIES with the top two phases of the HSSS, respectively. METHODS: We replicated the subject search for 61 Cochrane reviews. The included studies of each review that were indexed in MEDLINE were pooled together by review and then combined with the subject search and each of the four proposed search strategies, the top two phases of the HSSS, and all three phases of the HSSS. These retrievals were used to calculate the sensitivity and precision of each of the six search strategies for each review. RESULTS: Across the 61 reviews, the search term versus combined with the top two phases of the HSSS was able to find 3 more included studies than the top two phases of the HSSS alone, or in combination with any of the other proposed search terms, but at the expense of missing 56 relevant articles that would be found if all three phases of the HSSS were used. The estimated time needed to finish a review is 1086 hours for all three phases of the HSSS, 823 hours for the strategy versus, 818 hours for the first two phases of the HSSS or any of the other three proposed strategies. CONCLUSION: This study shows that compared to the first two phases of the HSSS, adding the term versus to the top two phases of the HSSS balances the sensitivity and precision in the reviews studied here to some extent but the differences are very small. It is well known that missing relevant studies may result in bias in systematic reviews. Reviewers need to weigh the trade-offs when selecting the search strategies for identifying RCTs in MEDLINE.</style></abstract><label><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">Include</style></label><notes><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">1471-2288&#xD;Zhang, Li&#xD;Ajiferuke, Isola&#xD;Sampson, Margaret&#xD;Comparative Study&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t&#xD;BMC Med Res Methodol. 2006 May 9;6:23. doi: 10.1186/1471-2288-6-23.</style></notes><urls></urls><custom2><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">PMC1488863</style></custom2><electronic-resource-num><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">10.1186/1471-2288-6-23</style></electronic-resource-num><remote-database-provider><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">NLM</style></remote-database-provider><language><style face="normal" font="default" size="100%">eng</style></language></record></records></xml>